<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Product | Fiona MacNeill | Macknowlogist</title>
    <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/tags/product/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://fionamacneill.co.uk/tags/product/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Product</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 16:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/media/icon_hu_57d0698421383678.png</url>
      <title>Product</title>
      <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/tags/product/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>LTUX Brighton presents, Talk UX: Redesigning Place</title>
      <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/events/talkux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/events/talkux/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2025, LTUX Brighton hosted the international conference for 
, 
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;talk-ux-stats&#34;&gt;Talk UX Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;188 attendees over 2 days | 151 in-person and 37 online&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20 talks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 workshops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 short film screenings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 panel discussion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;£201 raised for local charity, 
.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-reflection&#34;&gt;Personal Reflection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, Talk UX was one of the most challenging, yet fulfilling experiences of my life. It really warrants it&amp;rsquo;s own blog post, particularly because we tried to make the event as responsible and sustainable as we could. As organisers we considered this in terms of how we organised, resourcing (both in-person and digital), and environmental impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew both in so many ways as a person, as a designer, as a leader, and as a business leader through the experience. I will be forever thankful for the vision, belief, and trust or our organising group and everything we achieved together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This marked the end of my chapter leadership of LTUX Brighton. I&amp;rsquo;m staying on as treasurer as we move into next phase of our development as a group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;TalkUX-organisersonlyv2-170925.webp&#34; alt=&#34;the group of organiser for Talk UX at the front of the main room, in front of a projected image showing the Brighton beach front.&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by Laura Rodriguez&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Left-to-right:&lt;/strong&gt; Inka Howorth, Fiona MacNeill, Heidi Swigon, Lou Carroll, Alex Woodward, Emily Clark, Deeksha Bhushan, Alice Umeji.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;QuietDownThereCharity.webp&#34; alt=&#34;At Harriet&#39;s Press upstairs at the Brighton&#39;s Open Market. Fiona MacNeill and Heidi Swigon are handing a hand drawn cheque to Emily Atkinson from Quiet Down There.&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;**A huge thank you to Quiet Down There for their collaboration. Although we were only able to make a small donation this time, we hope to be able to do more in the future. Our goal was to help raise awareness about the amazing work they do to address hygiene poverty and we successfully did that with Talk UX and through our social media posts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Green Software Practitioner Study Day at Sussex Innovation Centre</title>
      <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/events/greensoftwarestudyday/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/events/greensoftwarestudyday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This event follows on from my 
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I conceived Green Practitioner Study Day as a collaboration between LTUX Brighton and Green Software Brighton. Having previously collaborated on an amazing hackathon in 2024, we knew this could work well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea for the event came to me during a Green Software Brighton meetup evening. Folks at the event mentioned completing the Green Software Foundation and The Linux Foundation&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Green Software Practitioner certificate&lt;/em&gt; which is a free self-study module now available on the 
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I too wanted to complete the certificate, but I found myself wondering if others encountered the same issues I did when it comes to self-paced online learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: it wasn&amp;rsquo;t that the motivation wasn&amp;rsquo;t there, but as a small business owner the time wasn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance&lt;/strong&gt;: in tech noone is an island, we are part of interdisciplinary teams. It seemed to me that the power of this learning could only be unlocked through collaboration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Momentum&lt;/strong&gt;: on that point driving forward sustainability needs multiple champions to gain traction. As a contractor I needed other folks&amp;rsquo; stories to help understand what more I could be doing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journeys&lt;/strong&gt;: I wanted to know that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t alone and that others were also encountering the same barriers that I was. We are on this journey together!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this, I felt called for an in-person experience, by tech folks for tech folks. Where the time was reserved and structured to allow for the completion of the certificate and interdisciplinary disucssion. So, I set about creating an interest page as an experiment, were other people interested in such a day?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought that I would get maybe 12 people to attend. To my surprise, we sold out 27 spaces with a healthy waiting list. We were also given a grant from Brighton &amp;amp; Hove Buses to help defray the costs of the event and provide some free spaces for students and those on limited incomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What an attendee said:&lt;/p&gt;



  
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;border-l-4 border-neutral-300 dark:border-neutral-600 pl-4 italic text-neutral-600 dark:text-neutral-400 my-6&#34;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;…being able to be in a friendly location with a group of people interested in the same subject
matter especially was incredibly, encouraging and helped a lot…I would&amp;rsquo;ve otherwise just spoke about it for ages but not actually managed to execute.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;will-you-join-us-at-the-next-green-practitioner-study-day&#34;&gt;Will you join us at the next Green Practitioner Study Day?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a longer blog post that I need to write about the sustainability of the Study Day itself (it truly was a sustainable workshop!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two further events planned in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Friday, 30th January at WRAP (next to Brighton Station). Details and tickets at the 
.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Friday, 13th March at Plus X. Details and tickets are coming soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;PledgeCardsGreenStudyDay060825.webp&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34; alt=&#34;Three mini playcard sized whiteboards on a table with messages written in erasable pen.&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pledge cards from the end of the event - using the mini-reusable whiteboards that I created for the Study Day which have now become a fixture at almost all my workshops. The three cards read, &amp;ldquo;Start doing: At 1st stage, consider carbon impact of anythng I work on; Keep doing: expanding my knowledge, learn ways to improve practice; Stop doing: being thoughtless about consumption. Thank you to Deeksha Bhushan for giving me permission to use this photo.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
