<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ux | Fiona MacNeill Portfolio and Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/ux/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/ux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Ux</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2022 18:21:29 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu4186623227307172452.png</url>
      <title>Ux</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/ux/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>UX Brighton 2022 - 4th November</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2022 18:21:29 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brilliant-return-of-ux-brighton&#34;&gt;The brilliant return of UX Brighton&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UX Brighton, a mainstay of the Brighton UX community returned on 4th of November after a 2-year hiatus. This year&amp;rsquo;s event focused on UX and Product Management. I have been reflecting on this intersection both personally and professionally of late and outline my thoughts below. Some thoughts are fledgling, some are fully formed, some I may revisit, some I may abandon later.
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-according-to-one-of-my-sketchbooks-2020-and-2021-never-happened&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Two pages in a sketchbook showing the back of a conference name badge, displaying the schedule. One is for 2020 and one is for 2022.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/images/SketchbookHiatus051122UXBri_hu10231105725610361248.webp 400w,
               /post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/images/SketchbookHiatus051122UXBri_hu12041081289063751725.webp 760w,
               /post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/images/SketchbookHiatus051122UXBri_hu1819990805462986231.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/images/SketchbookHiatus051122UXBri_hu10231105725610361248.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      According to one of my sketchbooks 2020 and 2021 never happened.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-level-of-a-problem&#34;&gt;The level of a problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Products solve customer&amp;rsquo;s problems or as I prefer to term it products provide a means for customers to get the thing that they want to do, done (props to &lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2016/09/know-your-customers-jobs-to-be-done&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Christensen &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as this is blatantly inspired by Jobs-to-be-Done). So a product should represent an innovation in that it makes that thing they want to do quicker, or easier, or safer, or cheaper, or some combination of the former. But what about once that product exists? It needs to mature and respond to the way the customers change, their contexts change, or the thing that they are trying to do change. These are internal problems for the product to address within itself so that it might carry on solving the high-level problem for the most customers and also gain new customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;when-a-product-stops-solving-a-problem&#34;&gt;When a product stops solving a problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am in the process of moving away from Evernote. As a committed customer for many years it used to be my brain outside my brain. Was it the lack of new features that pushed me away? No, although I am intrigued by the promise of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transclusion&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;transclusion&lt;/a&gt; and interconnection between thoughts and ideas, I was still mostly happy with it. Ultimately, what pushed me away were the little cracks in functionality; the five times duplicated note, the slow load times, the indexing failures. My trust was broken, just like an unreliable human relationship it was the little things which set off alarm bells. As a seasoned technologist, these tell-tale signs of an unloved product get me packing my bags. To the point where my bags are packed before I&amp;rsquo;ll even adopt a product these days (&lt;em&gt;shakes head&lt;/em&gt; at proprietary file formats). No escape plan, no deal. This is what comes from years of being the person charged with saving other people&amp;rsquo;s data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;defining-a-problem&#34;&gt;Defining a problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it would be more accurate to say defining the definition of a product-problem. In UX a problem might be at a micro level as in a specific process or interaction is failing, e.g., I cannot buy the replacement fridge-freezer I need due to an issue with one part of the payment workflow on a popular UK-based vendor&amp;rsquo;s website (true story). At a product level, if that website were a product and it&amp;rsquo;s primary purpose was to enable the successful sale of fridges then that product has failed. So UX problems can be product problems. So, is it more about the lens by which we see these problems? Could it be that the product manager owns a collection of problems across the product&amp;rsquo;s development cycle and the UXer owns their problems as a subset of that. I think that is how I interpret it as someone outside that particular domain, yet also identifying with it. My products are learning experiences, when they are successful they result in the subsequent adoption of desired behaviours. If the means of product delivery in terms of suitability, usability, accessibility, availability, reliability, and robustness fails, then my product also fails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;defining-a-collection-of-problems&#34;&gt;Defining a collection of problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problems do not exist in a vacuum and are often symptomatic of bigger issues. So, acknowledging the breadth and distribution of problems and then identifying which are the most important and impactful to address is essential. This theme arose in both Janna Bastow&amp;rsquo;s and Matt LeMay&amp;rsquo;s talks. Deciding what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; most important relies on research and analysis based on having access to a variety of information sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also clear that a collection of problems derive from and are influenced by multiple domains within a business. So this is where the connections between business strategy, product strategy, and UX strategy converge. Jaime Levy&amp;rsquo;s excellent book on &lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.eu/d/8oLQ7QC&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UX Strategy&lt;/a&gt; was referenced by speaker, Alison Rawlings. A profoundly influential book during my years in graduate school. This was where I learned about business research staples such as competitor analyses, a method I still use frequently today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How did someone else solve this problem? Was the outcome a new product, or a collection of approaches working alongside a product (more like a service)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;defining-plans-to-address-each-problem-in-your-collection&#34;&gt;Defining plans to address each problem in your collection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where it all gets a bit Pokemon, but then consider for a moment an epic boss-style battle in Pokemon or any other strategy-based game. You have a collection of problems; your opponents, the posse of pokémon. You have a bunch of constraints; the skills that your pokémon have, and those skills in comparison to your opponent&amp;rsquo;s skills. Your battle strategy should reflect that nuance of playing to the strengths of your pokémon or the weaknesses of your opponent&amp;rsquo;s pokémon. There is probably a reason why the word &lt;em&gt;strategy&lt;/em&gt; conjures up pictures in my mind of mustachioed people in a room playing a gigantic game of Risk. It is complex, it is messy, and very few people have a holistic viewpoint, preferring to stick to their own area of the board. Then add to all of this chance and the inevitable risk that brings; the roll of the dice, the rogue influence of a powerful person, a pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;defining-a-strategy-as-a-collection-of-plans&#34;&gt;Defining a strategy as a collection of plans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strategy attempts to understand problems, barriers, constraints, context and external influencing factors and create a framework for plans, and by extension a rationale for decisions. As Matt LeMay noted, your goals will gain clarity if you can explain the reasons for trade-offs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-decisions-and-actioning-plans&#34;&gt;Making decisions and actioning plans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To expand on the above further, I feel that strategy can be a framework or container for plans, plans are the catalyst for actions, and actions are reliant on decisions. So my key take away from speakers Lucy Spence and Alison Rawlings was the need for clarity in decision making. Good decisions, or at least a decision of best-fit, are research and data informed. Decisions should also be reflected upon after they are made. As an approach to this Spence shared statements that she uses to bring transparency to her decision making:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing the outcome, I would make the same decision again&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing the outcome, I would make a different decision today&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would use the same process to solve the problem again&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would use a different process if I were doing this again&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-hmmm-the-little-thought-experiment-with-evernote-below-could-help-me-learn-something-as-it-sits-in-the-bottom-right-quadrant-of-this-decision-matrix&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Lucy Spence shows her decision making record, which includes the statements above map across an intersecting axis, the x axis shows making a decision from change to no change, the y axis shows using a process form no change to change&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/images/LSpence041122UXBri_hu12669616015415625707.webp 400w,
               /post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/images/LSpence041122UXBri_hu13825797174012674249.webp 760w,
               /post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/images/LSpence041122UXBri_hu7659303798439612904.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/images/LSpence041122UXBri_hu12669616015415625707.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Hmmm the little thought experiment with Evernote below could help me learn something as it sits in the bottom-right quadrant of this decision matrix.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-decision-to-use-evernote-back-in-2013&#34;&gt;My decision to use Evernote back in 2013&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at decision to adopt the Evernote product in the first place, perhaps I will gain further clarity&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selected statement:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Knowing the outcome, I would make a &lt;strong&gt;different&lt;/strong&gt; decision today&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because my expectations have shifted and I have changed since I adopted Evernote. It is also proving to be quite a lengthy process to get my notes out intact&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How have you changed?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I&amp;rsquo;m much more into coding than I was back in 2013. I suppose I want a note taking app a bit more like GitHub with tagging and version control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It sounds like the context has changed&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My expectations have changed because the technology landscape has changed. But my  skills and knowledge in coding were the catalyst for my increased awareness of the broader technology landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selected statement:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;I would use a &lt;strong&gt;different process&lt;/strong&gt; if I were doing this again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because my requirements have changed. The issues with functionality have probably just pushed the matter forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A ha! There we are getting to the truth of the issue, but like any human decision it isn&amp;rsquo;t clear cut. I had outgrown the product &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; my trust was degraded, the combination of both led to a level of inconvenience so as to hasten my move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;recognising-when-yourplans-are-not-working-and-correcting-the-course&#34;&gt;Recognising when your plans are not working and correcting the course&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As noted by speaker Janna Bastow, this might manifest as solving too many problems for a small number of influential people, at the expense of solving the biggest problems for the most people. Bastow advocated splitting up this kind of custom or agency-style work from the product work. This is an interesting idea as it is clear to me throughout my career that large scale projects have often suffered at the expense of the small ones. While many small projects which seem doable on paper, ultimately they eat up the time which should be dedicated to larger ones. Lest us not forgot that having many smaller projects on the go calls for the need to routinely context-switch which consumes more mental energy as a matter of course. The popularity of methods such as Sprints, indicate this need for placemaking for mental space-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-conclude&#34;&gt;To conclude&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude, it is clear to me that when you own a product, it is always on show. What I mean by that is that as long as a product fulfills the core need then it will be loved and largely ignored, but when the cracks appear and that situation is compounded by eager competitors or lack of innovation then abandonment feels more enticing. I always had respect for product managers, now I have even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;random-closing-thought&#34;&gt;Random closing thought&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was Captain Kirk engaging in metacognition when he took the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kobayashi_Maru&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kobayashi Maru&lt;/a&gt; test? If you take the scenario at face value he cheated at the test. However, was Kirk considering this problem-space of the Kobayashi Maru at a philosophical level? Kirk refused to accept that the solution was predetermined and by researching the situation found an alternative. This alternative reflected his personal ethos and values. These values persisted throughout his career, he did not accept the no-win scenario&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. There was always a solution, he just needed the right crew of people to work together and see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of two of my favourite points in Matt LeMay&amp;rsquo;s talk&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Most questions of &lt;strong&gt;role clarity&lt;/strong&gt; are actually best resolved by &lt;strong&gt;goal clarity&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;High performing cross-functional teams naturally self-organise around shared goals.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A table showing a red column for a bad situation, yellow column for a risky situation, green column for a good situation as a decision plot for identifying when a process should stop&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/images/MLeMay041122UXBri_hu6770584174246259865.webp 400w,
               /post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/images/MLeMay041122UXBri_hu8933792402176026399.webp 760w,
               /post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/images/MLeMay041122UXBri_hu7299809568709912682.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/images/MLeMay041122UXBri_hu6770584174246259865.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LeMay also provided a great primer on Adam Thomas&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TheHonorableAT&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@TheHonorableAT on twitter&lt;/a&gt;) &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theadamthomas.com/what-are-survival-metrics-how-do-they-work/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Survival Metrics&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; which relate to the sunk cost fallacy (which Mr Spock explains below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/hnOn8EiniFE?start=105&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, I have moved to &lt;a href=&#34;https://obsidian.md/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt; and used the following script to convert my notebooks to Markdown: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Aias/evernote-to-markdown&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub - Aias/evernote-to-markdown: Converts HTML notes exported from Evernote to plain markdown files, to do with what you will.&lt;/a&gt; On that point I also write this blog in Markdown; a clear example of how my requirements have changed since 2013.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course [spoiler alert] Khan put Kirk&amp;rsquo;s ethos to the test (in both the original and the reboot), but that could be a whole other blog post.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cufflinks - Edition 2 - 23rd October</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2022/10/cufflinks-1022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2022 18:21:29 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2022/10/cufflinks-1022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;welcome-back-to-cufflinks&#34;&gt;Welcome back to &lt;em&gt;Cufflinks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello again! Truth be told I was not expecting a 6-month hiatus between blog posts. I have had so many thoughts, ideas, and experiences that I have wanted to blog about but lacked the time to do so. What have I been doing all this time? Well I&amp;rsquo;ll provide you with an overview below, but first I will share my favourite articles over the past few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reading-highlights&#34;&gt;Reading highlights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://behavioralscientist.org/get-comfortable-with-feeling-uncomfortable/?utm_source=pocket_mylist&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get Comfortable with Feeling Uncomfortable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ayelet Fishbach for Behavioral Scientist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Headline:&lt;/strong&gt; embracing a level of discomfort means that your are actively learning and growing. A very wise friend once told to me that we often do the thing that we are second best at. That is because the thing that we are best at is often deeply uncomfortable. I feel this way when I am working in the solution space in design, especially when there is a lot of ambiguity. I also felt like this when I worked as an artist and curator. In short if I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel uncomfortable I knew I wasn&amp;rsquo;t really doing to work. As humans we tend to like the path of least resistance. So keeping your sights on the longer term benefits is essential if you want to stay the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://uxplanet.org/product-design-methods-mind-map-f6511820a7d5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product Design Methods In a Mind Map&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Mei Zhang for UX Planet on Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mei Zhang&amp;rsquo;s post is a wonderful gift to all designer-kinds. It provides a helpful article and an &lt;a href=&#34;https://miro.com/app/board/o9J_ktZHnRA=/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;essential mind map&lt;/a&gt; for navigating the many methods and tools approaches available during each phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://uxplanet.org/what-is-design-thinking-lets-cook-it-out-fe8d239412ce&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Is Design Thinking? Let&amp;rsquo;s Cook It Out&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Chinwe Uzegbu on for UX Planet on Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article provides a very fun and accessible explanation of Design Thinking and how it works. Using a high stakes dinner party as an analogy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://uxdesign.cc/the-problem-solvers-playbook-17-questions-to-sharpen-your-thinking-167e2ce134c2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problem-solver’s playbook: 17 questions to sharpen your thinking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Debbie Widjaja for UX Collective on Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article is pure brilliance and I keep coming back to it over and over. It has become a permanent fixture in my &lt;em&gt;personal&lt;/em&gt; playbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://laurayarrow.medium.com/the-mail-never-stops-105fddbbe612&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The mail never stops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Laura Yarrow on Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article include excellent time and communications flow management tips. Many I had already implemented, some I had not and now do. On this topic, I am really looking forward to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/microsoft-teams-blog/what-s-new-in-microsoft-teams-microsoft-ignite-2022/ba-p/3614158&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Schedule Send feature which is finally coming to MS Teams&lt;/a&gt;. That has been a great feature in Slack and is a good way to respect folks&amp;rsquo; time and control your own communications hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-partner=&#34;tweetdeck&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Even those of us who have been writing alt text for years can improve our practice (so many that I would tweak with hindsight). This guide is going into my &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/LX?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#LX&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/UX?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#UX&lt;/a&gt; toolkit for safekeeping and frequent reference. Thank you &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/scope?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@scope&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/a11y?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#a11y&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/accessibility?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#accessibility&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/LwEXLBdl4i&#34;&gt;https://t.co/LwEXLBdl4i&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/OsvecKhRk3&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/OsvecKhRk3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Fiona MacNeill (@fmacneill) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fmacneill/status/1535532289928548352?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 11, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-things-i-did-and-things-that-i-am-doing&#34;&gt;Some things I did and things that I am doing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a whistle stop tour of my person highlights over Spring/Summer 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-was-a-guest-on-the-ux-coach-podcast&#34;&gt;I was a guest on the UX Coach Podcast&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an honour and a pleasure to be invited to be a guest on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theuxcoach.com/about.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Andy Parker&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; UX Coach Podcast which aired in July. Visit the UX Coach website to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theuxcoach.com/2022/07/24/make-an-action-plan.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;listen to the episode or read the transcript&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the highlights for me during the discussion was talking about the difference that coaching made for me in my career&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;I had to make a change&amp;hellip;having that coaching experience and being able to look inside myself and go &amp;ldquo;what are the skills I have to solve this
problem?&amp;rdquo; Oh, I actually know a bit about data analysis. I know a bit about algorithms and what are recruitment processes based on? Algorithms, LinkedIn keywords. Okay. Let’s go and have a look at what all of the keywords are on the favorite jobs I would really like on LinkedIn. And then let’s think about how those apply to me and do I have them? And I thought, yeah, I actually do. I can genuinely cover all of those keywords. Those are all things that I know about and have applied. So then I added those to my profile. And within a week I got a recruiter contacting me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And it was like, if I just thought of about it in the way that I think about solving problems in my job, then I could have been onto this much earlier&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more on this you can check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.susanbbentley.com/results/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;my coach, Suse Bentley&amp;rsquo;s case study on her site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what I have learned is if I approach solving my own problems with the same level of interest and tenacity that I apply to those of my clients, I will find solutions. This is &lt;em&gt;rut&lt;/em&gt; kyptonite!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-completed-some-career-firsts&#34;&gt;I completed some career firsts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;my-first-sprint&#34;&gt;My first Sprint&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I devised my first design Sprint (Knapp, Zeratsky and Kowitz, 2016) in August for an internal client group. It was both intense and invigorating to consider inputs, outputs, flexibility and outcomes. The process was successful and thanks to the ingenuity of my collaborators we only used 4 sheets of paper across the event. We avoided the usual pile of sad and used-up post-it notes by using &lt;a href=&#34;https://getrocketbook.co.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Rocketbook products&lt;/a&gt; which allowed us to write, wipe off, and reuse. My particular favourites were the &lt;a href=&#34;https://getrocketbook.co.uk/collections/best-sellers/products/rocketbook-cloud-cards?variant=39291463368776&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;cloud cards&lt;/a&gt; (index cards) which have now become a mainstay in my design studio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;learning-campaign-based-on-user-research&#34;&gt;Learning campaign based on user research&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have designed and run outreach campaigns before. However, this was the first time that in-depth user research and interview transcript analysis had pointed towards the approach as the most effective solution. Discovery to truly understand the underlying problem made all the difference. The campaign itself is multi-channel across intranet, internal communications tools, and email. It also includes a three-week challenge via the LMS as a mini-course with a limited-edition badge. The campaign has resulted in the creation of valuable job aids which can persist beyond, helping colleagues in their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-have-been-volunteering-for-ladies-that-ux-brighton&#34;&gt;I have been volunteering for Ladies that UX Brighton&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this is the venture which has been taking up time when I might have been blogging, but it is totally worth it! Ladies that UX (LTUX) is a magnificent organisation holding meetups in 85 places around the world and supporting women and people of underrepresented genders in UX. LTUX Brighton chapter has been on hiatus since March 2020 due to the pandemic. So, myself and co-organisers now have the task of rebuilding it from the ground up. After several months of meetings and concerted networking we are getting ready to re-launch in 2023. A highlight for me has been getting to give a talk to students on my former MSc UX program. It was such a heartening experience to share my enthusiasm for UX and the Brighton UX community with a group of interested people. If you would like to learn more or get involved (we are seeking more volunteers and speakers) visit the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ladiesthatux.com/brighton/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LTUX Brighton site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;flow of activities starting with video interviews, a written interview transcript, a chart showing click activities when using software Then example statements for a job when I am context, to help me motivation, so I can outcome&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2022/10/cufflinks-1022/images/LTUXBrightonLocalSublime_hu1447441321651271237.webp 400w,
               /post/2022/10/cufflinks-1022/images/LTUXBrightonLocalSublime_hu3542266375365254829.webp 760w,
               /post/2022/10/cufflinks-1022/images/LTUXBrightonLocalSublime_hu12678372389051257266.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2022/10/cufflinks-1022/images/LTUXBrightonLocalSublime_hu1447441321651271237.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My favourite image from the new branding from Ladies that UX. Can you guess where this is in Brighton? - Answer at the end of the post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-am-feeding-my-mind-moving-my-body-and-curating-my-space&#34;&gt;I am feeding my mind, moving my body, and curating my space&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am cultivating creative and curious encounters on a daily basis. This is a lifelong pursuit for me, but I have to admit that I had let it lapse a bit due to busyness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a similar vein I can recommend the work of Stefaan van Hooyd, author of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Workplace-Curiosity-Manifesto-Transformational-Organizations/dp/B0B2HQ7DHS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Workplace Curiosity Manifesto&lt;/a&gt; who I saw give a talk at the Learning Technologies Autumn Forum (13th October, ExCel Centre, London).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-partner=&#34;tweetdeck&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Amazing talk with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/stefaanvanhooyd?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@stefaanvanhooyd&lt;/a&gt; on Curiosity &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/LTAF22?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#LTAF22&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Cow6lSSqxs&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Cow6lSSqxs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Fiona MacNeill (@fmacneill) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fmacneill/status/1580542508660293632?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;October 13, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;activities-to-feed-my-mind&#34;&gt;Activities to feed my mind&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applying for my alumni library membership and reading books outside my current area of knowledge. Currently I am reading a book on linguistics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-partner=&#34;tweetdeck&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Okay I have to admit that I let out a high pitched exclamation of delight when I received my approval for alumni library membership today. Thank you  &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/brightonalumni?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@brightonalumni&lt;/a&gt; for making this possible! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Y2KrmoUnup&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Y2KrmoUnup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Fiona MacNeill (@fmacneill) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fmacneill/status/1554933626609041410?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 3, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to the theatre more. The show that caused to me to think, learn and reflect this week was Ifrah Mansour&amp;rsquo;s one-woman show, &amp;ldquo;How to have fun in a Civil War&amp;rdquo;. Which effectively and poignantly retold her own experiences as a young child in Somalia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been drawing again and will be trying to attend life drawing sessions at least once every couple of months. It is clear to me that the intense observation required in drawing supports my practice as a designer. It is a muscle I definitely need to continue flexing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding any excuse to see art both locally and when I am working in London. Sticking around after work to visit the Tate Modern for an hour where I saw the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tate.org.uk/whats-on/tate-modern/cecilia-vicu%C3%B1a&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;work of Cecilia Vicuña in the Turbine Hall&lt;/a&gt;, as shown in the featured image for this post. I loved the way that the former oil tanks at Tate remind me of the former industrial smell and tranquility of the nooks and crannies in The Soap Factory (an art gallery and former workplace of mine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another unexpected delight was getting to go up The Shard last week and gaining a  whole new appreciation of London. Seeing the space where the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cityoflondon.gov.uk/things-to-do/walks-and-itineraries/itineraries/roman-london&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Roman settlement of Londinium&lt;/a&gt; was founded from the vantage point of their gods and wondering what life must have been like 2,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img title=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;images/ViewFromTheShard.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A selfie high above London in the Shard skyscraper&#34; data-align=&#34;inline&#34; width=&#34;504&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;moving-my-body&#34;&gt;Moving my body&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took part in two runs in September. One with work colleagues through City of London for SolarAid. It was amazing to run freely without cars amongst the towering buildings and neons reflecting off the rain-sprinkled tarmac in the evening light. I also ran my first half-marathon in September as part of the Great North Run. I raised nearly £400 for Mind charity and spent a wonderful long weekend in Newcastle with my mum. I also continue to kickbox and have taken up a bit of Thai boxing when I can fit it in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img title=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;images/GreatNorthRun.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Fiona in a running vest and shorts pictured at the end of the run&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; data-align=&#34;inline&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;curating-my-space&#34;&gt;Curating my space&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found some signed cards by one of my heroes, the artist Marina Abramović at the Baltic art gallery in Newcastle. The cards suggest ways to essentially hack your perception and are based on techniques Abramović uses prior to her performance art pieces. I decided that these are great for my studio and give me inspiration alongside some psychology cards and the odd cloud notecard! You&amp;rsquo;ll also note some fairy lights to cheer me up as we enter the long-dark of Winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;fairy lights with clipped on cards, each card with a diffferent picture or message&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2022/10/cufflinks-1022/images/CuratingMySpace_hu9547979046297449794.webp 400w,
               /post/2022/10/cufflinks-1022/images/CuratingMySpace_hu6039912154369726025.webp 760w,
               /post/2022/10/cufflinks-1022/images/CuratingMySpace_hu3295236739691401557.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2022/10/cufflinks-1022/images/CuratingMySpace_hu9547979046297449794.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;279&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;em&gt;You may not find a skull in the grand tradition of momento mori to be tranquil. For some reason I do!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;something-i-made-or-fixed&#34;&gt;Something I made or fixed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been contributing to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mrbracchi&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@mrbracchi&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; awesome ID list of helpful tools for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mrbracchi/Awesome-ID&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Instructional Design&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also been knitting these socks for my dad. Pretty jazzy huh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/sockmaking.JPG&#34; title=&#34;MarkText logo&#34; alt=&#34;1 and half hand knitted socks in lots of colours and patterns&#34; width=&#34;206&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The answer to my question about the building in Brighton:&lt;/strong&gt;
it is the top of the Dr Marten&amp;rsquo;s shoe shop (&lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/maps/Ld6vRc4U3gimZtQ46&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;take a look on Google Maps&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knapp, J, Zeratsky, J., Kowitz, B. (2016) Sprint: How to solve big problems and test new ideas in just five days. &lt;em&gt;New York: Bantam Press.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;extra-features&#34;&gt;Extra features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;on the topic of referencing&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-partner=&#34;tweetdeck&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;A thread 🧵: As a &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Dyslexic?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Dyslexic&lt;/a&gt; person who struggles with reading-at-speed, screen readers are a gateway to knowledge. I like to stay up-to-date by reading academic papers and industry reports. However, I want to talk about academic referencing styles and why they are a problem...&lt;/p&gt;— Fiona MacNeill (@fmacneill) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fmacneill/status/1525423338100858881?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;May 14, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vlog 3 [1/2]: Adventures in ViewX - Double Diamond for Watch Parties</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflecting-on-designing-a-watch-party-for-ux-brighton&#34;&gt;Reflecting on designing a watch party for UX Brighton&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/GmCNObzZEbo&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch the UX Brighton watch party for yourself &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PL3X0iMolG4HwSH9WRA0XiD9hP-uy2uNF3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;using this playlist on YouTube&lt;/a&gt; (took place on 13th April 2021)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1b747H2vIbIp2eLVWibukc_LpVY7vJw78yuibyfaNF10/edit?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;schedule and information for the event&lt;/a&gt; which was provided as a Google Doc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visit the &lt;a href=&#34;https://app.mural.co/t/fiona7703/m/fiona7703/1625313369702/58272bac1b627de1c54c394c658c1a9d23f64e2b?sender=fmacneill8446&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mural board&lt;/a&gt; that I used to guide my design and then reflect on my experiences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://fjm15.brighton.domains/oer/demo/ux-brighton-video-bingo/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;video bingo mini challenge&lt;/a&gt; (H5P interactive activity)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;edited-vlog-transcript&#34;&gt;Edited Vlog Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi folks, I know it&amp;rsquo;s been a while. So, yeah basically what I can say is I&amp;rsquo;ve had a couple of really paperwork intensive months. I ran a watch party for &lt;a href=&#34;https://uxbri.org/UX-Watch-Party/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UX Brighton&lt;/a&gt; because I presented about a few of the challenges I&amp;rsquo;d found through working on some discovery at my workplace. The suggestion was that perhaps we could do a UX Brighton watch party and that might provide me with an opportunity to experiment to try out some things that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t try out at work and to get some really helpful critical feedback. So, I&amp;rsquo;m really delighted to say that I got that opportunity because I really did get amazing feedback and I have since used the learning that I gained from that particular watch party to feed into my professional portfolio, and I&amp;rsquo;ve also used it to think really critically about how I talk to staff about watch parties how I encourage them to onboard people during watch parties.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;discover&#34;&gt;Discover&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;three-key-problems-to-solve&#34;&gt;Three key problems to solve&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll come on to some of the key takeaways in a little bit, but I&amp;rsquo;ve used a mural board to help me reflect. This is based on the Design Council&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Evolved Double Diamond&lt;/em&gt; (2015) which is what I used as the sort of basis for my design process for the watch party. From my discovery work within my workplace there were three key problems to solve. So, first of all staff had been screen sharing video that they wanted to show to students, and they wanted to screen share the video so that everyone could watch it together at the same time. The key issue was that when you share video over a tool like Microsoft Teams, like Zoom, it&amp;rsquo;s very much reliant on the speed of your broadband connection but also the speed of the people’s connection who are watching at home. So, what we&amp;rsquo;d often find is that the video would play fine for the person who was sharing but then at home people would find that there was no audio, or the video was kind of juddery. Some of the screen shared video was blocked by Digital Rights Management. So particularly in Microsoft Teams it has some Digital Rights Management and so what the student would see on their end was just a kind of grey or black screen there would be no content even though it was playing fine for the instructor. The biggest problem of the three was that when if you, as the instructor, were playing a video out to students and you were screen sharing it would look to me, as the student watching, like I could use the closed caption tools say if you were sharing a YouTube video. Most YouTube videos have a CC (Closed Caption) button on the bottom right-hand side that allows you to access the closed captions. Well, if you&amp;rsquo;re screen sharing it it&amp;rsquo;s sort of a flat facsimile of the video so I couldn&amp;rsquo;t actually interact with those subtitles, those closed captions so that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t help me if I needed that.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;facilitation-and-watching-other-people-watch&#34;&gt;Facilitation and watching other people &amp;lsquo;watch&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another key ingredient that I identified through the discovery phase was that there must always be a facilitator. SAnother key ingredient that I identified through the discovery phase was that there must always be a facilitator. So, for example if you were someone who had content ready, and you gave people a watch list of stuff it doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that you can then go away and just leave them to it. There&amp;rsquo;s something about needing to be there, needing to guide that discussion, or guide the activities which are kicked off by the video content, so the video content is really more of a prompt to get things going it&amp;rsquo;s a way of presenting information and then interspersing it with something more personable something more um discursive. So, it allows you to potentially cover more content quickly because a video is kind of produced. The next point here is that I think there&amp;rsquo;s something to be said for watching other people &amp;lsquo;watch&amp;rsquo; things (I have included some of my favourite references related to this concept &lt;a href=&#34;https://ukc-word-edit.officeapps.live.com/we/wordeditorframe.aspx?ui=en%2DUS&amp;amp;rs=en%2DUS&amp;amp;wopisrc=https%3A%2F%2Funibrightonac-my.sharepoint.com%2Fpersonal%2Ff_macneill_brighton_ac_uk%2F_vti_bin%2Fwopi.ashx%2Ffiles%2Ff25048be836d483697882ba2c1c40cdd&amp;amp;wdorigin=OFFICECOM%2dWEB%2eSTART%2eREC&amp;amp;wdenableroaming=1&amp;amp;mscc=1&amp;amp;wdodb=1&amp;amp;hid=1FB5E59F-F011-3000-213E-3C92F26DF21D&amp;amp;wdhostclicktime=1629019735157&amp;amp;jsapi=1&amp;amp;jsapiver=v1&amp;amp;newsession=1&amp;amp;corrid=ade27623-5843-4087-61dc-d7c46c032939&amp;amp;usid=ade27623-5843-4087-61dc-d7c46c032939&amp;amp;sftc=1&amp;amp;mtf=1&amp;amp;sfp=1&amp;amp;instantedit=1&amp;amp;wopicomplete=1&amp;amp;wdredirectionreason=Unified_SingleFlush&amp;amp;preseededsessionkey=486a2f06-9826-5966-1d8b-46432be69c2e&amp;amp;preseededwacsessionid=ade27623-5843-4087-61dc-d7c46c032939&amp;amp;rct=Medium&amp;amp;ctp=LeastProtected#refs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;at the bottom of this post&lt;/a&gt;). So, I know that when I&amp;rsquo;m in a cinema my attention span is much better than it is when I&amp;rsquo;m just sitting at home watching Netflix. So, if my attention&amp;rsquo;s lagging in a film I kind of look around and go &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;are other people still interested in this film or is other people looking kind of you know a little bit bored&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; and if everyone else is really engaged then that kind of makes me think well &amp;ldquo;_I should re-engage, obviously I&amp;rsquo;m missing something her_e&amp;rdquo;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;define&#34;&gt;Define&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;software-requirements-to-address-the-challenges&#34;&gt;Software requirements to address the challenges&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next thing was to think about &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;well what interface do I actually need?&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;what software would meet these requirements um for the watch parties?&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. So, I had some must-haves: audio discussion, must have space for people to write into a chat that is yep definitely needed, webcam video connection yep, and access to closed captions (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fionamacneill.co.uk/blog/2021/04/vlog-2-but-what-about-the-subtitles/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;my post, &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;But what about the subtitles?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; Discussed issues meeting this requirement). We needed some kind of high-quality way of sharing the video. Basically, any way of screen sharing video wasn&amp;rsquo;t great, so I needed something that allowed me to kind of press start and stop for everyone at the same time. Circles here that have the ticks on them (on the Mural board), these are actually requirements that were met by the software that I used for the watch party which I&amp;rsquo;ll come onto in a bit. There were some &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;should have&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo; things so access to closed caption customization so being able to change the font size and the position of the closed captions is really important. Having access to reaction tools like smiling and clapping and thumbs up and being able to move aspects of the interface so if the chat box was really distracting to me while the video is on, I could minimize it I could also choose which things I kind of wanted &amp;lsquo;on&amp;rsquo; tool-wise or ‘off’. The thing we didn&amp;rsquo;t have was support for mobile devices that the tool we ended up using really didn&amp;rsquo;t work great on mobile devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;thinking-about-viewx-or-the-exerience-of-viewing&#34;&gt;Thinking about &amp;lsquo;ViewX&amp;rsquo; or the Exerience of Viewing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, while I was kind of going through this process, I also thought about defining what formats were possible with a watch party. Funnily enough I&amp;rsquo;ve sort of nicknamed this process ViewX so like UX but ViewX like the experience of viewing um I think there is something about this that&amp;rsquo;s just been utterly fascinating to me like how does the environment of viewing affect how you view? So, the first approach I had was named after Nick Knowles who&amp;rsquo;s a DIY expert on TV and this one was about using your own video footage but then chunking it into key concepts. The next method I thought about was based on &lt;em&gt;Elvira the Mistress of the Dark&lt;/em&gt; who always would play, this is kind of a 1980s thing, but she would play like really rubbish B movies and she would intersperse her own commentary with that. So, it&amp;rsquo;s a little bit like Mystery Science Theater um, but it was more like segments that interspersed with the video. Because it might be that video requires that kind of contextualization in order for it to make sense but there is also um some value which I&amp;rsquo;ll come on to in perhaps not always presenting one way of interpreting video and in fact leaving it more vague and open to audience interpretation. That&amp;rsquo;s where that can really help to stimulate your discursive elements during the watch party. So, what I came up with was what I&amp;rsquo;ve now since labelled the Michael Moore approach which is sort of a video essay type approach where I actually captured sections of YouTube videos and represented them as a mashup, so each section of the watch party was sort of a video mashup where I&amp;rsquo;d placed really short clips from a range of videos together. With the Michael Moore approach as I&amp;rsquo;m calling it you can present these video clips smashed together with or without video commentary so you could have a sort of voiceover that presented some context which is similar to the Elvira approach, or you can just present the videos together with no context which is almost more interesting. I think it depends on what you&amp;rsquo;re aiming for. So, I think that because there was no commentary from me the videos were just presented as they are, but as snippets, people had to decide well &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;why did Fiona pick that snippet and why did that how does that relate to the next slip snippet or how does that relate to the one that came before&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Slide showing the TV presenter, Nick Knowles, to represent a DIY approach to watch party&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/images/WatchPartiesAndLiveLectures_hu4896585576407987618.webp 400w,
               /post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/images/WatchPartiesAndLiveLectures_hu5699058291793578900.webp 760w,
               /post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/images/WatchPartiesAndLiveLectures_hu3699759353966392618.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/images/WatchPartiesAndLiveLectures_hu4896585576407987618.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;lsquo;Nick Knowles&amp;rsquo;, using your own content. A chaptered Panopto video is shown as an example on the right of the slide image&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Elvira mistress of the dark on the left in an open-topped car and a video of Fiona providing video commentary on a video of Michael Caine from the 1980s&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/images/WatchPartiesAndLiveLectures2_hu15945727926602469186.webp 400w,
               /post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/images/WatchPartiesAndLiveLectures2_hu10557024921461860191.webp 760w,
               /post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/images/WatchPartiesAndLiveLectures2_hu15700117417519748780.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/images/WatchPartiesAndLiveLectures2_hu15945727926602469186.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;lsquo;Elvira&amp;rsquo; format or approach. Video commentary alongside a video of Michael Caine is shown as a visual example on the image of the slide&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Michael Moore on the left and a series of embedded YouTube videos on the right within the context of a Virtual Learning Environment&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/images/WatchPartiesAndLiveLectures3_hu13220054536651272348.webp 400w,
               /post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/images/WatchPartiesAndLiveLectures3_hu4701176105745347385.webp 760w,
               /post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/images/WatchPartiesAndLiveLectures3_hu1321625527040814259.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2021/07/vlog-3-part-1-adventures-in-viewx/images/WatchPartiesAndLiveLectures3_hu13220054536651272348.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The director Michael Moore is pictured to represent an approach of curating preexisting content from YouTube or other video services. An example of a series of clipped and embedded YouTube videos is shown as an example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;defining-a-format-or-schedule-for-the-event&#34;&gt;Defining a format or schedule for the event&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this brought me to kind of defining the format for the event itself. It was a three-part watch party over two hours. So, we had a sort of conceptually based video collection, as I say, mashed together short clips, kind of one after the other. Then we had some discussion and then we had our second video collection. That was followed by some more discussion and a break. Then we came back and played a game. An online game which was not related to any of the content it was literally just kind of providing social levity if you will, and then we had a third video which we were planning to watch and we didn&amp;rsquo;t watch it because I basically lost my nerve a bit and felt like we were too close to the end and that we should just wrap up.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;selecting-the-tools---leading-into-the-develop-phase-second-diamond&#34;&gt;Selecting the tools - leading into the Develop phase (second diamond)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this leads me to the tool. So, based on all of these kind of aspects in the &lt;em&gt;discovery&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;definition&lt;/em&gt; phase I decided that the best choice was a tool called backyard.co which had all of those reactions, chat tools, and this thing called YouTube watch party as one of its kind of interactive games that it offered. So, I like the fact that we could use the YouTube watch party game or tool and then switch to another game in the same platform so it would feel very integrated. It wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a case of us switching between completely different tools in a session which I have since found that you kind of have a maximum of two tools in a session, otherwise you do start to lose people.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;a href=&#34;https://h5p.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;H5P&lt;/a&gt; (interactive learning tool) to create the video bingo because I wanted something that was quick to build, it allowed interaction on a variety of different devices, and it also gave automatic feedback so people kind of got a confirmation that they had got the bingo right and that they had filled all of the squares in, and then I asked them as part of the onboarding to let me know when they had filled in all the squares. So, that I could kind of celebrate the person who managed to identify all the bingo phrases that were said in the videos first before anyone else!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brame, C. J. (2016) ‘Effective educational videos: Principles and guidelines for maximizing student learning from video content’, &lt;em&gt;CBE—Life Sciences Education, 15&lt;/em&gt;(4). doi: 10.1187/cbe.16-03-0125&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design Council (2015) ‘What is the framework for innovation? Design Council’s evolved Double Diamond’, &lt;em&gt;Design Council&lt;/em&gt;. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.designcouncil.org.uk/news-opinion/what-framework-innovation-design-councils-evolved-double-diamond&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.designcouncil.org.uk/news-opinion/what-framework-innovation-design-councils-evolved-double-diamond&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed: 13 March 2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guo, P. J., Kim, J. and Rubin, R. (2014) ‘How video production affects student engagement’, in &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the first ACM conference on Learning @ scale&lt;/em&gt;. ACM, pp.41–50. doi: 10.1145/2556325.2566239&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hotchkiss, G. (2010) &amp;lsquo;The psychology of entertainment: Why we love watching in crowds&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;Out of My Gord&lt;/em&gt;, 20 February. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://outofmygord.com/2010/02/20/the-psychology-of-entertainment-why-we-love-watching-in-crowds/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://outofmygord.com/2010/02/20/the-psychology-of-entertainment-why-we-love-watching-in-crowds/&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed: 4 July 2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mastead, T. (2005) &amp;lsquo;The social dimension of emotion&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;The Psychologist&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;18&lt;/em&gt;(8), pp.484-487. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://thepsychologist.bps.org.uk/volume-18/edition-8/social-dimension-emotion&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://thepsychologist.bps.org.uk/volume-18/edition-8/social-dimension-emotion&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed: 4 July 2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UCL (2020) &amp;lsquo;Why watching a movie could improve wellbeing&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;UCL Brain Sciences&lt;/em&gt;, 20 January. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/brain-sciences/news/2020/jan/why-watching-movie-could-improve-wellbeing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/brain-sciences/news/2020/jan/why-watching-movie-could-improve-wellbeing&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed: 4 July 2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;von Zimmerman, J. and Richardson, D. C. (2018) &amp;lsquo;Synchrony and the art of signalling&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;The Psychologist, 31&lt;/em&gt;, pp.32-36. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://thepsychologist.bps.org.uk/volume-31/june-2018/synchrony-and-art-signalling&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://thepsychologist.bps.org.uk/volume-31/june-2018/synchrony-and-art-signalling&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed: 4 July 2021).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UX Camp Brighton 2018: Jobs-To-Be-Done-(R) #uxcb18</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-am-i-here-as-in-you-at-this-blog-and-reading-this-now&#34;&gt;Why am I here (as in you, at this blog, and reading this now)?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you are here because you would like an introduction to using RStudio for data visualisation. I also hope that you are here because you are interested in &lt;a href=&#34;https://strategyn.com/customer-centered-innovation-map/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jobs-To-Be-Done&lt;/a&gt; (abbrev~ JTBD; Ulwick, 2016). This blog provides an example of how to apply one of the approaches that sits under the mantle of JTBD, an Opportunity Landscape (Ulwick, 2016; VIII. Target Hidden Growth Opportunities section).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-we-going-to-do&#34;&gt;What are we going to do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are going to create a plot, or Opportunity Landscape (SEE also Ulwick, 2017), based on data from a quick opinion survey that was distributed via social media. Survey respondents were asked to rate particular tasks that they regularly complete on a smart watch according to importance and satisfaction on 5-part &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Likert_scale&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Likert scales&lt;/a&gt;. At this point I should add a caveat, for those familiar with JTBD. These questions were not based on full &lt;em&gt;job&lt;/em&gt; statements or stories but were abbreviated task statements. This is largely because based on survey testing, I found that the time it took to read and consider longer Job stories, based on Situation-&amp;gt;Motivation-&amp;gt;Expected Outcome (Klement, 2016) required too much mental effort for a &amp;lt;15min survey. I have found Job stories to be indispensable at the interview stage, when derived from transcripts as a means to uncover motivations. In the context of this post I would say that my methodology is a bit of a mash-up of JTBD and Gerry McGovern&amp;rsquo;s top tasks (2010; 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-are-creating-a-plot&#34;&gt;Why are creating a plot?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that the true purpose of any plot is to start conversations. Data visualisations have the power to both subvert truth and to challenge commonly held assumptions, I aim for the latter. Always.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-are-we-using-rstudio-with-ggplot2&#34;&gt;Why are we using RStudio with ggplot2?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty of using RStudio with ggplot2 is&amp;hellip;well beauty. Most people can make standard Excel visualisations without too much effort, but even with a lot of tweaking they still have a heady whiff. In the past I used Adobe Illustrator, but speaking of my own failings it was too easy to leave the land of accuracy and enter the land of surface-treatment. Here are my top reasons why you should consider using RStudio with ggplot2:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You know how to use Microsoft Excel, but would like to create better visualisations&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have lots of data and you would like to segment it and look at a smaller portions without getting caught in a scrolling cycle-of-doom in a humongous spreadsheet&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want something inexpensive - the only cost here is time, but it is well worth it&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once you have built it, it can be used over and over and over&amp;hellip;and tweaked quickly for whatever the need&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bonus:&lt;/strong&gt; RStudio and gpplot2 can be used to prototype data visualisations for interface design and depending on your audience a realistic looking representation/visualisation could be very important.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If any of the statements above have piqued your interest then keep reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-1-collect-the-data-show-me-the-data&#34;&gt;Step 1: Collect the Data, Show me the Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In true Blue Peter style, here is one I made earlier&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image of an Opportunity Landscape plot&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/JTBD_demo_image-1rd4pz7_hu4257426719150724564.webp 400w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/JTBD_demo_image-1rd4pz7_hu7160451143862470047.webp 760w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/JTBD_demo_image-1rd4pz7_hu16312118645119623351.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/JTBD_demo_image-1rd4pz7_hu4257426719150724564.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;608&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
 The plot above is based on Webcredible&amp;rsquo;s fantastic blog post on the topic of JTBD (Josephy, 2016).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should add that your plots can be much more extravagant than this, but essentially this is the basic type of plot that we are going to create to get started. The descriptive lines above are superfluous&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. They are useful to keep commented-out in your code though as they can be used to create quick descriptive visuals for stakeholders when needed. What we can read from the visualisation above is that I could have asked about a lot more &lt;em&gt;jobs&lt;/em&gt;; it is a bit sparse, but 12 jobs is what this particular survey could accommodate. Also the majority of the jobs fall into the &amp;lsquo;overserved&amp;rsquo; domain. This means satisfaction has been rated higher than importance and according to Ulwick (2016) this is prime territory for disruption. So although initially, when I looked at this visualisation I was like &amp;ldquo;oh blast&amp;rdquo;, as I was looking for some untapped potential related to smart watch jobs and there is none. Actually it is more that customers are overserved for jobs that aren&amp;rsquo;t perceived as that important and therefore the landscape is primed for some new competitor to come in and do the job in a cheaper and perhaps less good, but cheaper way, which though market adoption and iteration of &amp;lsquo;said&amp;rsquo; cheap version may eventually lead to something better (Ulwick, 2016). Of course another dimension would be to ask questions about jobs that have not yet been considered for smart watch, but these were out of scope for this particular survey. In a way this plot perfectly sums up smart watches as they are still finding their footing, they are still superfluous to the smartphone which is almost ubiquitous. The point I am getting to here is that this plot asks questions of the data, that we might not normally ask if we were looking at each question in isolation. It is only when we bring these jobs together that we reach a new level of meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;collect-the-data&#34;&gt;Collect the data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need a survey question something like this&amp;hellip; 















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Screenshot of survey question&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/00_display-w6adj4_hu11432230900108597048.webp 400w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/00_display-w6adj4_hu6343540083054042405.webp 760w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/00_display-w6adj4_hu5738906302310737442.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/00_display-w6adj4_hu11432230900108597048.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;435&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
 &amp;hellip;Or split it into two versions of the same question depending on the allowances of your survey tool. &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;DANGER, WILL ROBINSON!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-danger-will-robinson-by-basilleaf-on-flickr&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Photo of a 1960s-style robot with oval head made of clear glass&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/8309044921_5b3e0021a1_m_hu4308417083972661176.webp 400w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/8309044921_5b3e0021a1_m_hu8441131541161243420.webp 760w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/8309044921_5b3e0021a1_m_hu6905223669964946683.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/8309044921_5b3e0021a1_m_hu4308417083972661176.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;240&#34;
               height=&#34;240&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      DANGER WILL ROBINSON by BasilLeaf, on Flickr
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;A photo of a robot based on the character from the 1960s TV show, Lost in Space.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/garynlisa/8309044921/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DANGER WILL ROBINSON&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY 2.0&lt;/a&gt;) by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/people/garynlisa/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BasilLeaf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: Hey didn&amp;rsquo;t you say earlier that you need a 5 part Likert scale? But you only have four options in the &amp;lsquo;satisfaction&amp;rsquo; scale above?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is I had to take a difficult decision about the experience of users on smartphones using my survey. One more column and it was over the precipice into the land of non-function. As I am only interested in &amp;lsquo;Quite Important&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Very Important&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Satisfied&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Highly Satisfied&amp;rsquo; in this context I sacrificed the final column. So the results for the first question looked like this&amp;hellip; 















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image of results&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/00_result-qp4oul_hu17308248608783363378.webp 400w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/00_result-qp4oul_hu6238986280423095458.webp 760w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/00_result-qp4oul_hu838624317351699530.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/00_result-qp4oul_hu17308248608783363378.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;579&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
] For the Satisfaction element, I created an &lt;a href=&#34;https://support.office.com/en-us/article/IFS-function-36329a26-37b2-467c-972b-4a39bd951d45&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IFS Function&lt;/a&gt; in my final spreadsheet, to make 4 equaled 5, 3 equaled 4, 2 equaled 3 and 1 equaled 2. This put everything on the same scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;download-the-data&#34;&gt;Download the data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any good survey tool should allow you to download the results to CSV format (Comma Separated Values) and any survey tool worth its salt should also provide a SPSS or data analysis format which codes each response with a number. So in my case I wanted to the most positive response to have the highest rank value. I am going to use Excel to sort the data, as that is/was my comfort zone and I think that it is good to start from a position of confidence and trust in the original figures prior to visualising them. Personally speaking after only a few months of working with RStudio, I now feel happy to complete the entire workflow in RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip: Split up your Importance (IMP) and Satisfaction (SAT) onto separate tabs in your Excel spreadsheet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Believe me this will make your life SO much easier, when it comes to doing your calculations. 















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image of sort data slide&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/sort-the-data.001-1jk68l1_hu8306759350944689574.webp 400w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/sort-the-data.001-1jk68l1_hu12536099441163713147.webp 760w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/sort-the-data.001-1jk68l1_hu846163279079221957.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/sort-the-data.001-1jk68l1_hu8306759350944689574.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-2-do-the-maths&#34;&gt;Step 2: Do the Maths&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having separated your data, create a new tab in your spreadsheet and create the rows defined in the column labelled &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; below. Then use the data on your Importance tab to populate column &lt;strong&gt;B.&lt;/strong&gt; Start with one question-worth of data, we&amp;rsquo;ll get to the rest of your questions soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So for row 3 &amp;ldquo;total importance&amp;rdquo;: count all the entries in the importance column for that particular job from the first data row to the last - indicated by A_x_ \[COUNTA\].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For row 4 we want to count how many of these entries had a rating of 4 (Quite Important) and 5 (Very Important). So we use a COUNTIF formula to look at values greater than 3. As we aren&amp;rsquo;t dealing with decimals (yet), &amp;ldquo;&amp;gt;3&amp;rdquo; is accurate enough for this purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For row 5 we need to find out what percentage of overall responses are &lt;em&gt;Quite&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Very Important&lt;/em&gt;. So we divide row 4 by row 3 and then times by 10.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;1&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;C&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Job&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am a job&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;In Excel speak&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;total importance&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;How many entries are there in the column?&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;=COUNTA(&amp;lsquo;IMP data’!A2:A x)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;imp &amp;gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;How many entries are there in the column &amp;gt;3?&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;=COUNTIF(&amp;lsquo;IMP data&amp;rsquo;!A2:A x, &amp;ldquo;&amp;gt;3&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;imp %&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Importance/total importance X 10&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;=B4/B3*10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create identical rows for satisfaction&lt;/strong&gt; (after in my case, adjusting it upwards first, due to having a satisfaction scale of 4 parts), so that you end up with this&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-opportunity-algorithm&#34;&gt;The Opportunity Algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image of the opportunity algorithm&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/presentation.001-28jxl4y_hu9780605367064712980.webp 400w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/presentation.001-28jxl4y_hu2320321359076610231.webp 760w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/presentation.001-28jxl4y_hu14723826080612170379.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/presentation.001-28jxl4y_hu9780605367064712980.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
 So you will need a final row, row 10 to calculate the &lt;strong&gt;Opportunity Score&lt;/strong&gt;. This is outlined above, but to explain the contents of the image. You take the outcome of importance, which is your percentage, so 9.6 in this case and take away the outcome of satisfaction, again a percentage. So that would leave you with -0.1, then add back on the outcome percentage which is is 9.6 and you end up with the total opportunity score of 9.5. outcome importance + (outcome importance - outcome satisfaction) = Opportunity Score 9.6 + (9.6 - 9.7) = 9.5 This is not the most exciting opportunity score, the most exciting ones are more than 10, or better yet more than 12. Oh and here is why I said that you should start with the formulae for one question-worth of data and to split Importance and Satisfaction onto separate sheets&amp;hellip;Once you have created one column for Importance and Satisfaction data you can simply drag the formulae across all of your questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/C0V1I-bigQI?rel=0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;create-r-food&#34;&gt;Create R Food&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having done all that you need to get your data into columns for RStudio, specifically we want four columns to start off with: Job; Importance; Satisfaction; Opportunity; and Score. So that it looks like this&amp;hellip; 















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image showing the columns in the spreadsheet&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/becalculated.001-1mbcuiy_hu16210955959804757597.webp 400w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/becalculated.001-1mbcuiy_hu6338840829146341820.webp 760w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/becalculated.001-1mbcuiy_hu13145842533791863457.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/becalculated.001-1mbcuiy_hu16210955959804757597.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
 Tip to get your data from rows to these columns use the transpose(array) function in Excel, here it is in action&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/sCdz2fOSWAI?rel=0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-3-get-started&#34;&gt;Step 3: Get Sta(R)ted&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install R from the R Archive:&lt;/strong&gt; Pick a mirror close-by (geographically speaking), e.g in UK - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stats.bris.ac.uk/R/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;University of Bristol&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.ma.imperial.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Imperial College London&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mac tip:&lt;/strong&gt; make sure that you check the MD5 hash and SHA hash match. You can do this quickly and easily in terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/HHdrIlHS2-4?rel=0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;\[Mac only\]:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.xquartz.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;XQuartz&lt;/a&gt; Install - information about this is provided at R Archive above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install RStudio:&lt;/strong&gt; again do check the MD5. You can get the installer here - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download/#download&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download/#download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-4-ooooh-arrrrr&#34;&gt;Step 4: OoooH aRrrrr&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Launch RStudio and have a go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image of the RStudio UI&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/RStudio-console-u9gkdl_hu18059678836653725427.webp 400w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/RStudio-console-u9gkdl_hu10876822247238170187.webp 760w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/RStudio-console-u9gkdl_hu15977988678247841919.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/RStudio-console-u9gkdl_hu18059678836653725427.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;556&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Image of the RStudio UI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now that you have done all of the preparation you can actually start to create plots. Before you do anything else you need to load your library. In this case we are using ggplot2 which is part of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tidyverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hadley Wickham&amp;rsquo;s (and others) Tidyverse&lt;/a&gt; - packages for R with standardised concepts and grammar. This is a good place to start as I have found that some of the R packages are quite idiosyncratic and it can take a bit of time to wrap your head around the internal logic, whereas the Tidyverse stuff all made a lot of sense. This could be because I originally learned to code in the JavaScript iteration of &lt;a href=&#34;https://processing.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Processing.&lt;/a&gt; RStudio comes with a lot of packages already, so&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34; data-lang=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;library&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;gpplot2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you needed to install it first and say you wanted the whole Tidyverse it would intuitively be&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34; data-lang=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;install.packages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;tidyverse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next you need to define your data and as you will recall we set that us as a .csv file on the desktop so lets call the data &amp;lsquo;jtdb&amp;rsquo;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34; data-lang=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;library&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;gpplot2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;jtbd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;read.csv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;~/Desktop/JTBD\_R/jtbd.csv&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;header&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;bp&#34;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;#This is a comment in RMarkup, &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;#so lets also find out about the data itself by using the summary function summary(jtbd) &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Result in the console:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fionamacneill.co.uk/blog/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/resultinconsole-t8dbkw.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Screenshot of results in console&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/resultinconsole-t8dbkw_hu15406952014914648873.webp 400w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/resultinconsole-t8dbkw_hu14720792961774716272.webp 760w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/resultinconsole-t8dbkw_hu15676726823077579924.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/resultinconsole-t8dbkw_hu15406952014914648873.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;515&#34;
               height=&#34;339&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; Well&amp;hellip;that is jolly helpful information!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;now-for-the-plot-part&#34;&gt;Now for the plot part:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34; data-lang=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;#the plot mapping - telling where your data to map on the axis &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;ggplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;jtbd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;aes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;Importance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;Satisfaction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# the &amp;#34;+&amp;#34; allows you to add another function, each function goes on its own layer, &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;#so the order is important for example geom_point defines your data as points on the plot &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;geom_point&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;blue&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;alpha&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;0.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# To map aesthetics in a more intentional way - for instance adding labels, &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# we can use another function geom label which requires two variables &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;#(in this case Importance and Satisfaction) &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# and tell it which column to get the labels from, in this case, the &amp;#34;Job&amp;#34; column &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;geom_label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;aes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;jtbd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;Job&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;nudge_y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;0.08&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;nudge_x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;0.06&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;hjust&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;right&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;alpha&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;0.8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This gives a starter plot like this&amp;hellip; [















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Image of starter plot&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/star_R-244yio2_hu13346763320747740684.webp 400w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/star_R-244yio2_hu7961699609849074676.webp 760w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/star_R-244yio2_hu5849118592068151610.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/star_R-244yio2_hu13346763320747740684.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;408&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
. Just to prove that it is easy to get started I gave myself a little challenge&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/NJY0dQdV-7I?rel=0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that it is really all about the aesthetics with this particular plot. Specifically I added a data.frame (a container for data) for each aesthetic element such as text, lines, shaded polygons and areas. These were then called as shown below&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34; data-lang=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;#Labels for the areas of the plot &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;labelover&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;data.frame&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;9.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;OVERSERVED&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;#Potential for disruption line &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;segment4&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;data.frame&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;xend&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;yend&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;#further down in the code where the plot is created - I call these&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;ggplot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;jtbd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;aes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;Importance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;Satisfaction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;#Calling the text &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;geom_text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;labelover&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;aes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;#Calling the &amp;#39;potential for disruption line&amp;#39; and adding some annotation to it &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;geom_segment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;segment4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;aes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;xend&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;xend&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;yend&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;yend&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;alpha&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;0.2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;linetype&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;annotate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;text&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;5.1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;label&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Potential for disruption&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;step-5-aesthetics&#34;&gt;Step 5: Aesthetics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well that provides an overview of the basics the rest will be based on your own aesthetic decisions. So I have provided the full code work-up with annotation below and recommend that you have a go and explore. Also if any of you are R and ggplot2 &amp;lsquo;pros&amp;rsquo; I am open to feedback as I am sure that it could be improved. To summarise, from my perspective using RStudio has provided the following benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A fast way to create reproducible visualisations of JTBD data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An effective way to create prototype data visualisations for a range of design contexts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An inexpensive option when compared to other data packages. Although I can get a student discount on software at the moment, I was thinking about the long term and developing a skill with an open source package&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has helped me to think differently about data and to iterate visualisations in the same way that I would with other design projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is immensely satisfying&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-reading&#34;&gt;Further Reading:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RStudio online learning materials: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/online-learning/#DataScience&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.rstudio.com/online-learning/#DataScience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RMarkdown gallery for ideas: &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/gallery.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/gallery.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RStudio Cheatsheets (they taught me pretty much everything that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t figure out from the built-in docs): &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/resources/cheatsheets/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.rstudio.com/resources/cheatsheets/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the Tidyverse: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tidyverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.tidyverse.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Josephy, J. (2016) &amp;lsquo;Jobs to be done - a better way to innovate&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;Webcredible blog&lt;/em&gt;, 19 May. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.webcredible.com/blog/may16-jobs-be-done-better-way-innovate/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.webcredible.com/blog/may16-jobs-be-done-better-way-innovate/&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed: 23 March 2018).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Klement, A. (2016) &amp;lsquo;Designing features using job stories&amp;rsquo;, in &lt;em&gt;Intercom on Jobs-to-be-Done&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/em&gt; pp. 28-80. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.intercom.com/books/jobs-to-be-done&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.intercom.com/books/jobs-to-be-done&lt;/a&gt; (Downloaded: 24 March 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McGovern, G. (2010) &lt;em&gt;The stranger&amp;rsquo;s long neck: How to deliver what your customers really want&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;online&lt;/em&gt;. London: A &amp;amp; C Black.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McGovern, G. (2017) &amp;lsquo;Measuring customer effort with Top Tasks&amp;rsquo; &lt;/p&gt;
\[_PowerPoint_ presentation\]&lt;p&gt;. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/uxbri/measuring-customer-effort-with-top-tasks-gerry-mcgovern&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.slideshare.net/uxbri/measuring-customer-effort-with-top-tasks-gerry-mcgovern&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed: 23 February 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tufte, E. R. (2001) &lt;em&gt;The visual display of quantitative information&lt;/em&gt;. 2nd edn. USA, CT: Graphics Press. Reprint, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ulwick, A. W. (2016) &lt;em&gt;Jobs to be Done: Theory to Practice.&lt;/em&gt; Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.eu/7BpXFp0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://amzn.eu/7BpXFp0&lt;/a&gt; (Downloaded: 3 March 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ulwick, A. W. (2017) &amp;lsquo;The path to growth: The opportunity algorithm&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;The marketing journal,&lt;/em&gt; 9 July. Available at: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marketingjournal.org/the-path-to-growth-the-opportunity-algorithm-anthony-ulwick/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.marketingjournal.org/the-path-to-growth-the-opportunity-algorithm-anthony-ulwick/&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed: 23 March 2018).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;code&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access the code for this post on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/FionaMacNeill/OpportunityLandscape/blob/main/jtbd.R&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;public GitHub Repository, &amp;lsquo;OpportunityLandcape&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Creative Commons Licence&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/88x31_hu216248282441888343.webp 400w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/88x31_hu8837335831164863444.webp 760w,
               /post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/88x31_hu1479922774419710758.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2018/03/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r/images/88x31_hu216248282441888343.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;88&#34;
               height=&#34;31&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&lt;/a&gt;) Code for JTBD data visualisation by &lt;a href=&#34;http://fionamacneill.co.uk/blog/2018/03/24/ux-camp-brighton-2018-jobs-to-be-done-r&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fiona MacNeill&lt;/a&gt; is licensed under a &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;. Based on a work at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marketingjournal.org/the-path-to-growth-the-opportunity-algorithm-anthony-ulwick/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.marketingjournal.org/the-path-to-growth-the-opportunity-algorithm-anthony-ulwick/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edward Tufte (2001) would likely frown to see these lines - &amp;ldquo;erase non-data-ink&amp;rdquo; (p. 105).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Talk] Factors of Trust in IoT App Interfaces Redux</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2016/06/trust-in-iot-app-interfaces-redux/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2016/06/trust-in-iot-app-interfaces-redux/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;talk-presented-at-ux-camp-brighton-2016---redux-on-140616-at-68-middle-street&#34;&gt;Talk presented at UX Camp Brighton 2016 - Redux on 14/06/16 at 68 Middle Street&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://uxbrighton.org.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://uxbrighton.org.uk/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://fionamacneill.co.uk/blog/2016/03/19/talk-factors-of-trust-in-iot-app-interfaces/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;See original blog post&lt;/a&gt; for the version of this talk given at UX Camp Brighton, 2016 (19/03/16). Video version of original talk.&lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/160628235&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;FACTORS OF TRUST IN IOT APP INTERFACES&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/user10479357&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fiona MacNeill&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/160628235&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; height=&#34;600&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;session-description&#34;&gt;Session description:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does your app rely on OAuth to offer connection to other apps and services? Based on my research studying app-to-device relationships in Internet of Things systems (e.g. Fitbit, Jawbone UP, Nest, SmartThings, Glooko), I have uncovered some best practice recommendations when it comes to inspiring trust within your interface. Trust definitions used in this video are from Pavlidis, Islam, Mouratidis, and Kearney (2014). This research is aligned with the SenSe research Cluster at the University of Brighton (secure and dependable software systems).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-sense&#34;&gt;About SenSe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brighton.ac.uk/research/our-research/life-health-and-physical-sciences/research-groups/computing/index.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The SenSe cluster&lt;/a&gt; aims to develop novel and pragmatic ways to assure the dependability of software systems with particular emphasis on security, trust and risk. We focus on theories from model-based engineering and analysis-based assurance to develop methods, models, practices and tools that promote the provision of security and dependability in complex interconnected and heterogeneous systems and information infrastructures that underpin our economy and society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;preliminary-recommendations&#34;&gt;Preliminary recommendations:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UX Questions to Ask in Relation to IoT Apps&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;#&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Category&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Questions to ask&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;System dialogues and Semantics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Are system dialogues consistent?&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For data permissions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;for use tips&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;for motivational messages&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Settings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Are all the settings housed together? Are items like the privacy policy and standards adherence available from this area? Can the Terms of Service (or a shortened format of ToSs) be accessed from within the app? Can connected apps and devices be reviewed/managed from within the app? Can support documentation be accessed from within the app?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Checkups for Setup/Workflow/Privacy &lt;/strong&gt;An essential part of onboarding. Also a method for supporting trust and helping users to invest time in learning the higher-level functions of an app, which promotes realisation of app benefits and long-term commitment to use of the app (Brignull, 2013).&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Periodic reminders about setup:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Can the setup be improved?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;What devices could be added safely?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;What benefits might be available as part of the system that the user may be unaware of?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Periodic review of workflow: &lt;/strong&gt;ask users to review the workflow in the system to add a level of human oversight. If the app is not accessed frequently then email and text message may be effective ways to prompt engagement. Think of it like entering a monthly gas meter reading.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Is an automated workflow still operating as intended?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Is the function still needed?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;A possible incentive could be that the workflow will stop/timeout if it is not reviewed a la IFTTT.&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Periodic review of p&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;rivacy: &lt;/strong&gt;privacy overview and audit tools within the app.&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;What information is shared with third-party developers?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;For what purpose/s is it shared?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;Non-legalese overview of changes to T&amp;Cs should be included in privacy checks.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Role/function of the app &lt;/strong&gt;Applies to central app and third-party apps.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;This sounds really obvious, but a lot of primary IoT apps don&#39;t actually explain their purpose within the system. What service does the app offer? What need does the app fulfill? What does the app do? How important is the app to the operation of the system? E.g. is it the primary interface or management tool for the system? What data does it need? - Make it clear what is used and why, in plain English.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health/status of hub/sensor/device &lt;/strong&gt;At any point in time the user should be able to view a basic log of what is currently going on in the system.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;What is going on in the system right now? Is recent system activity accessible? Is it possible to access logs from other time periods? Is it possible to see what communication channels are in operation? What third-party apps are connected to the system, what are they doing? What third-party devices are connected to the system, what are they doing? This should be more like what you expect from your banking app when it comes to overseeing the operation of high-importance health, home/business automation IoT systems.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OAUTH and API: secondary app data use&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Respect users and prove that your app is more trustworthy by only calling data that you are actually using. What data is needed into order to provide the desired third-party service? How is the data used to provide the service? &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; platform manufacturers/developers need to ensure that third-party apps aren&#39;t over-privileged in terms of the data they access and the calls they can make via APIs (See the work of  Fernandes, Jung and Prakesh, 2016). Developers need to state their intention when it comes to use of information that they call via the API. This doesn&#39;t stop those with malicious intent, but it helps users to distinguish between those who pay due diligence to privacy and those who are either malicious or sloppy.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;strong&gt;What is shared?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Can data access be allowed/disallowed? Once disallowed from the primary app, is this decision upheld? &lt;strong&gt;Ideal world:&lt;/strong&gt; provide granular options for allowing/disallowing access to data which is not necessary for the operation of the service offered by the app. Better yet, don&#39;t ask for the data at all if it isn&#39;t essential to operation.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access control&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is two-step authentication an option for the web app and login from a new device? Does the smartphone/tablet app offer biometric authentication? Does the app offer the option of setting a passcode for auto screen lock? Particularly if the app controls home appliances.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dependency and operational relationship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;As systems become more complicated it is crucial that the user is aided in building a mental picture of the basic configuration of the system. I [keep thinking of Max](https://cycling74.com/products/max/) when I think of this issue. Is logging available? What is going on in the system right now? What is attached to this system (devices/sensors/users)? Is the system visualised in any way?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try before you buy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Wearables have the right idea on this one, allowing you to trial a wearable companion app using your smartphone&#39;s built-in sensors. What if you could try out the perks of the system before you buy the actual device? Is a preview of how the app will operate with devices, provided as part of onboarding? Can you try of some of the functionality of the system without buying a system-specific device?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
\[alex\]&lt;p&gt;. (2016, May 2). &lt;em&gt;SmartThings platform security - response from Alex&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved June 13, 2016, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.smartthings.com/t/smartthings-platform-security-response-from-alex/46878&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://community.smartthings.com/t/smartthings-platform-security-response-from-alex/46878&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aliph, Inc. (2016). Jawbone UP (Version 4.13) &lt;/p&gt;
\[Mobile application software\]&lt;p&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/app/up-by-jawbone-track-up-move/id461125277?mt=8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/app/up-by-jawbone-track-up-move/id461125277?mt=8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barcena, M. B., Wueest, C., &amp;amp; Lau, H. (2014). How safe is your quantified self? (1.1). Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.symantec.com/content/en/us/enterprise/media/security_response/whitepapers/how-safe-is-your-quantified-self.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.symantec.com/content/en/us/enterprise/media/security_response/whitepapers/how-safe-is-your-quanti fied-self.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BBC (2016). &lt;em&gt;Hidden killers, series 1: 2. The Edwardian home&lt;/em&gt; Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/b03lyv9x/hidden-killers-series-1-2-the-edwardian-home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/b03lyv9x/hidden-killers-series-1-2-the-edwardian-home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilton, N. (2016, January 18). Nest thermostat glitch leaves users in the cold. The New York Times. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/14/fashion/nest-thermostat-glitch-battery-dies-software-freeze.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/14/fashion/nest-thermostat-glitch-battery-dies-software-freeze.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bradbury, D. (2015, November 26). Usability v safety: How to design our way to better security. The Guardian. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/media-network/2015/nov/26/usability-safety-how-to-design-better-security-technology&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/media-network/2015/nov/26/usability-safety-how-to-design-better-security-technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brooks, J. (2016, January 8). Fitbit hit with class action lawsuit over alleged misreading of heart rates &lt;/p&gt;
\[Blog post\]&lt;p&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://ww2.kqed.org/futureofyou/2016/01/08/fitbit-hit-with-class-action-lawsuit-over-alleged-misreading-of-heart-rates/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://ww2.kqed.org/futureofyou/2016/01/08/fitbit-hit-with-class-action-lawsuit-over-alleged-misreading-of-heart-rates/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brignull, H. (2013, March). &lt;em&gt;Ramp Up&lt;/em&gt;. Personalising the experience, Brighton. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://uxbrighton.org.uk/Personalisation-the-Experience/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://uxbrighton.org.uk/Personalisation-the-Experience/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brignull, H. (2016). &lt;em&gt;User interfaces designed to trick people&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved June 13, 2016, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://darkpatterns.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://darkpatterns.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BS ISO/IEC. (2011). Systems and software engineering — Systems and software quality requirement and evaluation (SQuaRE) — System and software quality models (ISO/IEC 25010:2011(E)) Switzerland: ISO/IEC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catalyst IT. (2016). Mahara (Version 1.10.5) &lt;/p&gt;
\[Computer software\]&lt;p&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://mahara.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://mahara.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chen, E. Y., Pei, Y., Chen, S., Tian, Y., Kotcher, R., &amp;amp; Tague, P. (2014). OAuth Demystified for mobile application developers. &lt;em&gt;CCS ’14 Proceedings of the 2014 ACM SIGSAC Conference on Computer and Communications Security&lt;/em&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=2660267.2660323&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;10.1145/2660267.2660323&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cluley, G. (2013, February 13). Jawbone accounts compromised by hackers - personal info accessed, passwords disabled &lt;/p&gt;
\[Blog post\]&lt;p&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://nakedsecurity.sophos.com/2013/02/13/jawbone-hack/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://nakedsecurity.sophos.com/2013/02/13/jawbone-hack/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cycling’74. &lt;em&gt;Max is a visual programming language for media&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved March 19, 2016, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://cycling74.com/products/max/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://cycling74.com/products/max/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ericsson. (2016, June). &lt;em&gt;Wearable technology and the Internet of things&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ericsson.com/thinkingahead/consumerlab/consumer-insights/wearable-technology-and-the-internet-of-things&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.ericsson.com/thinkingahead/consumerlab/consumer-insights/wearable-technology-and-the-internet-of-things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faily, S. (2014). Engaging stakeholders in security design: An assumption-driven approach. Proceedings of the Eighth International Symposium on Human Aspects of Information Security &amp;amp; Assurance (HAISA 2014), Plymouth, 21-29. doi:10.13140/2.1.3997.2647&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feamster, N. (2016, January 19). Who will secure the Internet of things? &lt;/p&gt;
\[Blog post\]&lt;p&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://freedom-to-tinker.com/blog/feamster/who-will-secure-the-internet-of-things/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://freedom-to-tinker.com/blog/feamster/who-will-secure-the-internet-of-things/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felt, A. P., Egelman, S., &amp;amp; Wagner, D. (2012). I’ve got 99 problems, but vibration ain’t one. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the second ACM workshop on Security and privacy in smartphones and mobile devices - SPSM ’12&lt;/em&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=2381934.2381943&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;10.1145/2381934.2381943&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Field, C. (2004, January 23). Danger high voltage! Edwardian electric Tablecloth uncovered Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.culture24.org.uk/history-and-heritage/art19432&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.culture24.org.uk/history-and-heritage/art19432&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fitbit, inc. (2016). Fitbit (Version 2.18) &lt;/p&gt;
\[Mobile application software\]&lt;p&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/app/fitbit/id462638897?mt=8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/app/fitbit/id462638897?mt=8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guadamuz, A. (2015). The monkey selfie: Copyright lessons for originality in photographs and internet jurisdiction. &lt;em&gt;Internet Policy Review&lt;/em&gt;. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://policyreview.info/articles/analysis/monkey-selfie-copyright-lessons-originality-photographs-and-internet-jurisdiction&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;10.14763/2016.1.398&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glooko, Inc. (2015). Glooko (Version 3.2) &lt;/p&gt;
\[Mobile application software\]&lt;p&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/app/glooko/id471942748?mt=8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/app/glooko/id471942748?mt=8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harrison, D., Marshall, P., Bianchi-Berthouze, N., &amp;amp; Bird, J. (2015). Activity tracking: Barriets, workarounds and customisation. Proceedings of UBICOMP ‘15, Osaka, Japan. doi:10.1145/2750858.2805832&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hess, W. (2015, May 7). &lt;em&gt;Onboarding: Designing Welcoming First Experiences&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved March 19, 2016, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://uxmag.com/articles/onboarding-designing-welcoming-first-experiences&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://uxmag.com/articles/onboarding-designing-welcoming-first-experiences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Higginbotham, S. (2016, January 22). Episode 42: These are the two biggest challenges facing the smart home Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://iotpodcast.com/2016/01/episode-42-these-are-the-two-biggest-challenges-facing-the-smart-home/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://iotpodcast.com/2016/01/episode-42-these-are-the-two-biggest-challenges-facing-the-smart-home/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Higginbotham, S. (2016, March 17). &lt;em&gt;Episode 50: Are your devices being held hostage?&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved March 28, 2016, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://iotpodcast.com/2016/03/nest-hostage/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://iotpodcast.com/2016/03/nest-hostage/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internet Policy Review. (2013). &lt;em&gt;Privacy &amp;amp; security&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved June 13, 2016, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://policyreview.info/categories/privacy-security&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://policyreview.info/categories/privacy-security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IoT security research at university of Michigan. (2016). Retrieved June 13, 2016, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://iotsecurity.eecs.umich.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://iotsecurity.eecs.umich.edu/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kastrenakes, J. (2016, March 10). Nest can now use your phone to tell when you’ve left the house Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theverge.com/2016/3/10/11188888/nest-now-uses-location-for-home-away-states-launches-family-accounts&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.theverge.com/2016/3/10/11188888/nest-now-uses-location-for-home-away-states-launches-family-accounts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kalloniatis, C., Mouratidis, H., Vassilis, M., Islam, S., Gritzalis, S., &amp;amp; Kavakli, E. (2014). Towards the design of secure and privacy-oriented Information Systems in the Cloud: Identifying the major concepts. Computer Stan- dards &amp;amp; Interfaces, 36(4), 759–775. doi:10.1016/j.csi.2013.12.010&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Krok, A. (2016, June 6). &lt;em&gt;British security firm hacks Mitsubishi Outlander via mobile app, Wi-Fi - Roadshow&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved June 12, 2016, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cnet.com/roadshow/news/british-security-firm-hacks-mitsubishi-outlander-via-mobile-app-wi-fi/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.cnet.com/roadshow/news/british-security-firm-hacks-mitsubishi-outlander-via-mobile-app-wi-fi/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lohr, S. (2016, June 9). Tony Fadell steps down amid tumult at nest, a Google acquisition. &lt;em&gt;Technology&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/06/04/technology/tony-fadell-nest-google-alphabet.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/06/04/technology/tony-fadell-nest-google-alphabet.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Malik, O. (2015, December 30). In Silicon valley now, it’s almost always winner takes all. &lt;em&gt;The New Yorker&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/tech/elements/in-silicon-valley-now-its-almost-always-winner-takes-all&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.newyorker.com/tech/elements/in-silicon-valley-now-its-almost-always-winner-takes-all&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;myDevices. (2016). &lt;em&gt;First IoT project builder - myDevices cayenne&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved March 19, 2016, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cayenne-mydevices.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.cayenne-mydevices.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nest Labs, Inc. (2016). Nest app (Version 5.2.2) &lt;/p&gt;
\[Mobile application software\]&lt;p&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/app/nest-app/id464988855?mt=8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/app/nest-app/id464988855?mt=8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O’Neill, O. (2002). A question of trust: The BBC Reith lectures 2002 (4th ed.). United Kingdom: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O’Neill, O. (2013, September 25). How to trust intelligently &lt;/p&gt;
\[Blog post\]&lt;p&gt;. Retrieved from [http://blog.ted.com/ how-to-trust-intelligently/](&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.ted.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://blog.ted.com/&lt;/a&gt; how-to-trust-intelligently/)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pavlidis, M., Islam, S., Mouratidis, H., &amp;amp; Kearney, P. (2014). Modeling trust relationships for developing trust- worthy Information systems. International Journal of Information System Modelling and Design, 5(1), 25–48. doi:10.4018/2014010102&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;openHAB. (2016). &lt;em&gt;OpenHAB&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved June 13, 2016, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openhab.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.openhab.org/&lt;/a&gt; Rogers, C. Martha Lane Fox interviewed by the house magazine Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://doteveryone.org.uk/blog/2016/05/martha-lane-fox-in-the-house-magazine/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doteveryone.org.uk/blog/2016/05/martha-lane-fox-in-the-house-magazine/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sasse, A. (2015). Scaring and bullying people into security won’t work. IEEE Security &amp;amp; Privacy 13(3), 80-83. doi:10.1109/MSP.2015.65&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scoseria, I. (2016). MyDevices launches cayenne, the world’s First drag-and-drop IoT project builder. Retrieved 19 March 2016, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://press.mydevices.com/2016/01/26/mydevices-launches-cayenne-the-worlds-first-drag-and-drop-iot-project-builder/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://press.mydevices.com/2016/01/26/mydevices-launches-cayenne-the-worlds-first-drag-and-drop-iot-project-builder/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secure Tropos. (2013). SecTro2 (Version 2.1) &lt;/p&gt;
\[Computer software\]&lt;p&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.omilab.org/web/secure-tropos/environment&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.omilab.org/web/secure-tropos/environment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sempers, P. (2015, October 19). &lt;em&gt;Samsung Smartthings app tour on galaxy s6 - #ThinkSmartThings&lt;/em&gt; Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UmqmpJg_xFA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UmqmpJg_xFA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seuss (1999). &lt;em&gt;The cat in the hat&lt;/em&gt; (5th ed.). New York: Random House USA Children’s Books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spary, S. (2016, January 6). Online criminals are tageting Fitbit user accounts. BuzzFeed News. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.buzzfeed.com/saraspary/online-criminals-are-targeting-fitbit-user-accounts&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.buzzfeed.com/saraspary/online-criminals-are-targeting-fitbit-user-accounts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SmartThings, Inc. (2016). SmartThings Mobile (Version 2.0.7) &lt;/p&gt;
\[Mobile application software\]&lt;p&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/app/smartthings-mobile/id590800740?mt=8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/app/smartthings-mobile/id590800740?mt=8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wollerton, M. (2016, May 23). The best smart hub. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://thewirecutter.com/reviews/best-smart-hub/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://thewirecutter.com/reviews/best-smart-hub/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woods, B. (2016, January 19). &lt;em&gt;Hippocratic oath for connected medical devices&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved June 12, 2016, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iamthecavalry.org/domains/medical/oath/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.iamthecavalry.org/domains/medical/oath/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-current-personal-hero&#34;&gt;My current personal hero:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Hxdqp3N_ymU&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wireframes: Are friends electric</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The title of this blog post is a nod in the direction of &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/ZF4Z6smOrZw&#34; title=&#34;Gary Numan in 1979&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mr. Gary Numan&lt;/a&gt;. It felt like the right time to get some simple mock-ups ready in Adobe Fireworks; thus we became electric and moved away from paper, but only temporarily as this will speedup some of the low-fi paper prototypes that I plan later on. Fireworks seemed like the best choice as it is javascript-centric and I think that in all likelihood the final product would be coded in &lt;a href=&#34;http://getbootstrap.com/&#34; title=&#34;Bootstrap main site&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bootstrap JS&lt;/a&gt; (but that would be up to my hypothetical developer). This is going to be a very long journal entry as there were a lot of decisions involved in taking the jump to the new format. Bear with me. So first on my list, although I did it second (as I &amp;rsquo;think&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;in colour&lt;/em&gt;) was to create a flexible frame-based mock-up of a topic page where learning content would be delivered. The frame size is set to 805 X 604 as this is the size of the window typically specified by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nottingham.ac.uk/xerte/index.aspx&#34; title=&#34;Xerte webpage&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Xerte&lt;/a&gt;, the University of Nottingham&amp;rsquo;s Learning Object creation tool. The specific Xerte example that I drew inspiration from can be found at the following link: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nottingham.ac.uk/toolkits/play_8203&#34; title=&#34;Xerte online toolkit example&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.nottingham.ac.uk/toolkits/play_8203&lt;/a&gt;. You will see that my progression buttons at the bottom of the page bears some resemblance to theirs, as I felt that it was an elegant solution to the problem in both a browser window and on a mobile device. I would be sure to cite this in my final code! However, I do think that a bit of polishing is needed and possibly an alternative for testing purposes; I think that the &amp;ldquo;2 / 4&amp;rdquo; looks like a button too, which could lead to confusion, so that is something to fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-first-simple-grey-scale-version&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;First simple grey scale wireframe version 1&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframe1-20fxmyq_hu4755069295801087234.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframe1-20fxmyq_hu5768807124856787339.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframe1-20fxmyq_hu13844897398610554019.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframe1-20fxmyq_hu4755069295801087234.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      First simple grey scale version
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Several key decisions have gone into the wireframes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I decided to use icons in order to minimise the size of side tabs (rather than text alone). I did not take this decision lightly as icons can be problematic due to individual interpretation. I looked through a cross section of modern icon collections online and I felt that the icons shown above were modern and appropriate for the user group of the learning object. The &lt;em&gt;Index&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Save&lt;/em&gt; icons are directly from the collection, &lt;em&gt;Glossary/Help&lt;/em&gt; button is my own unique icon taking some inspiration from the icon set. I found the icon set &lt;a href=&#34;http://ewebdesign.com/web-outline-icons/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;at the ewebdesign website&lt;/a&gt;. The icon set is originally from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dryicons.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dry Icons site&lt;/a&gt; and is licensed under a &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 unported license&lt;/a&gt;). So, the source of these icons would need to be cited in the code and site attributions. However at this point in the design process they are really just placeholders pending the decision of the Graphic Designer on the eventual (hypothetical) design team. I did try out an alternative save button from the icon set, just to test. However it did not work as well as the conventional floppy disk icon as shown below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Alternative save button&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframeALTsavebutton-12p9ckg_hu818319912957950109.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframeALTsavebutton-12p9ckg_hu7166381454353511546.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframeALTsavebutton-12p9ckg_hu16198982411900179215.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframeALTsavebutton-12p9ckg_hu818319912957950109.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;183&#34;
               height=&#34;281&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;cog&lt;/em&gt; on the bottom left, as a button to access settings &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; correct in terms of positioning and I think that it stands out as an interactive tool without adding too much distraction to the learning environment. This cog is my own Adobe Illustrator drawing based on a cog designed by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gentleface.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.gentleface.com&lt;/a&gt; under a [Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 unported license] (&lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/&lt;/a&gt;) - as this is student work I am definitely not getting any commercial gain from this). I found the cog at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iconfinder.com/icons/42195/cog_icon#size=48&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;iconfinder.com&lt;/a&gt;. The positioning and style of the cog was a result of my earlier on-paper sketching, so I feel that, that process was particularly valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revisiting the wireframe above it seems that the audio mute button might want to be bigger in order to be more symmetrical with the settings button. I liberated the audio from the &amp;ldquo;settings&amp;rdquo; area; I have yet to fully define how the settings area will look. I did this because if an end-user were accessing the Learning Object from a mobile device they would want the default to be mute and then they could choose to turn on the audio narrative if they had headphones plugged into their device. Based on this I felt that making the audio settings more present and clickable/tapable would benefit, both users on desktop computers in office environments where computer noise might not be preferable and those on mobile devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A closer inspection of the web site&amp;rsquo;s terms showed that the icons cannot be transformed in any way and have to be used as-is. The colour is inverted but other than that there are no structural changes. This suggests that these icons will need to be replaced in the final version of the site. &lt;a href=&#34;http://dryicons.com/terms/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;See free license agreement section&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;experiment-time&#34;&gt;Experiment Time!!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then in reference to decision 1 above, I wondered if the icons could stand on their own without the titles. So I gave that a go&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Basic Wireframe 2&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframe2-2gpk21n_hu17715602071537010788.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframe2-2gpk21n_hu11105332374687761970.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframe2-2gpk21n_hu15186418772630552566.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframe2-2gpk21n_hu17715602071537010788.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then I thought how do you deal with any uncertainty about the icons. Perhaps a JS popover? I explored how that would look, just out of interest. I don&amp;rsquo;t think that it was successful (click on the image below for the interactive version).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Basic Wireframe 3&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframe3-2ax1oj2_hu6617450510911057937.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframe3-2ax1oj2_hu10066276439964552010.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframe3-2ax1oj2_hu13290360167631772346.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/basicwireframe3-2ax1oj2_hu6617450510911057937.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned at the beginning of this post, I started with colour prototypes. The colour scheme was loosely inspired by the University of Exeter&amp;rsquo;s blue, as outlined in their &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.exeter.ac.uk/designstudio/visualidentity/thelogo/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;visual identity guidelines&lt;/a&gt; although the branding for university-x needs a bit more thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colour hex values annotation is included for later reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Basic Wireframe 4&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe_fontsizeadjusted-1a2s480_hu3962015454183725247.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe_fontsizeadjusted-1a2s480_hu14440175548911936673.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe_fontsizeadjusted-1a2s480_hu14510295212529971845.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe_fontsizeadjusted-1a2s480_hu3962015454183725247.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the accessibility settings it is necessary for the user to be able to change the font in the interface. I tried a few experiments to see how this would look, as different fonts take up differing amounts of space on the page. It would also be necessary to provide a contextual preview of these settings as users altered them, so they could see how the fonts and other adjustments would manifest. I chose the fonts very carefully as although it would be great to offer a font like Verdana as a legible sans-serif, particularly because it distinguishes letters which often get confused &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;L&amp;rdquo;, there are some font licensing considerations to bear in mind. I liked the &lt;a href=&#34;http://webaim.org/techniques/fonts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;example provided by the WebAIM accessibility website&lt;/a&gt; where they use the word &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Illustration&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; to show the legibility difference between Arial and Verdana: e.g. in Verdana: Illustration and Arial: Illustration. I have included this word in my examples below to help show differences between the fonts. With regard the licensing issue mentioned above, as the ethos of this learning object is open source and having checked font distribution licensing for Verdana, Arial and others and finding that they were not ideal, I sought open source alternatives. Examples and annotation is provided below. It is also important the the selected fonts provide language support for translation engine purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;font-1---pt-sans&#34;&gt;Font 1 - PT Sans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Font 1, the default, is PT Sans (shown in all visual examples above) a family licensed by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.paratype.com/public/pt_openlicense_eng.asp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the ParaType Ltd foundry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;font-2---liberation-sans&#34;&gt;Font 2 - Liberation Sans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Font 2 - Liberation at 12pt - license: &lt;a href=&#34;http://scripts.sil.org/cms/scripts/page.php?site_id=nrsi&amp;amp;id=OFL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SIL Open Font License&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://fontlibrary.org/en/font/liberation-sans&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;source on font library website&lt;/a&gt;. Partial language support, stated 99% at fontlibrary.org&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments:&lt;/strong&gt; this font does distinguish between &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;L&lt;/em&gt; and is quite a standard sans-serif. A bit more compact than PT Sans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Colour wireframe font 2&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe2_font2-29pct79_hu2642842995054355694.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe2_font2-29pct79_hu11190625951011260951.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe2_font2-29pct79_hu14459768869655711979.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe2_font2-29pct79_hu2642842995054355694.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;font-3---encode-sans&#34;&gt;Font 3 - Encode Sans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Font 3 - Encode Sans at 12pt - license: &lt;a href=&#34;http://scripts.sil.org/cms/scripts/page.php?site_id=nrsi&amp;amp;id=OFL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SIL Open Font License&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://fontlibrary.org/en/font/encode-sans&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;source on font website&lt;/a&gt;. Full language support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments:&lt;/strong&gt; this font uses height to differentiate, &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;L&lt;/em&gt;. It features more curves than some of the other fonts, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a lot of white space, so although it is condensed it might be better for some dylexic readers as this will limit the ghosting effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;colour wireframe 3 font 3&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe3_font3-126bofy_hu4000536106193367363.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe3_font3-126bofy_hu9620818128454166846.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe3_font3-126bofy_hu12622421538842600077.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe3_font3-126bofy_hu4000536106193367363.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;font-4---crimson&#34;&gt;Font 4 - Crimson&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Font 4 - Crimson at 12pt - the serif option. - license: [SIL Open Font License] (&lt;a href=&#34;http://scripts.sil.org/cms/scripts/page.php?site_id=nrsi&amp;amp;id=OFL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://scripts.sil.org/cms/scripts/page.php?site_id=nrsi&amp;id=OFL&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://fontlibrary.org/en/font/crimson&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;source on font website&lt;/a&gt;. Full language support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments:&lt;/strong&gt; my own personal tendency is to go for sans-serif fonts, however some users may prefer a serif font designed for screen reading. This font bears some similarity to both Georgia and Lucinda, I have found &lt;a href=&#34;ttp://webstyleguide.com/wsg3/8-typography/4-web-typefaces.html&#34;&gt;the chapter on Typography in the web style guide&lt;/a&gt; to be particularly informative in this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Colour wireframe font 4&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe4_font4-1ynve9s_hu17930204210042155405.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe4_font4-1ynve9s_hu16177096240694772074.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe4_font4-1ynve9s_hu2130270433694737462.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe4_font4-1ynve9s_hu17930204210042155405.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;font-5---earthbound&#34;&gt;Font 5 - Earthbound&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Font 5 - Earthbound at 12pt - license: &lt;a href=&#34;http://scripts.sil.org/cms/scripts/page.php?site_id=nrsi&amp;amp;id=OFL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SIL Open Font License&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://fontlibrary.org/en/font/earthbound&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;source on font website&lt;/a&gt;. Full language support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments:&lt;/strong&gt; this is quite a curvy font, which once again uses character height as well as curved &lt;em&gt;L&lt;/em&gt; to differentiate between &lt;em&gt;L&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Colour wireframe font 5&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe5_font5-1bl790i_hu3599910284337286609.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe5_font5-1bl790i_hu5916020492642913342.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe5_font5-1bl790i_hu6359525453526786157.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe5_font5-1bl790i_hu3599910284337286609.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;font-6---opendyslexic&#34;&gt;Font 6 - OpenDyslexic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Font 6 - OpenDyslexic at 12pt - a font specifically designed for Dyslexic readers - &lt;a href=&#34;http://opendyslexic.org/legal/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;license for OpenDyslexic&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://gumroad.com/l/OpenDyslexic&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;source on gumroad.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments:&lt;/strong&gt; Stylistically I find this font to err on the side of the 1970s, however at least personally I have found that it does increase my personal reading speed. I believe there is value in including it as an option in the settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Colour wireframe font 6&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe6_font6-1qi0s2q_hu1542065031022699807.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe6_font6-1qi0s2q_hu13491192536604010808.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe6_font6-1qi0s2q_hu10168016022324612467.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe6_font6-1qi0s2q_hu1542065031022699807.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to explore how the font would look if the size were increased and how that would be tacked with formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;colour wireframe font resized&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe_fontsizeadjusted2-rwctgy_hu8830594416216882377.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe_fontsizeadjusted2-rwctgy_hu12757116691580997601.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe_fontsizeadjusted2-rwctgy_hu412093424094026352.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframe_fontsizeadjusted2-rwctgy_hu8830594416216882377.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fonts-that-i-decided-against-and-size-decision&#34;&gt;Fonts that I decided against and size decision&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took a look at some Google fonts, but felt that they did not fit the licensing needs as well as the SIL OFL fonts. Here are some of the fonts that I reviewed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/fonts#ReviewPlace:refine/Collection:PT&amp;#43;Sans%7cRoboto%7cTenor&amp;#43;Sans&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PT San | Roboto | Tenor Sans&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also looked at an open font called &lt;a href=&#34;https://fontlibrary.org/en/font/gen-light&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gen&lt;/a&gt; however when I looked at the word &lt;em&gt;Illustration&lt;/em&gt; there was no differentiation between &lt;em&gt;L&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt;. In terms of the default size, I decided on 12pt based on some of the guidance included in the Web Style Guide 3rd addition. Specifically the &lt;a href=&#34;http://webstyleguide.com/wsg3/8-typography/4a-type-size-legibility.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Type Sizes for Comfortable Reading&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-influential-sources-for-this-process&#34;&gt;Some influential sources for this process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The incredibly helpful resources at the WebAIM site:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://webaim.org/techniques/fonts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fonts page on the WebAIM site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://webaim.org/standards/wcag/checklist&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Their WCAG 2.0 Checklist&lt;/a&gt;, which would prove useful for both the execution of, and the content within the Learning Object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The W3C Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;further-treatments---looking-at-the-background-colour-options-for-the-settings&#34;&gt;Further treatments - looking at the background colour options for the settings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NB. the default colour is the cream colour shown in the images above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Colour wireframe background 1&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk1_font1-1qeeorl_hu17812241953243827272.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk1_font1-1qeeorl_hu14919988859387437834.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk1_font1-1qeeorl_hu3179356474187420079.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk1_font1-1qeeorl_hu17812241953243827272.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Alt background 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Colour wireframe background 2&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk2_font1-thkh8p_hu8677875439306230527.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk2_font1-thkh8p_hu17405592025044082399.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk2_font1-thkh8p_hu8239819719217970856.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk2_font1-thkh8p_hu8677875439306230527.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Alt background 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Colour wireframe background 3&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk3_font1-2acivda_hu15999637230729689607.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk3_font1-2acivda_hu3998599831024841306.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk3_font1-2acivda_hu14401875355227057815.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk3_font1-2acivda_hu15999637230729689607.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Alt background 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Colour wireframe background 4&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk4_font1-2lnx1ce_hu615165798391736765.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk4_font1-2lnx1ce_hu932288164301224201.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk4_font1-2lnx1ce_hu14665520479591280454.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk4_font1-2lnx1ce_hu615165798391736765.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Alt background 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example of background colour change and font change&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;colour wireframe background 4 and font 6&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk4_font6-18b56s3_hu15938526009489904780.webp 400w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk4_font6-18b56s3_hu5112154137840759784.webp 760w,
               /post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk4_font6-18b56s3_hu3508651775774666395.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2016/01/wireframes-are-friends-electric/images/colourwireframebk4_font6-18b56s3_hu15938526009489904780.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-inspiration&#34;&gt;Further inspiration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of further development of the settings and help/glossary, I found the following blog posts from the Nielsen Norman Group (NNG) to be particularly helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nngroup.com/articles/overuse-of-overlays/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Overuse of Overlays: How to Avoid Misusing Lightboxes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. What not to do!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nngroup.com/articles/pop-up-adaptive-help/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pop-ups and Adaptive Help Get a Refresh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. The example of the Google Play and AdWords help tools could offer an elegant solution for the glossary/help pop-up. Settings may be too involved to be a pop-up, as previously a preview of how the settings adjust the content would be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case against flat design. There are some helpful tips in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nngroup.com/articles/flat-design/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this blog post from NNG about hinting at interactivity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references-in-addition-to-websites-listed-above&#34;&gt;References (in addition to websites listed above)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodyear, P. (2005). Educational design and networked learning: Patterns, pattern languages and design practice. &lt;em&gt;Australasian Journal of Educational Technology, 21&lt;/em&gt;(1). Advance online publication. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://ajet.org.au/index.php/AJET/article/view/1344&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://ajet.org.au/index.php/AJET/article/view/1344&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green, S., Jones, R., Pearson, E., &amp;amp; Gkatzidou, S. (2006). Accessibility and adaptability of learning objects: Responding to metadata, learning patterns and profiles of needs and preferences. &lt;em&gt;Alt-J, Research in Learning Technology, 14&lt;/em&gt;(1), 117-129. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://repository.alt.ac.uk/104/1/ALT_J_Vol14_No1_2006_Accessibility%20and%20adaptability.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://repository.alt.ac.uk/104/1/ALT_J_Vol14_No1_2006_Accessibility%20and%20adaptability.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith, R. S. (2004). Guidelines for authors of learning objects. Retrieved from NMC: New Media Consortium website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nmc.org/publication/guidelines-for-authors-of-learning-objects/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.nmc.org/publication/guidelines-for-authors-of-learning-objects/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wireframes: Pondering Topic Pages</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/wireframes-pondering-topic-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/wireframes-pondering-topic-pages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Wireframe 4&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2015/12/wireframes-pondering-topic-pages/images/wireframe04-13nl89i_hu10979425404193427517.webp 400w,
               /post/2015/12/wireframes-pondering-topic-pages/images/wireframe04-13nl89i_hu17593920240945140589.webp 760w,
               /post/2015/12/wireframes-pondering-topic-pages/images/wireframe04-13nl89i_hu14422716716271756973.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/wireframes-pondering-topic-pages/images/wireframe04-13nl89i_hu10979425404193427517.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;525&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Van Duyne, D. K., Landay, J. A., &amp;amp; Hong, J. I. (2007). &lt;em&gt;The design of sites: Patterns for creating winning web sites&lt;/em&gt; (2nd ed.). USA: Prentice Hall PTR.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wireframe sketching: looking at the index/home</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/wireframe-sketching-looking-at-the-indexhome/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/wireframe-sketching-looking-at-the-indexhome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;wireframe sketches part 3&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2015/12/wireframe-sketching-looking-at-the-indexhome/images/03wireframes-oci7on_hu8736382556772067287.webp 400w,
               /post/2015/12/wireframe-sketching-looking-at-the-indexhome/images/03wireframes-oci7on_hu6739993620829097616.webp 760w,
               /post/2015/12/wireframe-sketching-looking-at-the-indexhome/images/03wireframes-oci7on_hu3293666610607364015.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/wireframe-sketching-looking-at-the-indexhome/images/03wireframes-oci7on_hu8736382556772067287.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;539&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Van Duyne, D. K., Landay, J. A., &amp;amp; Hong, J. I. (2007). &lt;em&gt;The design of sites: Patterns for creating winning web sites&lt;/em&gt; (2nd ed.). USA: Prentice Hall PTR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usability.gov&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;usability.gov&lt;/a&gt; website I mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I particularly like the quick reference tabs on the left of the site, which slide out on hover. Also the type enlargement tool on their site, it is easy to use and very effective. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.usability.gov/site-tour.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Their site tour page&lt;/a&gt; which provides an overview is really fascinating, showing the decisions that they made and why. I have also watched their webinar about the revamp of the site, featured on the page above. Some key questions, &lt;em&gt;funnily enough I keep coming back to these too!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the goals of this website (in my case web application in the form of a Learning Object)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is the audience and who are our users?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are their goals?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Major discoveries, minor anguish</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You may ask, what happened to you Fiona, between 6/12 and 20/12? Well this is what happened. I was teaching an online course called the 12 Apps of Christmas (a satellite of course run at Regent&amp;rsquo;s University, London) and it was ALL consuming. I was also working on my Learning Object project during this time (and you thought I was slacking!) however, for the most part I have to admit to reverting to paper reflections for a while, due to sheer convenience. Currently my notes are collectively living on bits of scrap-paper, serviettes/napkins, and Evernote entries. I plan to pull them together here over the next few days, a process that I have started with the inclusion of &lt;a href=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2015/12/real-time-reflection-experience-of-completing-a-learning-object/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;my reflection of using a learning object as an end user&lt;/a&gt;, I will include more on that later in the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-a-few-relevant-reflections-from-my-experience-working-on-12-apps-of-christmas&#34;&gt;First a few relevant reflections from my experience working on 12 Apps of Christmas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the course we ran a completion survey. Although there is only a small number of responses so far (11 respondents out of 192 course subscribers; survey is open until the end of January), the responses do correlate with some of the observations that I had made. As the course was designed as an opportunity for academic staff, the insights into that population are helpful as I move forward with the Learning Object design, that is geared to the same community. &lt;em&gt;Course subscribers really appreciated clear image-based instructions with accompanying step-by-step written annotation.&lt;/em&gt; Commentary: This could inform aspects of user documentation for the Learning Object. Specifically, the idea to include accompanying PDF guides for topics is supported by this anecdotal evidence. &lt;em&gt;Four learning activities or exercises is about the right number to minimise time and interest drop-off.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;screenshot of some of the results&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/Screen-Shot-2015-12-28-at-14.44.10-21v040u_hu7113386726983320215.webp 400w,
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/Screen-Shot-2015-12-28-at-14.44.10-21v040u_hu1696597203425239464.webp 760w,
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/Screen-Shot-2015-12-28-at-14.44.10-21v040u_hu3782701086059396519.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/Screen-Shot-2015-12-28-at-14.44.10-21v040u_hu7113386726983320215.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;281&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;commentary&#34;&gt;Commentary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a structure of 12+ exercises due to the preexisting structure of the 12 apps course, but interest did drop-off sharply after the 4th day (1 exercise per day). However, when considering a learning object this would seem like a pertinent observation. Also the topic of the learning object is probably (lets be honest) less interesting than learning about mobile apps presented with a festive theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Google Analytics for Dec 2015&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/Screen-Shot-2015-12-28-at-14.47.21-1pef2hw_hu10848913839219444700.webp 400w,
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/Screen-Shot-2015-12-28-at-14.47.21-1pef2hw_hu8936587814933441788.webp 760w,
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/Screen-Shot-2015-12-28-at-14.47.21-1pef2hw_hu16853473938062625621.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/Screen-Shot-2015-12-28-at-14.47.21-1pef2hw_hu10848913839219444700.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;693&#34;
               height=&#34;464&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beware of the inverse Field of Dreams (1989) effect&amp;hellip;If you build it, they won&amp;rsquo;t necessarily come&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-as-much-web-traffic-as-we-did-took-major-effort&#34;&gt;Getting as much web traffic as we did took major effort&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building and maintaining the blog where we delivered the content; promoting the content via Twitter and keeping to our self-imposed publishing deadlines. In spite of this effort, the traffic dropped off after the 4th day, as documented in the screenshot from the site analytics above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that it is important to admit that learning resource content and therefore the Learning Object that I am designing has a very limited shelf-life, both in the sense of consumable shelf-life and continued relevance. This does not undermine the reusable goal of the Learning Object and it&amp;rsquo;s Open Education ethos, but it does mean that it is more of a reusable template as opposed to being completely reusable in and of itself. I think that best way of considering the reuse aspect is that this Learning Object can be reused through a simple hyperlink to it, but is not geared towards being part of a open learning object repository (it would continue to live with the client university, university-x). Furthermore with my learning technologist hat on, driving traffic to the learning object would require a clearly structured publicity plan so that it was viewed as a timely tool in relation to the changes to DSA funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, this point really speaks to the importance of the delivery environment and how it portrays the importance of the Learning Object. As the Learning Object is academic staff-focused it is not best placed within the Virtual Learning Environment, a more centralised site with a focus on learning and teaching guidance at the fictional client university may be more appropriate. This will help to ensure that our main target audience have ready access and memorable access. So this is the spot in my thought process where I revised the purpose &lt;strong&gt;sentence&lt;/strong&gt; slightly, as it wasn&amp;rsquo;t quite right:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes to funding for support of disabled students, necessitates the need to increase academic staff knowledge of best practices involving technology, to help disabled students and to fill areas of deficit created by the reduction of funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-act-of-doing-this-resulted-in-a-crucial-thought&#34;&gt;The act of doing this resulted in a crucial thought&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Learning Object is to promote awareness of DSA and accessible practices. How on earth did it end up being about Microsoft Word? I realised that by narrowing the scope, as my prior ideas were too expansive for the project prescribed by my instructor, I also undermined the purpose of the Learning Object. However, I was relieved to realise that this was largely a matter of semantics and learning content rather than an issue that would affect the &amp;ldquo;structure plane&amp;rdquo; (Garrett, 2011) of the Learning Object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarise, the Learning Object will still focus on accessibility in documents but this will be presented alongside information about DSA and increasing awareness of different student needs, so the new provisional title is: &lt;em&gt;Making your documents accessible.&lt;/em&gt; The only aspects that still look at software-based techniques are the guidance PDFs and the &lt;em&gt;offline exercise,&lt;/em&gt; which are easier for university-x support staff to update independently and then add new versions to the Learning Object&amp;rsquo;s back-end storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thought that I had in relation to this point, is that learning video repositories like Lynda.com might be provided at university-x, so software training in my Learning Object would be a &lt;em&gt;poor relation&lt;/em&gt; when compared to the quality of such repositories. Therefore the key features that set the Learning Object apart are the bite-sized and context specific learning topics, the option to complete it anonymously and its enhanced accessibility. The Learning Object may also be more approachable for users who find the vast choice of videos that are available in a service like Lynda.com to be overwhelming as a starting point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-major-discoveries&#34;&gt;Other major discoveries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I undertook &lt;a href=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2015/12/real-time-reflection-experience-of-completing-a-learning-object/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;my reflection of using a learning object&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to take a shot at &lt;a href=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2015/12/bits-pieces-put-together-to-present-a-semblance-of-a-whole/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sketching some wireframes based on v5 of my UML model diagram&lt;/a&gt;. However, as soon as I started to do it my fears were realised and it became clear that I would need to revise the scenarios and then change the UML model diagram accordingly. This was a lot of extra work, but worth doing as it is important to me that I create something that hopefully equals or improves upon existing Learning Objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my first shot at sketching around about 20th of December:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;wireframe sketches 1&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/featuredpost1-2b0dvmx_hu12987883476670449014.webp 400w,
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/featuredpost1-2b0dvmx_hu17279453447118292333.webp 760w,
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/featuredpost1-2b0dvmx_hu5760305753375578163.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/featuredpost1-2b0dvmx_hu12987883476670449014.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;546&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;as-a-result-of-this-i-decided-to&#34;&gt;As a result of this I decided to&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I removed one of the Topics, &lt;em&gt;Readability.&lt;/em&gt; As it would be covered in &lt;em&gt;Fonts &amp;amp; Legibility&lt;/em&gt; and was redundant. It would also add to the time that it would take to complete the Learning Object and this cannot exceed 30mins (a usability requirement).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Removed &lt;em&gt;view feedback&lt;/em&gt; from the Topics as feedback is built into the proceedings of a learning activity - previously called &lt;em&gt;Quiz&lt;/em&gt; and then later &lt;em&gt;Lesson&lt;/em&gt; in the UML iterations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Established the use of a learning activity, based &amp;ldquo;programmed instruction&amp;rdquo; as defined in the IMS Learning Design Specification (2003a, 2003b). This model features questions, presented alongside information; these will take the form of multiple choice questions with built-in feedback. This is based on an established design pattern outlined in the IMS LDS (2003b, Section 4.1, para. 1).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have worked on standardising the language within the scenarios and Learning Object in the wake of what I have learned through study of the IMS Design Specification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I added a centralised topic index page. I had something like this very early on, but it became clear to me after I worked though a Learning object myself that users need a clear overview of the contents of the learning object from the get-go. This also displays the test and certificate, although not available immediately, to give users an idea of the narrative flow of the proceedings as well as the internal end goal; obtaining the certificate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I added a glossary as a global component of the Learning Object. This was based on a needs from the user characteristics that I had not picked up on for users external to university-x. I also felt frustrated by the lack of a glossary when I was using a Learning Object as a user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I added settings and help as a global component of the Learning Object. This is based on the ideas from my &lt;a href=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2015/12/bits-pieces-put-together-to-present-a-semblance-of-a-whole/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;, when I felt that use of the accessibility settings needed to be built into the task scenarios.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having quizzes for each topic, no longer made sense and as an incentivizing measure I added a central test that becomes available once the three main topics are completed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The introduction became a &lt;em&gt;tutorial&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;slides&lt;/em&gt;. Slides were too visually prescriptive and I want to provide a step-by-step guide so that users can learn how to use the interface quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plus there is the glaringly obvious oversight&amp;hellip; in addition to the normal objectives of software this Learning Object requires Learning Outcomes. &lt;strong&gt;This is the reason why I am no longer referring to the Learning Object as LO, as this is a common shortening for Learning Outcomes in educational terminology and may lead to confusion.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I took out task scenario 2 where the user could return to the saved Learning Object via a hyperlink in an email. This is not great practice as it encourages behaviour on the part of the user that could lead to them becoming victims of phishing in the future (Van Duyne, Landay, &amp;amp; Hong, p.555). The solution is to provide a clear link to a university domain parent page, rather than a user-specific URL and instruct the user to copy and paste the parent URL into the web browser address bar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all this, I ended up with the following - I feel MUCH more positive about this as the structure makes more sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-half-of-this-image-is-contrast-adjusted-as-it-was-drawn-in-pencil&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The second iteration of the wireframe sketches&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/02wireframes-239sxt1_hu8497614045190291310.webp 400w,
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/02wireframes-239sxt1_hu12591134592983709389.webp 760w,
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/02wireframes-239sxt1_hu17136798741151885040.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/02wireframes-239sxt1_hu8497614045190291310.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;538&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Half of this image is contrast-adjusted as it was drawn in pencil.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-few-notes-about-ims-lds&#34;&gt;A few notes about IMS LDS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have mixed feelings about my discovery of the IMS Learning Design Specification. I came across it as I searched the ALT (Association of Learning Technologists) wiki, as I was curious what standards and specifications exist for Learning Technologies as these technologies have been around for a long time. Initially I came across information on Educational Modelling Language, which has folded into the IMS standard (original information from the ALT wiki which no longer exists as of 2022 when this post was revisited).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one-hand the specifications feature learning design patterns, which are immensely valuable to this project and also within my day job. The specifications also include a very comprehensive outline of the XML metadata requirements that are needed to create a Learning Object that is truly reusable and also searchable; the following article some some good annotation of the XML to demonstrate the metadata properties (Ragbir &amp;amp; Mohan, 2009). However, as a specification it is too complex for this project, so as much as I would like to create a perfect learning object, in order to be compliant with the standard I would need to start from scratch and create something with multiple roles (student and support) and far more complex taxonomies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also looked into whether I could adapt it and use it as a documentation standard, as a perhaps more appropriate alternative to the NASA documentation standard (1991), however as I started to map the necessary concepts over the contents page and it became clear that would not be possible within the scope of this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-trying-to-map-the-ims-learning-design-information-model-to-my-existing-work-and-concepts-that-i-need-to-cover-it-didnt-go-well-screenshot-from-2003a&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Trying to map to IMS standards&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/Screen-Shot-2015-12-28-at-11.49.00-1sps8rh_hu238714783129827700.webp 400w,
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/Screen-Shot-2015-12-28-at-11.49.00-1sps8rh_hu14640306667514818415.webp 760w,
               /post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/Screen-Shot-2015-12-28-at-11.49.00-1sps8rh_hu16094974436031137054.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/major-discoveries-minor-anguish/images/Screen-Shot-2015-12-28-at-11.49.00-1sps8rh_hu238714783129827700.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;453&#34;
               height=&#34;502&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Trying to map the IMS Learning Design Information Model to my existing work and concepts that I need to cover. It didn&amp;rsquo;t go well (screenshot from 2003a).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;so-what-am-i-going-to-use-from-ims-lds&#34;&gt;So what am I going to use from IMS LDS?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have tried my best to use the language outlined in the IMS LDS as this will provide a common way to describe the processes, architecture and learning design using terminology that is understood in my professional field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will reference some of the learning design patterns (as found in Section 2. Use Cases in 2003b) as they are very helpful and provided some positive validation of the work that I had done so far, in terms of the structural make-up of a Learning Object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I absolutely love the stage-play metaphor that the IMS LDS standard uses to explain a learning object. In short a Unit of Learning (UoL), as defined in the standard, is a package that includes the learning content, including code and physical files alongside the specified metadata. This content is &amp;ldquo;played&amp;rdquo; and is compatible with different delivery &amp;ldquo;environments&amp;rdquo;. The actions or method within the UoL are a series of &amp;ldquo;Plays&amp;rdquo;. Those plays are structured as &amp;ldquo;acts&amp;rdquo; and within the acts the &amp;ldquo;Roles&amp;rdquo; perform their requisite &amp;ldquo;activities&amp;rdquo; within the &amp;ldquo;environment&amp;rdquo; (2003b, Section 3.2.3). The most succinct description of the standard that I have found is a PowerPoint presentation by researchers from the University of Vienna, Introduction to IMS Learning Design (Derntl, Neumann, &amp;amp; Oberhuemer, 2009).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having looked at the NASA software documentation standard (1991) again I felt that an adapted version of the IEEE Recommended Practice for Software Requirements Specifications (1998) will actually be more suitable in terms of outlining the final concept document. This standard has more common group with the IMS LDS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the &amp;ldquo;minor anguish&amp;rdquo; of this post&amp;rsquo;s title, as you can tell from the my writing above, discoveries have resulted in substantial work and with limited time available this has certainly led to a certain level of anguish. This was largely due to the need to back-track in certain areas. However, I now feel that I am almost back on-track, with the aim of completing my wireframes before the Christmas holiday is out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Derntl, M., Neumann, S., &amp;amp; Oberhuemer, P. (2009). &lt;em&gt;Introduction to IMS Learning Design&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
\[PowerPoint slides\]&lt;p&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/mikederntl/introduction-to-ims-learning-design&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/mikederntl/introduction-to-ims-learning-design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Garrett, J. J. (2011). &lt;em&gt;The elements of user experience: User-centered design for the web and beyond&lt;/em&gt; (2nd ed.). Berkeley, CA: New Riders Publishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gordon, C., Gordon, L. (Producers), &amp;amp; Robinson, P. A. (Director). (1989). &lt;em&gt;Field of dreams&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
\[Film\]&lt;p&gt;. USA: Universal Pictures. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0097351&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0097351&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IEEE. (1998). I_EEE Recommended Practice for Software Requirements Specifications_,&amp;quot; (IEEE Std 830-1998). doi:10.1109/IEEESTD.1998.88286&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IMS Global Learning Consortium. (2003a). &lt;em&gt;IMS learning design information model&lt;/em&gt; (Version 1.0). Retrieved from IMS Global Learning Consortium Online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IMS Global Learning Consortium. (2003b). &lt;em&gt;IMS learning design best practice and implementation guide&lt;/em&gt; (Version 1.0). Retrieved from IMS Global Learning Consortium Online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA-STD-2100-91. (1991). &lt;em&gt;NASA software documentation standard&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved 29 November 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://ntrs.nasa.gov&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://ntrs.nasa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ragbir, D., &amp;amp; Mohan, P. (2009). Creating reusable lesson plans for e-learning using the IMS Learning Design specification. &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Education and Development using ICT&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;5&lt;/em&gt;(4). Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;http://ijedict.dec.uwi.edu/viewarticle.php?id=852&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://ijedict.dec.uwi.edu/viewarticle.php?id=852&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Van Duyne, D. K., Landay, J. A., &amp;amp; Hong, J. I. (2006). &lt;em&gt;The design of sites: Patterns for creating winning web sites (2nd edition)&lt;/em&gt; (2nd ed.). United States: Prentice Hall PTR.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-time reflection: experience of completing a Learning Object</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/real-time-reflection-experience-of-completing-a-learning-object/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2015/12/real-time-reflection-experience-of-completing-a-learning-object/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img title=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;file:///Users/fiona/Sites/portfolio/content/post/2015/12/real-time-reflection-experience-of-completing-a-learning-object/images/featuredpost1-2b0dvmx.png&#34; alt=&#34;Complex UML drawing with an annotated printout in my sketchbook&#34; width=&#34;630&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of my day job, I had to complete a Learning Object (as a learner/student) and decided to take the opportunity to reflect on what the experience was like from an end user perspective. Throughout the process, I considered what went well, what could have worked better and what I felt was missing. This exercise resulted in something of a &lt;em&gt;structural&lt;/em&gt; epiphany. I realised that I had missed some vital steps in the conceptual model, this was further borne out when I started my wireframe drawings and found that there were things that simply did not add up. Below is my, step-by-step written account of my experience in the Learning Object, I have highlighted sections of particular significance. My next post will outline some of the decisions that took place from December 16th onward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; this Learning Object has a longer duration than the one that I am building (about an hour in total). I took some screenshots for personal reference, but I cannot include them in this narrative as it is a proprietary system protected by copyright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Includes a title page&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opens in a new window and features an audio narrative that matches written information on-screen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has a keyboard shortcut clearly defined for navigation through the learning object. The keyboard shortcut is &amp;ldquo;c&amp;rdquo; this is not the most comfortable key on the keyboard to use. For right-handed people the arrow keys are in a better position. I am interested in why they chose &amp;ldquo;c&amp;rdquo;. I think that spacebar might offer a better experience for right-handed and left-handed people and also has an association with start and stop, due to its use in YouTube and other video streaming services as a start/stop video option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has a menu which persists throughout the LO with settings options clearly visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allows the option to replay each section or skip to the next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has integrated accessibility tools to adjust: colour scheme (background colour for the most part), audio on/off and subtitles. Also has a zoom and menu for accessing all settings that shows in each view at the top-right of the window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;visual pointers are shown to guide the user in the first screens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Includes an initial tour of the interface. How to save - how to adjust the view, sound settings etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that there is a welcome video outlining the content of the LO and the learning outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topic menu is shown on one page with a brief description of each topic and the time that it will take to complete the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certificate is included on the topics menu which is something that I have been considering for my LO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the learning topics or lessons - multiple choice questions are included for comment and then follows up with integrated feedback. Most of the questions state, &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rsquo;s your opinion&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;. This is helpful in terms of the soft side of considering accessibility issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have answered the questions the narrative voice of the LO either agrees or partially agrees with the answers which are given by the user. Providing definitions and points to remember along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uses display of very basic pie charts to show performance in certain areas, this is not particularly effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important to show progress through the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is not a test for each section - they have a test at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In each section the pages have the same layout, but the content on the page is flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Help question mark button goes to an online help guide about the generic use of the LO. However I was hoping for more of a Glossary to support one of the questions that I am being asked. NOTE to self- &amp;ldquo;I need a GLOSSARY&amp;rdquo; (said in the voice of the Knights who say &lt;em&gt;ni&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you get something wrong, you kind of what to un-do it and then get it right. I think that building in a &lt;strong&gt;replay function&lt;/strong&gt; for each question section is essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final test&lt;/strong&gt; - is accessed from the main menu. This is not a timed test. Feedback is provided on a per-question basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is important to give people the option to take the test more than once to allow them to improve their score.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answers are shuffled the next time that you take the test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scenario-based questions are shuffled, so one question is different from the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New project = New category</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2015/10/new-project-new-category/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2015/10/new-project-new-category/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;well-almost&#34;&gt;Well almost&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have had a #UX category on this blog for a while, but I have decided to formalise it as I embark on a grad school module, &lt;em&gt;Interaction Design and Evaluation Process.&lt;/em&gt; The UX category will be a place to collect my thoughts in relation to what I learn on the module and can be viewed in a collated format via the &amp;ldquo;UX&amp;rdquo; tab. Things to comment on this week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read and think about &lt;strong&gt;BS EN ISO 9241-210-2010 - Ergonomics of human-system interaction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read and comment on user profiles and personae&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read and comment on Scenarios&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this will also feed into my personal research project, looking at analyses of #IoT systems. See you soon!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
