<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogging | Fiona MacNeill Portfolio and Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/blogging/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/blogging/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Blogging</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 08:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu4186623227307172452.png</url>
      <title>Blogging</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/blogging/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Desigining a sustinable workshop</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2025/08/two-conferences-and-a-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 08:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2025/08/two-conferences-and-a-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-going-on&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s going on?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Penn and Teller
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8S8Peh9XH70&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8S8Peh9XH70&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-brief-catch-up-on-the-last-24-months&#34;&gt;A brief catch-up on the last 24 months&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site has been loved and it has been updated. However, between December 2023 and December 2025, I sort of lost myself a bit. The TL:DR version is between working on Ladies that UX Brighton (now &amp;lsquo;LTUX Brighton&amp;rsquo;) and working in a full-time agency role I lost sight of my thinking/academic/artistic pursuits; I let my reflective practice slip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bizarre irony is at last year&amp;rsquo;s UX Camp, in my opinion I hosted my second-best session, on &lt;a href=&#34;event/uxcamp2024/index&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;research hacks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (my first would have to be &lt;a href=&#34;2016/03/talk-factors-of-trust-in-iot-app-interfaces/index&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trust in IoT Systems&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; back in 2016 when I was invited back for the &lt;a href=&#34;2016/06/trust-in-iot-app-interfaces-redux/index&#34;&gt;redux event&lt;/a&gt;, which meant it must have been good!). Last year I even prepared materials for a series of session-related blog posts here explaining how to do each of the hacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did I post them?
No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a matter of personal shame on my &amp;rsquo;todo&amp;rsquo; list for an entire year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/ShameNuns.gif&#34; alt=&#34;The shame nuns with a bell from Game of Thrones walking through the streets shaking bells.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-new-leaf-is-unfurling&#34;&gt;A new leaf is unfurling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;m starting afresh. I have radically reduced the number of posts on this site. Only keeping the most important reflections in a bid to help reduce this site&amp;rsquo;s energy use to a minimum. I also started my own Limited company in January, Macknowlogist, contracting in UX, research, and technology. Working for myself has a different cadence, enabling me to re-jig my reflective practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-am-i-doing-differently-this-time&#34;&gt;What am I doing differently this time?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have created a template in Obsidian to help write these posts efficiently in markdown, from the start.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to write shorter posts more often to keep this site fresh. In particular I will &lt;strong&gt;write&lt;/strong&gt; posts on how I am developing the decision-making framework I previewed at UX Camp this year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On occasion I will write long form posts, but this must be intentional rather than accidental.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am self-editing by using washable index cards and other methods to keep things more concise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of all I am sketching more and more in my life and work and that is such a brilliant and restorative change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/SketchbookApril2025.webp&#34; alt=&#34;A very busy systems thinking page of my sketchbook with diagrams connections, notes, and scribbles&#34; /&gt;
&lt;caption&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not so much sketching on this page - this was the start of the ideas for the ethical framework, with various influences including John V Willshire&#39;s work on the top-right.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ux-camp-2025-rundown&#34;&gt;UX Camp 2025 Rundown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-ux-camp-brighton&#34;&gt;What is UX Camp Brighton?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only the best annual UX event in Brighton in my opinion (not a paid endorsement). Run impeccably by Patrick Samson, Lou Bloom, Luke Hay, Tom Prior, Chris How, Deeksha Bhushan, and Rob Pearson, it is an event where everyone is made to feel welcome to share their ideas on UX. As a &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;bar camp&lt;/a&gt; style event there is no agenda until the hosts arrive and place their session synopsis cards. Each session is limited to 20 mins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been going to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uxcampbrighton.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UX Camp Brighton&lt;/a&gt; since about 2014 and it has been, and continues to be, instrumental to my practice and learning. The other thing I find impressive is that every year, I can see how they have taken feedback onboard, improving the event and making it more inclusive. Like this year having the option of asking an organiser to pitch in the main room to the audience to remove that stressor. Nice!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sessions-i-got-to-see&#34;&gt;The sessions I got to see&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five sessions run simultaneously in each time slot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session you get to attend is based on three factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well the host&amp;rsquo;s pitch resonated with you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether you could get to the room on time before its too full&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t you need to either have a back-up choice, or make your way to a room with space #potluck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the sessions below were delightful brainfood regardless of the above. Truly, I always wish I could attend all of them. I have summarised my favourite concept from each session below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;graeme-aymer&#34;&gt;Graeme Aymer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graeme shared the relevance of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Baldwin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;James Balwin&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; writing (1924–1987) to compassion in UX. He expertly took us on a journey of analysis through the following Baldwin quote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Love has never been a popular movement. And no one&amp;rsquo;s ever wanted, really, to be free. The world is held together, really it is held together, by the love and the passion of a very few people. Otherwise, of course, you can despair. Walk down the street of any city, any afternoon, and look around you. What you&amp;rsquo;ve got to remember is what you&amp;rsquo;re looking at is also you. Everyone you&amp;rsquo;re looking at is also you. You could be that person. You could be that monster, you could be that cop. And you have to decide, in yourself, not to be.”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;~ James Baldwin (1970)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everyone you&amp;rsquo;re looking at is also you&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reminded me of the quote, &amp;ldquo;Be kind, for everyone you meet is fighting a harder battle&amp;rdquo;, or some variation of that. This quote is often attributed to Plato, Alice Walker, or Robin Williams–just proving that finding truth on the internet has been and always shall be a tenuous venture unless you have time to pull at all the threads. Hmm, remember this dear reader the next you use AI as a search engine 🤔&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless this is an important message, to paraphrase Graeme: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;you are the silos, you are the bad work culture, you are the stakeholders, you are the participants, you are the colleagues, you are the bosses, you are the direct reports, you are the customers using your designs&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. This is such a crucial point, not only in terms of empathy, but also in terms of taking action. It reminds us that we can actually change those systems, those hierarchies, because they are us and we are them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You could be that monster&amp;hellip;and you have to decide in yourself not to be&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sayani-mitra&#34;&gt;Sayani Mitra&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sayani provided a comprehensive overview of how UX research could help to improve and enhance AI-focused products and products where AI is being implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved Sayani&amp;rsquo;s easy to follow list structures to sit alongside the product development process. In a tech environment where research roles are under threat, often because of tight budgets, and the &amp;lsquo;promise&amp;rsquo; of AI for research (without researchers!) this is the talk we all needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I particularly loved the following aspects, which I plan to add to my &amp;lsquo;super-group&amp;rsquo; of decision-making frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncover&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; the real-world context early. What problem are you actually solving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prevent&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; prevent tech-first decision-making&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Define&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; value before features and map these&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audit&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; bias in datasets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Influence&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; the final product output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;sayanis-5-ps-of-ethical-ai&#34;&gt;Sayani&amp;rsquo;s 5 P&amp;rsquo;s of Ethical AI&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt; - Is AI even needed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People&lt;/strong&gt; - Who gains, who loses?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Process&lt;/strong&gt; - How is it designed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power&lt;/strong&gt; - Who controls outcomes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proof&lt;/strong&gt; - Is there proof that this thing even works in this context (my notes got smudged here, so this is my interpretation - the serendipity of analogue!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the implementation of AI always comes to down to these aspects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What type of AI are talking about (e.g., LLMs, ML, automation, something else?)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What context was the chosen flavour originally designed for? It is good to understand the origins of the tool you are using and therefore it&amp;rsquo;s limitations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it adding value beyond what you can already do without AI (as in &amp;lsquo;purpose&amp;rsquo; above)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we implement it in the most efficient and least wasteful way possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much of this thinking overlaps with Sayani&amp;rsquo;s points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rebecca-hugo&#34;&gt;Rebecca Hugo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rebecca’s talk was a clever construction with several levels of meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one level it pulled some valuable points about learning and behavioural change from the &lt;em&gt;seminal film&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0215129/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Road Trip&lt;/a&gt; (2000). Specifically, one character’s proclamation that given enough time he could &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;teach Japanese to a Monkey&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. The point here is that by finding ways to relate new knowledge to existing knowledge and interests, it is possible to ‘hook’ people and help them to retain new information. Crucially, they will also be able to better apply that acquired information. In the context of the film &amp;lsquo;said&amp;rsquo; character, &lt;em&gt;Rubin&lt;/em&gt; helps another character, &lt;em&gt;Josh&lt;/em&gt; prep for an exam with limited knowledge of the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On another level Rebecca gave an example of how to use analogy in a clear way when communicating with colleagues and clients. Even if you knew nothing of Road Trip and the other pop culture references in the presentation, Rebecca’s storytelling abilities essentially used these as a series of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacGuffin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MacGuffins&lt;/a&gt;. As in references relevant to the main protagonist or subject but irrelevant on their own in isolation. By using a range of references she added value for those who knew the reference and supplied intrigue to those who did not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, this talk was stacked full of useful advice and as a designer who focuses on learning. I enjoyed revisiting concepts such as ‘memory palaces’ (also known as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Method_of_loci&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;method of loci&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;), and the ‘&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/sH5i2skyCAU?feature=shared&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;story method’&lt;/a&gt;. I particularly chimed with Rebecca&amp;rsquo;s point that external skills and knowledge can come into play in your UX career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few of my favourite sound bites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same but different &lt;br /&gt;
Simply speak simply &lt;br /&gt;
Respond to the responses &lt;br /&gt;
Make it make sense&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating mottos is yet another helpful memetic and it is something that I know Rebecca excels at, having attended her talks at several UX Camp Brighton events over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;alex-edwards&#34;&gt;Alex Edwards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex talked about the steps for closing the Discovery process. Alex is a design strategist and it was superb to gain insight into the level of thought and learning layers of consideration involved in her work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key point for me was getting the right people in the room. This correlates with my experience as a consultant. It can certainly feel uncomfortable as you need to accept that there will be dissent. However, if you don’t take stakeholders on the journey with you from the start then you are destined for trouble later down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved Alex’s thinking around the different stakeholders you need to appeal to when wrapping up discovery (the preparatory research phase of any design project).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stakeholders were…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decision makers &lt;br /&gt;
Subject matter experts &lt;br /&gt;
Broader stakeholders &lt;br /&gt;
Snoopers and Poopers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last group, &amp;ldquo;snoopers and poopers&amp;rdquo; is the one you only learn about through experience. It is bet to figure out who they are as soon as you can, so that your project isn’t shut down by someone with an opposing agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved Alex’s approach to cataloguing insights throughout the discovery phase, with a table for listing all the content collected, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;transcriptions,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;information from the client,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;desk research,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought that the inclusion of star ratings out of five for the ‘applicability’, and ‘level of detail’ were really helpful criteria. I’ll definitely consider how to implement this in my own practice. Particularly as a new contractor, I often work alone. I do this work as well, but don’t have a central mapping or record of it. I will try using &lt;a href=&#34;https://obsidian.md/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Obsidian notebooks&lt;/a&gt; with a table like this at the top level. This might be especially helpful later in projects when the design process can inadvertently drift away from Discovery findings for range of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex’s advice when considering competitors was also quite brilliant. Specifically, in addition to  researching &amp;ldquo;competitors, comparators and disruptors&amp;rdquo;, it is worth considering the &amp;ldquo;household names&amp;rdquo; and then looking for patterns. Not only do I need to add this into my own process, but I also want to pull in, “how do/did they solve this problem now/before?”. Remembering that an analogue process might be a competitor is important and it is something I often encountered when working in Higher Education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a personal reflection, when under high levels of stress I retreat from my careful time boxing and resort to hand-written notes which then get into a state of disarray, adding to the stress. The solution? Have an A4 sized whiteboard to put thoughts onto and if I don’t digitise them they gradually degrade and get rubbed out by my wrist. There is also an analogue satisfaction to erasing these notes and at least I am no longer going through reams of paper notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/whiteboard-example.webp&#34; alt=&#34;An A4 sized whiteboard with scribbled notes on it, that are partially erased&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great tool suggestion from Alex was &lt;a href=&#34;https://octopus.do/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Octopus.do&lt;/a&gt; which builds visual site maps and screenflows. This is a really helpful way to understand dead ends. I did try it for a current project – it couldn&amp;rsquo;t quite handle all the layers of navigation. Regardless, I can see Octopus.do&amp;rsquo;s potential, even though I ended up mapping the structure manually in Figjam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;insights&#34;&gt;Insights&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after all this how do you “distillate the wins”? Alex used &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.airtable.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Airtable&lt;/a&gt; to collate the findings and also noted that affinity mapping as you go is key. You cannot leave this until later, you need to capture this thinking as you go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the concept of “sticky phrases” was very powerful and a great way for converting insights to memorable mottos (there we are with the mottos again!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of great examples were…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One size fits none&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Frontline staff are the heroes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the most important thing with discovery is to outline how, and crucially when, it will be actioned. This is key to ROI (return on investment) and something that I have learned the hard way in the past. Discovery and research in general are perceived as expensive, it is critical to show that discovery is not an optional part of the process and to close the phase in an action oriented way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This can happen, we are ready to start&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;shubhangar-sidharthan&#34;&gt;Shubhangar Sidharthan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shubhangar’s talk was a much needed wake-up call for me and for this reason it gained my vote as my favourite talk of the day in the follow-up survey. Shubhangar provided a comprehensive summary of algorithmic changes to personalisation in apps such as Instagram and TikTok. He covered the user benefits, as well as the algorithmic siloing, and the addictive tendencies that could be stimulated by these design decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk was a powerful reminder of how I need to engage with this tech to understand trends, even if I choose not to engage beyond professional necessity. I had a TikTok account back in 2021 when I made a number of accessibility focused learning videos. At the time, I was astounded by the level of engagement and positive responses compared to my experience using YouTube. However, I could also see that that this interface was, as Shubhangar astutely described a “fruit machine”. Having an awareness of my own tendencies I chose to switch off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have observed in learning how much the trends and personalisation evident in apps, like the aforementioned and Duolingo, have been adopted in learning platforms. However, I find myself questioning how affective swipe-centric learning really is, beyond initial engagement. At the end of the day it still isn’t embodied learning and for it to really stick it needs to be applied in the real world and be relevant to the goals of the person. No amount of personalisation will change that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the point of addiction, there is such a thing as addictive learning and not in a good way. I had a 400+ day streak on Duolingo which I recently ended for good&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The main reason was I felt pwned by the owl. As Duolingo resorted to increasingly manipulative design patterns (many have commented on this–a good overview by &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/blog/duolingos-emotional-blackmail-591a14cdf98d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Harris Sockel on Medium&lt;/a&gt;). I could feel this process taking hold and adding to my stress levels. Disrupting my sleep by encouraging me to continue the streak before bed, rather than reading a book and allowing my brain to switch down a gear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During those 400+ days, I learned a lot of French vocab, but so much of it was reliant on recognition rather than recall and unless I went to France on a regular basis, applying this knowledge in the real world, it won’t stick (see &lt;em&gt;Praxis&lt;/em&gt; later in this post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I come back to the need for learning to be supported by both intrinsic and extrinsic motivation. The true benefit of personalisation being the opportunity for the person who is learning to map their individual aspirations to recognised outcomes and experiences that will help get them reach those aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shubhangar’s parting point was both poignant and prescient:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The future of UX isn’t just knowing what users want. It’s knowing when they’ve had enough&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;richard-vahrman&#34;&gt;Richard Vahrman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great to see Richard again, after a 1-year hiatus. Richard, although he self-describes as someone who is not a UX designer, is brilliant at creating a memorable experience in 20 minutes. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to give too much away about Richard&amp;rsquo;s session as he was using it as an opportunity to test ideas for a future project. However, I am aways inspired by his ability to take people on a journey and pull people into his world. There is a such a playfulness to his ideas, while retaining a connection to more serious ideas in the case of his future project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard inspired the Godzilla card when I recently facilitated the &lt;a href=&#34;https://servicedesignbreakfast.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Clearleft Service Design Breakfast&lt;/a&gt;. His game using every day objects, reframed as talisman and trading objects, was brilliant. It really got people in the audience to think about group affiliations, the &amp;lsquo;in&amp;rsquo; crowd and &amp;lsquo;out&amp;rsquo; crowd and societal norms. This was &amp;lsquo;metaphor&amp;rsquo; at a level that anyone could understand, regardless of pre-existing knowledge, and for this reason it was absolute genius!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/GodzillaCard.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Three cards in a row from my generative AI discussion card game. The first card shows a hand-drawn Godzilla holding a plane with Japanese characters, then a question card about a wasteful AI processing workflow. Then an speculative equation for thinking about whether AI is the right solution&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ghaith-nassar&#34;&gt;Ghaith Nassar&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ghaith took us on a fascinating tour of how the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uk.bookshop.org/p/books/pedagogy-of-the-oppressed-paulo-freire/3823089?ean=9780241301111&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pedagogy of the Oppressed&lt;/em&gt; by Paulo Freire (1970)&lt;/a&gt; and how the book has influenced their practice as a multi-disciplinary designer and facilitator. I have reserved this book through my university library membership and look forward to reading it&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the embodied way that Ghaith presented the content. Placing the printed out would-be slides on the glass wall in the room. This allowed us to see a holistic map of the concepts as well as where we were currently were in the journey. It made me wish that there were a way of doing this in a presentation without it becoming inaccessible. &lt;a href=&#34;https://prezi.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prezi&lt;/a&gt; tried to accomplish this as a tool, however, it was always bound by the teacher&amp;rsquo;s or presenter&amp;rsquo;s path through the content. I found this approach delightfully metacognitive as a theme in Freire&amp;rsquo;s writing, as Ghaith described and I have interpreted was for the &amp;rsquo;teacher&amp;rsquo; to address their own hubris. What better way than to allow the &amp;lsquo;students&amp;rsquo; in the room to engage with the content now, and also look around to the content of now. I found myself looking back at the earlier concepts and seeing the connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing knowledge is not linear. So, why is it almost always a timeline? We let our tools dictate so much of what we do (&amp;lsquo;ahem, PowerPoint&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teachers have something to learn from students and students have something to learn from teachers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect that I found fascinating was this little equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflection + Action = Word = Praxis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved how Ghaith broke this down for us&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Action&lt;/strong&gt; ~ &amp;ldquo;Transform the world&amp;rdquo;
&lt;strong&gt;Word&lt;/strong&gt; ~ &amp;ldquo;Rights for everyone. With people not for people.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;strong&gt;Praxis&lt;/strong&gt; ~ Putting theory into practice or as per the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/praxis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cambridge English Dictionary definition&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;ldquo;the process of using a theory or something that you have learned in a practical way&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what about the relationship between the component parts of this equation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove &amp;lsquo;Action&amp;rsquo; and you are left with &amp;ldquo;Idle Chatter&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove &amp;lsquo;Reflection&amp;rsquo; and you are left with &amp;ldquo;Activism&amp;rdquo; for activism&amp;rsquo;s sake. Perhaps forgetting why you took action in the first place, is the action even still appropriate for meeting the desired end state?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equation above, together with the five pillars of dialogue (&amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;Love&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Humility&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Faith&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trust&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Hope&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;) are elements that I will consider including in my super group of thinking structures and frameworks. That is for a future blog post/s and was the topic of my own UX Camp presentation this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;reality as a process, as transformation, rather than as a static entity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;claire-bown&#34;&gt;Claire Bown&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I heard Claire speak at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://weareshesays.com/chapters/shesays-brighton/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SheSays Brighton&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.internationalwomensday.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;International Women&amp;rsquo;s Day&lt;/a&gt; event earlier this year and found her background in marketing and transition into AI consulting to be inspirational. As someone who spends a quite a bit of time researching and thinking about LLMs and machine learning, Claire&amp;rsquo;s talk covered some familiar ground. Regardless, I appreciated the visual way she presented both issues with gender equality in tech and the consequential issue of gender bias in the outputs form diffusion models. This will be further exacerbated by the prevalence of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychology#WEIRD_bias&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WEIRD biased data&lt;/a&gt; in the training models, so where women&amp;rsquo;s data is included, it will be predominantly Western and predominantly White. This is something that Michael Kibedi has discussed and explored on his &lt;a href=&#34;https://uxmichaelco.substack.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;First &amp;amp; Fifteenth Substack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claire asked &lt;a href=&#34;https://openai.com/index/hello-gpt-4o/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ChatGPT&amp;rsquo;s GPT-4o&lt;/a&gt; image generation to create an image for each professional role typically found on a product team. Interestingly all the images sort of look liked versions of the same caucasian man, with varying levels of facial hair. The exception was the UX designer who was both a woman and of mixed race. Without understanding more about the training data, it is hard to know why this role was different. If we assume majority US data, then the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uxpa.org/salary-surveys/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UXPA Salary Survey&lt;/a&gt; has pointed towards there being more women than men in UX roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.careerexplorer.com/careers/ux-designer/demographics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Career Explorer by Sokanu&lt;/a&gt; suggests that 53% of UX Designers are women in the US as compared to 47% men. This source also cites that many men more are interested in UX roles than are actually working in them, suggesting a bias towards women in the role. So, as compared to other roles, like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.careerexplorer.com/careers/app-developer/demographics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;App Developer&lt;/a&gt; (77% men | 23% women) this goes some way to explaining the generated image. The reason for the other characteristics remains unknown and I can only surmise that there might be something in the position of UX Designer as an advocate for all users that the model opted to be more representative of all users. A more linear explanation could be the language used to describe UX roles in job descriptions is typically femme-coded as &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@LadiesthatUX_Br/ltux-brighton-femme-coded-work-in-tech-4bc80b594cd7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LTUX Brighton, explored through a discussion panel last year.&lt;/a&gt; The panel included &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/intentionaut/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Saielle DaSilva&lt;/a&gt; who has spoken on this topic at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mindtheproduct.com/the-f-words-of-highly-successful-product-organisations-by-saielle-dasilva/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mind the Product&lt;/a&gt;. I need to do more research on this myself, anecdotally having looked at a lot of job descriptions recently I wonder if words like, empathy, collaboration, co-design, facilitation, listening, guiding, liaising, might lead an LLM towards this bias? (couching this thought&amp;hellip;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to the outputs above, I find this flagrant bias pretty disappointing. It concerns me that most things we build digitally seem to perpetuate the mistakes of the past rather than envisioning an entangled and messy, yet more humane future (á la &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ribaj.com/culture/profile-indy-johar-dark-matter-labs-boring-revolution&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Indy Johar&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;https://darkmatterlabs.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dark Matter Labs&lt;/a&gt;). I am not anti-AI by any means, I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://chat.greenpt.ai/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GreenPT&lt;/a&gt; and to supplement my own research for the paragraph above. I also use several other models in contextually sensitive and productivity focused ways. However, we really really need to try harder and not take what these companies, or their models, say at face value without scrutiny. Just as I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t believe a human, unless they provided evidence of what they were saying–even high trust humans&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; get things wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skepticism is probably one of the healthiest habits to cultivate. You can then feel happy on the occasions when you are proven wrong. It is the best route to critically responsible optimism!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my main take away from Claire&amp;rsquo;s talk - what do these platforms want?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;They want to keep you using their platform, their model.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, change it up, don&amp;rsquo;t have single brand loyalty try the same prompt in a different model and see how it performs. However, before you do, ask yourself my &lt;em&gt;Create Another Way&lt;/em&gt; question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; of the &lt;strong&gt;output&lt;/strong&gt; proportionate to the &lt;strong&gt;effort&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;cost&lt;/strong&gt; of the &lt;strong&gt;input&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, this is an existential question. If this question causes you to stop, pause, and create a single more effective prompt, in place of three, then I have done my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next year (although I will definitely blog sooner!), I leave you with Rebecca Hugo&amp;rsquo;s amazing speed tapping skills, as applied to the 2025 UX Camp Brighton quiz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/SpeedTapping.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Rebecca&#39;s using two fingers on one hand on a smartphone to extremely rapidly press on a click counter app, then changes strategy and moves the phone to her lap and presses even faster&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not related to the &amp;ldquo;AI-First Controversy&amp;rdquo;, a multifaceted issue discussed eloquently by &lt;a href=&#34;https://knowyourmeme.com/editorials/guides/whats-the-duolingo-ai-first-controversy-the-ceos-pro-ai-message-and-the-online-backlash-explained&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Know Your Meme&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time of writing I am now reading Freire&amp;rsquo;s book. Due to the way the book and the arguments within are structured, the format Ghaith used now makes even more sense!&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you consider me a &amp;ldquo;high-trust human&amp;rdquo; then I&amp;rsquo;m telling you now that I get things wrong and that is part of how I continually learn. It is possible that this post will have &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; things in it when I look back in future. However, unlike an LLM when you chat with me I will include phrases like, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;you&amp;rsquo;ll want to double-check this&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;*I&amp;rsquo;ll answer with the caveat that&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;I will come back to you with a more complete answer&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Conferences and a Course</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2025/07/two-conferences-and-a-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 08:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2025/07/two-conferences-and-a-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-going-on&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s going on?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-brief-catch-up-on-the-last-24-months&#34;&gt;A brief catch-up on the last 24 months&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site has been loved and it has been updated. However, between December 2023 and December 2025, I sort of lost myself a bit. The TL:DR version is between working on Ladies that UX Brighton (now &amp;lsquo;LTUX Brighton&amp;rsquo;) and working in a full-time agency role I lost sight of my thinking/academic/artistic pursuits; I let my reflective practice slip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bizarre irony is at last year&amp;rsquo;s UX Camp, in my opinion I hosted my second-best session, on &lt;a href=&#34;event/uxcamp2024/index&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;research hacks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (my first would have to be &lt;a href=&#34;2016/03/talk-factors-of-trust-in-iot-app-interfaces/index&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trust in IoT Systems&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; back in 2016 when I was invited back for the &lt;a href=&#34;2016/06/trust-in-iot-app-interfaces-redux/index&#34;&gt;redux event&lt;/a&gt;, which meant it must have been good!). Last year I even prepared materials for a series of session-related blog posts here explaining how to do each of the hacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did I post them?
No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a matter of personal shame on my &amp;rsquo;todo&amp;rsquo; list for an entire year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/ShameNuns.gif&#34; alt=&#34;The shame nuns with a bell from Game of Thrones walking through the streets shaking bells.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-new-leaf-is-unfurling&#34;&gt;A new leaf is unfurling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;m starting afresh. I have radically reduced the number of posts on this site. Only keeping the most important reflections in a bid to help reduce this site&amp;rsquo;s energy use to a minimum. I also started my own Limited company in January, Macknowlogist, contracting in UX, research, and technology. Working for myself has a different cadence, enabling me to re-jig my reflective practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-am-i-doing-differently-this-time&#34;&gt;What am I doing differently this time?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have created a template in Obsidian to help write these posts efficiently in markdown, from the start.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to write shorter posts more often to keep this site fresh. In particular I will &lt;strong&gt;write&lt;/strong&gt; posts on how I am developing the decision-making framework I previewed at UX Camp this year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On occasion I will write long form posts, but this must be intentional rather than accidental.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am self-editing by using washable index cards and other methods to keep things more concise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of all I am sketching more and more in my life and work and that is such a brilliant and restorative change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/SketchbookApril2025.webp&#34; alt=&#34;A very busy systems thinking page of my sketchbook with diagrams connections, notes, and scribbles&#34; /&gt;
&lt;caption&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not so much sketching on this page - this was the start of the ideas for the ethical framework, with various influences including John V Willshire&#39;s work on the top-right.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ux-camp-2025-rundown&#34;&gt;UX Camp 2025 Rundown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-ux-camp-brighton&#34;&gt;What is UX Camp Brighton?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only the best annual UX event in Brighton in my opinion (not a paid endorsement). Run impeccably by Patrick Samson, Lou Bloom, Luke Hay, Tom Prior, Chris How, Deeksha Bhushan, and Rob Pearson, it is an event where everyone is made to feel welcome to share their ideas on UX. As a &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;bar camp&lt;/a&gt; style event there is no agenda until the hosts arrive and place their session synopsis cards. Each session is limited to 20 mins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been going to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uxcampbrighton.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UX Camp Brighton&lt;/a&gt; since about 2014 and it has been, and continues to be, instrumental to my practice and learning. The other thing I find impressive is that every year, I can see how they have taken feedback onboard, improving the event and making it more inclusive. Like this year having the option of asking an organiser to pitch in the main room to the audience to remove that stressor. Nice!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sessions-i-got-to-see&#34;&gt;The sessions I got to see&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five sessions run simultaneously in each time slot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session you get to attend is based on three factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well the host&amp;rsquo;s pitch resonated with you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether you could get to the room on time before its too full&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t you need to either have a back-up choice, or make your way to a room with space #potluck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the sessions below were delightful brainfood regardless of the above. Truly, I always wish I could attend all of them. I have summarised my favourite concept from each session below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;graeme-aymer&#34;&gt;Graeme Aymer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graeme shared the relevance of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Baldwin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;James Balwin&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; writing (1924–1987) to compassion in UX. He expertly took us on a journey of analysis through the following Baldwin quote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Love has never been a popular movement. And no one&amp;rsquo;s ever wanted, really, to be free. The world is held together, really it is held together, by the love and the passion of a very few people. Otherwise, of course, you can despair. Walk down the street of any city, any afternoon, and look around you. What you&amp;rsquo;ve got to remember is what you&amp;rsquo;re looking at is also you. Everyone you&amp;rsquo;re looking at is also you. You could be that person. You could be that monster, you could be that cop. And you have to decide, in yourself, not to be.”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;~ James Baldwin (1970)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everyone you&amp;rsquo;re looking at is also you&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reminded me of the quote, &amp;ldquo;Be kind, for everyone you meet is fighting a harder battle&amp;rdquo;, or some variation of that. This quote is often attributed to Plato, Alice Walker, or Robin Williams–just proving that finding truth on the internet has been and always shall be a tenuous venture unless you have time to pull at all the threads. Hmm, remember this dear reader the next you use AI as a search engine 🤔&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless this is an important message, to paraphrase Graeme: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;you are the silos, you are the bad work culture, you are the stakeholders, you are the participants, you are the colleagues, you are the bosses, you are the direct reports, you are the customers using your designs&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. This is such a crucial point, not only in terms of empathy, but also in terms of taking action. It reminds us that we can actually change those systems, those hierarchies, because they are us and we are them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You could be that monster&amp;hellip;and you have to decide in yourself not to be&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sayani-mitra&#34;&gt;Sayani Mitra&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sayani provided a comprehensive overview of how UX research could help to improve and enhance AI-focused products and products where AI is being implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved Sayani&amp;rsquo;s easy to follow list structures to sit alongside the product development process. In a tech environment where research roles are under threat, often because of tight budgets, and the &amp;lsquo;promise&amp;rsquo; of AI for research (without researchers!) this is the talk we all needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I particularly loved the following aspects, which I plan to add to my &amp;lsquo;super-group&amp;rsquo; of decision-making frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncover&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; the real-world context early. What problem are you actually solving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prevent&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; prevent tech-first decision-making&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Define&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; value before features and map these&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audit&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; bias in datasets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Influence&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; the final product output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;sayanis-5-ps-of-ethical-ai&#34;&gt;Sayani&amp;rsquo;s 5 P&amp;rsquo;s of Ethical AI&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt; - Is AI even needed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People&lt;/strong&gt; - Who gains, who loses?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Process&lt;/strong&gt; - How is it designed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power&lt;/strong&gt; - Who controls outcomes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proof&lt;/strong&gt; - Is there proof that this thing even works in this context (my notes got smudged here, so this is my interpretation - the serendipity of analogue!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the implementation of AI always comes to down to these aspects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What type of AI are talking about (e.g., LLMs, ML, automation, something else?)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What context was the chosen flavour originally designed for? It is good to understand the origins of the tool you are using and therefore it&amp;rsquo;s limitations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it adding value beyond what you can already do without AI (as in &amp;lsquo;purpose&amp;rsquo; above)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we implement it in the most efficient and least wasteful way possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much of this thinking overlaps with Sayani&amp;rsquo;s points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rebecca-hugo&#34;&gt;Rebecca Hugo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rebecca’s talk was a clever construction with several levels of meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one level it pulled some valuable points about learning and behavioural change from the &lt;em&gt;seminal film&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0215129/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Road Trip&lt;/a&gt; (2000). Specifically, one character’s proclamation that given enough time he could &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;teach Japanese to a Monkey&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. The point here is that by finding ways to relate new knowledge to existing knowledge and interests, it is possible to ‘hook’ people and help them to retain new information. Crucially, they will also be able to better apply that acquired information. In the context of the film &amp;lsquo;said&amp;rsquo; character, &lt;em&gt;Rubin&lt;/em&gt; helps another character, &lt;em&gt;Josh&lt;/em&gt; prep for an exam with limited knowledge of the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On another level Rebecca gave an example of how to use analogy in a clear way when communicating with colleagues and clients. Even if you knew nothing of Road Trip and the other pop culture references in the presentation, Rebecca’s storytelling abilities essentially used these as a series of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacGuffin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MacGuffins&lt;/a&gt;. As in references relevant to the main protagonist or subject but irrelevant on their own in isolation. By using a range of references she added value for those who knew the reference and supplied intrigue to those who did not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, this talk was stacked full of useful advice and as a designer who focuses on learning. I enjoyed revisiting concepts such as ‘memory palaces’ (also known as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Method_of_loci&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;method of loci&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;), and the ‘&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/sH5i2skyCAU?feature=shared&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;story method’&lt;/a&gt;. I particularly chimed with Rebecca&amp;rsquo;s point that external skills and knowledge can come into play in your UX career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few of my favourite sound bites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same but different &lt;br /&gt;
Simply speak simply &lt;br /&gt;
Respond to the responses &lt;br /&gt;
Make it make sense&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating mottos is yet another helpful memetic and it is something that I know Rebecca excels at, having attended her talks at several UX Camp Brighton events over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;alex-edwards&#34;&gt;Alex Edwards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex talked about the steps for closing the Discovery process. Alex is a design strategist and it was superb to gain insight into the level of thought and learning layers of consideration involved in her work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key point for me was getting the right people in the room. This correlates with my experience as a consultant. It can certainly feel uncomfortable as you need to accept that there will be dissent. However, if you don’t take stakeholders on the journey with you from the start then you are destined for trouble later down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved Alex’s thinking around the different stakeholders you need to appeal to when wrapping up discovery (the preparatory research phase of any design project).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stakeholders were…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decision makers &lt;br /&gt;
Subject matter experts &lt;br /&gt;
Broader stakeholders &lt;br /&gt;
Snoopers and Poopers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last group, &amp;ldquo;snoopers and poopers&amp;rdquo; is the one you only learn about through experience. It is bet to figure out who they are as soon as you can, so that your project isn’t shut down by someone with an opposing agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved Alex’s approach to cataloguing insights throughout the discovery phase, with a table for listing all the content collected, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;transcriptions,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;information from the client,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;desk research,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought that the inclusion of star ratings out of five for the ‘applicability’, and ‘level of detail’ were really helpful criteria. I’ll definitely consider how to implement this in my own practice. Particularly as a new contractor, I often work alone. I do this work as well, but don’t have a central mapping or record of it. I will try using &lt;a href=&#34;https://obsidian.md/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Obsidian notebooks&lt;/a&gt; with a table like this at the top level. This might be especially helpful later in projects when the design process can inadvertently drift away from Discovery findings for range of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex’s advice when considering competitors was also quite brilliant. Specifically, in addition to  researching &amp;ldquo;competitors, comparators and disruptors&amp;rdquo;, it is worth considering the &amp;ldquo;household names&amp;rdquo; and then looking for patterns. Not only do I need to add this into my own process, but I also want to pull in, “how do/did they solve this problem now/before?”. Remembering that an analogue process might be a competitor is important and it is something I often encountered when working in Higher Education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a personal reflection, when under high levels of stress I retreat from my careful time boxing and resort to hand-written notes which then get into a state of disarray, adding to the stress. The solution? Have an A4 sized whiteboard to put thoughts onto and if I don’t digitise them they gradually degrade and get rubbed out by my wrist. There is also an analogue satisfaction to erasing these notes and at least I am no longer going through reams of paper notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/whiteboard-example.webp&#34; alt=&#34;An A4 sized whiteboard with scribbled notes on it, that are partially erased&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great tool suggestion from Alex was &lt;a href=&#34;https://octopus.do/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Octopus.do&lt;/a&gt; which builds visual site maps and screenflows. This is a really helpful way to understand dead ends. I did try it for a current project – it couldn&amp;rsquo;t quite handle all the layers of navigation. Regardless, I can see Octopus.do&amp;rsquo;s potential, even though I ended up mapping the structure manually in Figjam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;insights&#34;&gt;Insights&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after all this how do you “distillate the wins”? Alex used &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.airtable.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Airtable&lt;/a&gt; to collate the findings and also noted that affinity mapping as you go is key. You cannot leave this until later, you need to capture this thinking as you go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the concept of “sticky phrases” was very powerful and a great way for converting insights to memorable mottos (there we are with the mottos again!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of great examples were…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One size fits none&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Frontline staff are the heroes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the most important thing with discovery is to outline how, and crucially when, it will be actioned. This is key to ROI (return on investment) and something that I have learned the hard way in the past. Discovery and research in general are perceived as expensive, it is critical to show that discovery is not an optional part of the process and to close the phase in an action oriented way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This can happen, we are ready to start&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;shubhangar-sidharthan&#34;&gt;Shubhangar Sidharthan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shubhangar’s talk was a much needed wake-up call for me and for this reason it gained my vote as my favourite talk of the day in the follow-up survey. Shubhangar provided a comprehensive summary of algorithmic changes to personalisation in apps such as Instagram and TikTok. He covered the user benefits, as well as the algorithmic siloing, and the addictive tendencies that could be stimulated by these design decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk was a powerful reminder of how I need to engage with this tech to understand trends, even if I choose not to engage beyond professional necessity. I had a TikTok account back in 2021 when I made a number of accessibility focused learning videos. At the time, I was astounded by the level of engagement and positive responses compared to my experience using YouTube. However, I could also see that that this interface was, as Shubhangar astutely described a “fruit machine”. Having an awareness of my own tendencies I chose to switch off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have observed in learning how much the trends and personalisation evident in apps, like the aforementioned and Duolingo, have been adopted in learning platforms. However, I find myself questioning how affective swipe-centric learning really is, beyond initial engagement. At the end of the day it still isn’t embodied learning and for it to really stick it needs to be applied in the real world and be relevant to the goals of the person. No amount of personalisation will change that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the point of addiction, there is such a thing as addictive learning and not in a good way. I had a 400+ day streak on Duolingo which I recently ended for good&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The main reason was I felt pwned by the owl. As Duolingo resorted to increasingly manipulative design patterns (many have commented on this–a good overview by &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/blog/duolingos-emotional-blackmail-591a14cdf98d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Harris Sockel on Medium&lt;/a&gt;). I could feel this process taking hold and adding to my stress levels. Disrupting my sleep by encouraging me to continue the streak before bed, rather than reading a book and allowing my brain to switch down a gear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During those 400+ days, I learned a lot of French vocab, but so much of it was reliant on recognition rather than recall and unless I went to France on a regular basis, applying this knowledge in the real world, it won’t stick (see &lt;em&gt;Praxis&lt;/em&gt; later in this post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I come back to the need for learning to be supported by both intrinsic and extrinsic motivation. The true benefit of personalisation being the opportunity for the person who is learning to map their individual aspirations to recognised outcomes and experiences that will help get them reach those aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shubhangar’s parting point was both poignant and prescient:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The future of UX isn’t just knowing what users want. It’s knowing when they’ve had enough&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;richard-vahrman&#34;&gt;Richard Vahrman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great to see Richard again, after a 1-year hiatus. Richard, although he self-describes as someone who is not a UX designer, is brilliant at creating a memorable experience in 20 minutes. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to give too much away about Richard&amp;rsquo;s session as he was using it as an opportunity to test ideas for a future project. However, I am aways inspired by his ability to take people on a journey and pull people into his world. There is a such a playfulness to his ideas, while retaining a connection to more serious ideas in the case of his future project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard inspired the Godzilla card when I recently facilitated the &lt;a href=&#34;https://servicedesignbreakfast.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Clearleft Service Design Breakfast&lt;/a&gt;. His game using every day objects, reframed as talisman and trading objects, was brilliant. It really got people in the audience to think about group affiliations, the &amp;lsquo;in&amp;rsquo; crowd and &amp;lsquo;out&amp;rsquo; crowd and societal norms. This was &amp;lsquo;metaphor&amp;rsquo; at a level that anyone could understand, regardless of pre-existing knowledge, and for this reason it was absolute genius!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/GodzillaCard.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Three cards in a row from my generative AI discussion card game. The first card shows a hand-drawn Godzilla holding a plane with Japanese characters, then a question card about a wasteful AI processing workflow. Then an speculative equation for thinking about whether AI is the right solution&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ghaith-nassar&#34;&gt;Ghaith Nassar&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ghaith took us on a fascinating tour of how the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uk.bookshop.org/p/books/pedagogy-of-the-oppressed-paulo-freire/3823089?ean=9780241301111&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pedagogy of the Oppressed&lt;/em&gt; by Paulo Freire (1970)&lt;/a&gt; and how the book has influenced their practice as a multi-disciplinary designer and facilitator. I have reserved this book through my university library membership and look forward to reading it&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the embodied way that Ghaith presented the content. Placing the printed out would-be slides on the glass wall in the room. This allowed us to see a holistic map of the concepts as well as where we were currently were in the journey. It made me wish that there were a way of doing this in a presentation without it becoming inaccessible. &lt;a href=&#34;https://prezi.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prezi&lt;/a&gt; tried to accomplish this as a tool, however, it was always bound by the teacher&amp;rsquo;s or presenter&amp;rsquo;s path through the content. I found this approach delightfully metacognitive as a theme in Freire&amp;rsquo;s writing, as Ghaith described and I have interpreted was for the &amp;rsquo;teacher&amp;rsquo; to address their own hubris. What better way than to allow the &amp;lsquo;students&amp;rsquo; in the room to engage with the content now, and also look around to the content of now. I found myself looking back at the earlier concepts and seeing the connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing knowledge is not linear. So, why is it almost always a timeline? We let our tools dictate so much of what we do (&amp;lsquo;ahem, PowerPoint&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teachers have something to learn from students and students have something to learn from teachers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect that I found fascinating was this little equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflection + Action = Word = Praxis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved how Ghaith broke this down for us&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Action&lt;/strong&gt; ~ &amp;ldquo;Transform the world&amp;rdquo;
&lt;strong&gt;Word&lt;/strong&gt; ~ &amp;ldquo;Rights for everyone. With people not for people.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;strong&gt;Praxis&lt;/strong&gt; ~ Putting theory into practice or as per the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/praxis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cambridge English Dictionary definition&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;ldquo;the process of using a theory or something that you have learned in a practical way&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what about the relationship between the component parts of this equation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove &amp;lsquo;Action&amp;rsquo; and you are left with &amp;ldquo;Idle Chatter&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove &amp;lsquo;Reflection&amp;rsquo; and you are left with &amp;ldquo;Activism&amp;rdquo; for activism&amp;rsquo;s sake. Perhaps forgetting why you took action in the first place, is the action even still appropriate for meeting the desired end state?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equation above, together with the five pillars of dialogue (&amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;Love&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Humility&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Faith&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trust&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Hope&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;) are elements that I will consider including in my super group of thinking structures and frameworks. That is for a future blog post/s and was the topic of my own UX Camp presentation this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;reality as a process, as transformation, rather than as a static entity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;claire-bown&#34;&gt;Claire Bown&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I heard Claire speak at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://weareshesays.com/chapters/shesays-brighton/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SheSays Brighton&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.internationalwomensday.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;International Women&amp;rsquo;s Day&lt;/a&gt; event earlier this year and found her background in marketing and transition into AI consulting to be inspirational. As someone who spends a quite a bit of time researching and thinking about LLMs and machine learning, Claire&amp;rsquo;s talk covered some familiar ground. Regardless, I appreciated the visual way she presented both issues with gender equality in tech and the consequential issue of gender bias in the outputs form diffusion models. This will be further exacerbated by the prevalence of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychology#WEIRD_bias&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WEIRD biased data&lt;/a&gt; in the training models, so where women&amp;rsquo;s data is included, it will be predominantly Western and predominantly White. This is something that Michael Kibedi has discussed and explored on his &lt;a href=&#34;https://uxmichaelco.substack.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;First &amp;amp; Fifteenth Substack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claire asked &lt;a href=&#34;https://openai.com/index/hello-gpt-4o/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ChatGPT&amp;rsquo;s GPT-4o&lt;/a&gt; image generation to create an image for each professional role typically found on a product team. Interestingly all the images sort of look liked versions of the same caucasian man, with varying levels of facial hair. The exception was the UX designer who was both a woman and of mixed race. Without understanding more about the training data, it is hard to know why this role was different. If we assume majority US data, then the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uxpa.org/salary-surveys/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UXPA Salary Survey&lt;/a&gt; has pointed towards there being more women than men in UX roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.careerexplorer.com/careers/ux-designer/demographics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Career Explorer by Sokanu&lt;/a&gt; suggests that 53% of UX Designers are women in the US as compared to 47% men. This source also cites that many men more are interested in UX roles than are actually working in them, suggesting a bias towards women in the role. So, as compared to other roles, like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.careerexplorer.com/careers/app-developer/demographics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;App Developer&lt;/a&gt; (77% men | 23% women) this goes some way to explaining the generated image. The reason for the other characteristics remains unknown and I can only surmise that there might be something in the position of UX Designer as an advocate for all users that the model opted to be more representative of all users. A more linear explanation could be the language used to describe UX roles in job descriptions is typically femme-coded as &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@LadiesthatUX_Br/ltux-brighton-femme-coded-work-in-tech-4bc80b594cd7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LTUX Brighton, explored through a discussion panel last year.&lt;/a&gt; The panel included &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/intentionaut/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Saielle DaSilva&lt;/a&gt; who has spoken on this topic at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mindtheproduct.com/the-f-words-of-highly-successful-product-organisations-by-saielle-dasilva/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mind the Product&lt;/a&gt;. I need to do more research on this myself, anecdotally having looked at a lot of job descriptions recently I wonder if words like, empathy, collaboration, co-design, facilitation, listening, guiding, liaising, might lead an LLM towards this bias? (couching this thought&amp;hellip;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to the outputs above, I find this flagrant bias pretty disappointing. It concerns me that most things we build digitally seem to perpetuate the mistakes of the past rather than envisioning an entangled and messy, yet more humane future (á la &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ribaj.com/culture/profile-indy-johar-dark-matter-labs-boring-revolution&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Indy Johar&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;https://darkmatterlabs.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dark Matter Labs&lt;/a&gt;). I am not anti-AI by any means, I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://chat.greenpt.ai/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GreenPT&lt;/a&gt; and to supplement my own research for the paragraph above. I also use several other models in contextually sensitive and productivity focused ways. However, we really really need to try harder and not take what these companies, or their models, say at face value without scrutiny. Just as I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t believe a human, unless they provided evidence of what they were saying–even high trust humans&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; get things wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skepticism is probably one of the healthiest habits to cultivate. You can then feel happy on the occasions when you are proven wrong. It is the best route to critically responsible optimism!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my main take away from Claire&amp;rsquo;s talk - what do these platforms want?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;They want to keep you using their platform, their model.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, change it up, don&amp;rsquo;t have single brand loyalty try the same prompt in a different model and see how it performs. However, before you do, ask yourself my &lt;em&gt;Create Another Way&lt;/em&gt; question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; of the &lt;strong&gt;output&lt;/strong&gt; proportionate to the &lt;strong&gt;effort&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;cost&lt;/strong&gt; of the &lt;strong&gt;input&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, this is an existential question. If this question causes you to stop, pause, and create a single more effective prompt, in place of three, then I have done my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next year (although I will definitely blog sooner!), I leave you with Rebecca Hugo&amp;rsquo;s amazing speed tapping skills, as applied to the 2025 UX Camp Brighton quiz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/SpeedTapping.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Rebecca&#39;s using two fingers on one hand on a smartphone to extremely rapidly press on a click counter app, then changes strategy and moves the phone to her lap and presses even faster&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not related to the &amp;ldquo;AI-First Controversy&amp;rdquo;, a multifaceted issue discussed eloquently by &lt;a href=&#34;https://knowyourmeme.com/editorials/guides/whats-the-duolingo-ai-first-controversy-the-ceos-pro-ai-message-and-the-online-backlash-explained&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Know Your Meme&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time of writing I am now reading Freire&amp;rsquo;s book. Due to the way the book and the arguments within are structured, the format Ghaith used now makes even more sense!&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you consider me a &amp;ldquo;high-trust human&amp;rdquo; then I&amp;rsquo;m telling you now that I get things wrong and that is part of how I continually learn. It is possible that this post will have &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; things in it when I look back in future. However, unlike an LLM when you chat with me I will include phrases like, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;you&amp;rsquo;ll want to double-check this&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;*I&amp;rsquo;ll answer with the caveat that&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;I will come back to you with a more complete answer&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UX Camp 2025 Reflections</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2025/06/ux-camp-2025-reflections/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 08:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2025/06/ux-camp-2025-reflections/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-things-manageable&#34;&gt;Making things manageable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-brief-catch-up-on-the-last-24-months&#34;&gt;A brief catch-up on the last 24 months&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site has been loved and it has been updated. However, between December 2023 and December 2025, I sort of lost myself a bit. The TL:DR version is between working on Ladies that UX Brighton (now &amp;lsquo;LTUX Brighton&amp;rsquo;) and working in a full-time agency role I lost sight of my thinking/academic/artistic pursuits; I let my reflective practice slip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bizarre irony is at last year&amp;rsquo;s UX Camp, in my opinion I hosted my second-best session, on &lt;a href=&#34;event/uxcamp2024/index&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;research hacks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (my first would have to be &lt;a href=&#34;2016/03/talk-factors-of-trust-in-iot-app-interfaces/index&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trust in IoT Systems&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; back in 2016 when I was invited back for the &lt;a href=&#34;2016/06/trust-in-iot-app-interfaces-redux/index&#34;&gt;redux event&lt;/a&gt;, which meant it must have been good!). Last year I even prepared materials for a series of session-related blog posts here explaining how to do each of the hacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did I post them?
No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a matter of personal shame on my &amp;rsquo;todo&amp;rsquo; list for an entire year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/ShameNuns.gif&#34; alt=&#34;The shame nuns with a bell from Game of Thrones walking through the streets shaking bells.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-new-leaf-is-unfurling&#34;&gt;A new leaf is unfurling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;m starting afresh. I have radically reduced the number of posts on this site. Only keeping the most important reflections in a bid to help reduce this site&amp;rsquo;s energy use to a minimum. I also started my own Limited company in January, Macknowlogist, contracting in UX, research, and technology. Working for myself has a different cadence, enabling me to re-jig my reflective practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-am-i-doing-differently-this-time&#34;&gt;What am I doing differently this time?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have created a template in Obsidian to help write these posts efficiently in markdown, from the start.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to write shorter posts more often to keep this site fresh. In particular I will &lt;strong&gt;write&lt;/strong&gt; posts on how I am developing the decision-making framework I previewed at UX Camp this year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On occasion I will write long form posts, but this must be intentional rather than accidental.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am self-editing by using washable index cards and other methods to keep things more concise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of all I am sketching more and more in my life and work and that is such a brilliant and restorative change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/SketchbookApril2025.webp&#34; alt=&#34;A very busy systems thinking page of my sketchbook with diagrams connections, notes, and scribbles&#34; /&gt;
&lt;caption&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not so much sketching on this page - this was the start of the ideas for the ethical framework, with various influences including John V Willshire&#39;s work on the top-right.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ux-camp-2025-rundown&#34;&gt;UX Camp 2025 Rundown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-ux-camp-brighton&#34;&gt;What is UX Camp Brighton?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only the best annual UX event in Brighton in my opinion (not a paid endorsement). Run impeccably by Patrick Samson, Lou Bloom, Luke Hay, Tom Prior, Chris How, Deeksha Bhushan, and Rob Pearson, it is an event where everyone is made to feel welcome to share their ideas on UX. As a &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;bar camp&lt;/a&gt; style event there is no agenda until the hosts arrive and place their session synopsis cards. Each session is limited to 20 mins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been going to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uxcampbrighton.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UX Camp Brighton&lt;/a&gt; since about 2014 and it has been, and continues to be, instrumental to my practice and learning. The other thing I find impressive is that every year, I can see how they have taken feedback onboard, improving the event and making it more inclusive. Like this year having the option of asking an organiser to pitch in the main room to the audience to remove that stressor. Nice!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sessions-i-got-to-see&#34;&gt;The sessions I got to see&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five sessions run simultaneously in each time slot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session you get to attend is based on three factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well the host&amp;rsquo;s pitch resonated with you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether you could get to the room on time before its too full&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t you need to either have a back-up choice, or make your way to a room with space #potluck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the sessions below were delightful brainfood regardless of the above. Truly, I always wish I could attend all of them. I have summarised my favourite concept from each session below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;graeme-aymer&#34;&gt;Graeme Aymer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graeme shared the relevance of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Baldwin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;James Balwin&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; writing (1924–1987) to compassion in UX. He expertly took us on a journey of analysis through the following Baldwin quote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Love has never been a popular movement. And no one&amp;rsquo;s ever wanted, really, to be free. The world is held together, really it is held together, by the love and the passion of a very few people. Otherwise, of course, you can despair. Walk down the street of any city, any afternoon, and look around you. What you&amp;rsquo;ve got to remember is what you&amp;rsquo;re looking at is also you. Everyone you&amp;rsquo;re looking at is also you. You could be that person. You could be that monster, you could be that cop. And you have to decide, in yourself, not to be.”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;~ James Baldwin (1970)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everyone you&amp;rsquo;re looking at is also you&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reminded me of the quote, &amp;ldquo;Be kind, for everyone you meet is fighting a harder battle&amp;rdquo;, or some variation of that. This quote is often attributed to Plato, Alice Walker, or Robin Williams–just proving that finding truth on the internet has been and always shall be a tenuous venture unless you have time to pull at all the threads. Hmm, remember this dear reader the next you use AI as a search engine 🤔&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless this is an important message, to paraphrase Graeme: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;you are the silos, you are the bad work culture, you are the stakeholders, you are the participants, you are the colleagues, you are the bosses, you are the direct reports, you are the customers using your designs&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. This is such a crucial point, not only in terms of empathy, but also in terms of taking action. It reminds us that we can actually change those systems, those hierarchies, because they are us and we are them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You could be that monster&amp;hellip;and you have to decide in yourself not to be&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sayani-mitra&#34;&gt;Sayani Mitra&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sayani provided a comprehensive overview of how UX research could help to improve and enhance AI-focused products and products where AI is being implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved Sayani&amp;rsquo;s easy to follow list structures to sit alongside the product development process. In a tech environment where research roles are under threat, often because of tight budgets, and the &amp;lsquo;promise&amp;rsquo; of AI for research (without researchers!) this is the talk we all needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I particularly loved the following aspects, which I plan to add to my &amp;lsquo;super-group&amp;rsquo; of decision-making frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncover&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; the real-world context early. What problem are you actually solving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prevent&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; prevent tech-first decision-making&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Define&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; value before features and map these&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audit&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; bias in datasets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Influence&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;hellip; the final product output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;sayanis-5-ps-of-ethical-ai&#34;&gt;Sayani&amp;rsquo;s 5 P&amp;rsquo;s of Ethical AI&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt; - Is AI even needed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People&lt;/strong&gt; - Who gains, who loses?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Process&lt;/strong&gt; - How is it designed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power&lt;/strong&gt; - Who controls outcomes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proof&lt;/strong&gt; - Is there proof that this thing even works in this context (my notes got smudged here, so this is my interpretation - the serendipity of analogue!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the implementation of AI always comes to down to these aspects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What type of AI are talking about (e.g., LLMs, ML, automation, something else?)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What context was the chosen flavour originally designed for? It is good to understand the origins of the tool you are using and therefore it&amp;rsquo;s limitations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it adding value beyond what you can already do without AI (as in &amp;lsquo;purpose&amp;rsquo; above)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we implement it in the most efficient and least wasteful way possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much of this thinking overlaps with Sayani&amp;rsquo;s points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rebecca-hugo&#34;&gt;Rebecca Hugo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rebecca’s talk was a clever construction with several levels of meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one level it pulled some valuable points about learning and behavioural change from the &lt;em&gt;seminal film&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0215129/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Road Trip&lt;/a&gt; (2000). Specifically, one character’s proclamation that given enough time he could &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;teach Japanese to a Monkey&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. The point here is that by finding ways to relate new knowledge to existing knowledge and interests, it is possible to ‘hook’ people and help them to retain new information. Crucially, they will also be able to better apply that acquired information. In the context of the film &amp;lsquo;said&amp;rsquo; character, &lt;em&gt;Rubin&lt;/em&gt; helps another character, &lt;em&gt;Josh&lt;/em&gt; prep for an exam with limited knowledge of the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On another level Rebecca gave an example of how to use analogy in a clear way when communicating with colleagues and clients. Even if you knew nothing of Road Trip and the other pop culture references in the presentation, Rebecca’s storytelling abilities essentially used these as a series of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacGuffin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MacGuffins&lt;/a&gt;. As in references relevant to the main protagonist or subject but irrelevant on their own in isolation. By using a range of references she added value for those who knew the reference and supplied intrigue to those who did not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, this talk was stacked full of useful advice and as a designer who focuses on learning. I enjoyed revisiting concepts such as ‘memory palaces’ (also known as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Method_of_loci&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;method of loci&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;), and the ‘&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/sH5i2skyCAU?feature=shared&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;story method’&lt;/a&gt;. I particularly chimed with Rebecca&amp;rsquo;s point that external skills and knowledge can come into play in your UX career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few of my favourite sound bites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same but different &lt;br /&gt;
Simply speak simply &lt;br /&gt;
Respond to the responses &lt;br /&gt;
Make it make sense&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating mottos is yet another helpful memetic and it is something that I know Rebecca excels at, having attended her talks at several UX Camp Brighton events over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;alex-edwards&#34;&gt;Alex Edwards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex talked about the steps for closing the Discovery process. Alex is a design strategist and it was superb to gain insight into the level of thought and learning layers of consideration involved in her work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key point for me was getting the right people in the room. This correlates with my experience as a consultant. It can certainly feel uncomfortable as you need to accept that there will be dissent. However, if you don’t take stakeholders on the journey with you from the start then you are destined for trouble later down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved Alex’s thinking around the different stakeholders you need to appeal to when wrapping up discovery (the preparatory research phase of any design project).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stakeholders were…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decision makers &lt;br /&gt;
Subject matter experts &lt;br /&gt;
Broader stakeholders &lt;br /&gt;
Snoopers and Poopers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last group, &amp;ldquo;snoopers and poopers&amp;rdquo; is the one you only learn about through experience. It is bet to figure out who they are as soon as you can, so that your project isn’t shut down by someone with an opposing agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved Alex’s approach to cataloguing insights throughout the discovery phase, with a table for listing all the content collected, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;transcriptions,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;information from the client,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;desk research,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought that the inclusion of star ratings out of five for the ‘applicability’, and ‘level of detail’ were really helpful criteria. I’ll definitely consider how to implement this in my own practice. Particularly as a new contractor, I often work alone. I do this work as well, but don’t have a central mapping or record of it. I will try using &lt;a href=&#34;https://obsidian.md/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Obsidian notebooks&lt;/a&gt; with a table like this at the top level. This might be especially helpful later in projects when the design process can inadvertently drift away from Discovery findings for range of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex’s advice when considering competitors was also quite brilliant. Specifically, in addition to  researching &amp;ldquo;competitors, comparators and disruptors&amp;rdquo;, it is worth considering the &amp;ldquo;household names&amp;rdquo; and then looking for patterns. Not only do I need to add this into my own process, but I also want to pull in, “how do/did they solve this problem now/before?”. Remembering that an analogue process might be a competitor is important and it is something I often encountered when working in Higher Education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a personal reflection, when under high levels of stress I retreat from my careful time boxing and resort to hand-written notes which then get into a state of disarray, adding to the stress. The solution? Have an A4 sized whiteboard to put thoughts onto and if I don’t digitise them they gradually degrade and get rubbed out by my wrist. There is also an analogue satisfaction to erasing these notes and at least I am no longer going through reams of paper notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/whiteboard-example.webp&#34; alt=&#34;An A4 sized whiteboard with scribbled notes on it, that are partially erased&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great tool suggestion from Alex was &lt;a href=&#34;https://octopus.do/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Octopus.do&lt;/a&gt; which builds visual site maps and screenflows. This is a really helpful way to understand dead ends. I did try it for a current project – it couldn&amp;rsquo;t quite handle all the layers of navigation. Regardless, I can see Octopus.do&amp;rsquo;s potential, even though I ended up mapping the structure manually in Figjam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;insights&#34;&gt;Insights&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after all this how do you “distillate the wins”? Alex used &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.airtable.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Airtable&lt;/a&gt; to collate the findings and also noted that affinity mapping as you go is key. You cannot leave this until later, you need to capture this thinking as you go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the concept of “sticky phrases” was very powerful and a great way for converting insights to memorable mottos (there we are with the mottos again!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of great examples were…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One size fits none&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Frontline staff are the heroes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the most important thing with discovery is to outline how, and crucially when, it will be actioned. This is key to ROI (return on investment) and something that I have learned the hard way in the past. Discovery and research in general are perceived as expensive, it is critical to show that discovery is not an optional part of the process and to close the phase in an action oriented way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This can happen, we are ready to start&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;shubhangar-sidharthan&#34;&gt;Shubhangar Sidharthan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shubhangar’s talk was a much needed wake-up call for me and for this reason it gained my vote as my favourite talk of the day in the follow-up survey. Shubhangar provided a comprehensive summary of algorithmic changes to personalisation in apps such as Instagram and TikTok. He covered the user benefits, as well as the algorithmic siloing, and the addictive tendencies that could be stimulated by these design decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This talk was a powerful reminder of how I need to engage with this tech to understand trends, even if I choose not to engage beyond professional necessity. I had a TikTok account back in 2021 when I made a number of accessibility focused learning videos. At the time, I was astounded by the level of engagement and positive responses compared to my experience using YouTube. However, I could also see that that this interface was, as Shubhangar astutely described a “fruit machine”. Having an awareness of my own tendencies I chose to switch off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have observed in learning how much the trends and personalisation evident in apps, like the aforementioned and Duolingo, have been adopted in learning platforms. However, I find myself questioning how affective swipe-centric learning really is, beyond initial engagement. At the end of the day it still isn’t embodied learning and for it to really stick it needs to be applied in the real world and be relevant to the goals of the person. No amount of personalisation will change that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the point of addiction, there is such a thing as addictive learning and not in a good way. I had a 400+ day streak on Duolingo which I recently ended for good&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The main reason was I felt pwned by the owl. As Duolingo resorted to increasingly manipulative design patterns (many have commented on this–a good overview by &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/blog/duolingos-emotional-blackmail-591a14cdf98d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Harris Sockel on Medium&lt;/a&gt;). I could feel this process taking hold and adding to my stress levels. Disrupting my sleep by encouraging me to continue the streak before bed, rather than reading a book and allowing my brain to switch down a gear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During those 400+ days, I learned a lot of French vocab, but so much of it was reliant on recognition rather than recall and unless I went to France on a regular basis, applying this knowledge in the real world, it won’t stick (see &lt;em&gt;Praxis&lt;/em&gt; later in this post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I come back to the need for learning to be supported by both intrinsic and extrinsic motivation. The true benefit of personalisation being the opportunity for the person who is learning to map their individual aspirations to recognised outcomes and experiences that will help get them reach those aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shubhangar’s parting point was both poignant and prescient:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The future of UX isn’t just knowing what users want. It’s knowing when they’ve had enough&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;richard-vahrman&#34;&gt;Richard Vahrman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great to see Richard again, after a 1-year hiatus. Richard, although he self-describes as someone who is not a UX designer, is brilliant at creating a memorable experience in 20 minutes. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to give too much away about Richard&amp;rsquo;s session as he was using it as an opportunity to test ideas for a future project. However, I am aways inspired by his ability to take people on a journey and pull people into his world. There is a such a playfulness to his ideas, while retaining a connection to more serious ideas in the case of his future project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard inspired the Godzilla card when I recently facilitated the &lt;a href=&#34;https://servicedesignbreakfast.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Clearleft Service Design Breakfast&lt;/a&gt;. His game using every day objects, reframed as talisman and trading objects, was brilliant. It really got people in the audience to think about group affiliations, the &amp;lsquo;in&amp;rsquo; crowd and &amp;lsquo;out&amp;rsquo; crowd and societal norms. This was &amp;lsquo;metaphor&amp;rsquo; at a level that anyone could understand, regardless of pre-existing knowledge, and for this reason it was absolute genius!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/GodzillaCard.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Three cards in a row from my generative AI discussion card game. The first card shows a hand-drawn Godzilla holding a plane with Japanese characters, then a question card about a wasteful AI processing workflow. Then an speculative equation for thinking about whether AI is the right solution&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ghaith-nassar&#34;&gt;Ghaith Nassar&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ghaith took us on a fascinating tour of how the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uk.bookshop.org/p/books/pedagogy-of-the-oppressed-paulo-freire/3823089?ean=9780241301111&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pedagogy of the Oppressed&lt;/em&gt; by Paulo Freire (1970)&lt;/a&gt; and how the book has influenced their practice as a multi-disciplinary designer and facilitator. I have reserved this book through my university library membership and look forward to reading it&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the embodied way that Ghaith presented the content. Placing the printed out would-be slides on the glass wall in the room. This allowed us to see a holistic map of the concepts as well as where we were currently were in the journey. It made me wish that there were a way of doing this in a presentation without it becoming inaccessible. &lt;a href=&#34;https://prezi.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prezi&lt;/a&gt; tried to accomplish this as a tool, however, it was always bound by the teacher&amp;rsquo;s or presenter&amp;rsquo;s path through the content. I found this approach delightfully metacognitive as a theme in Freire&amp;rsquo;s writing, as Ghaith described and I have interpreted was for the &amp;rsquo;teacher&amp;rsquo; to address their own hubris. What better way than to allow the &amp;lsquo;students&amp;rsquo; in the room to engage with the content now, and also look around to the content of now. I found myself looking back at the earlier concepts and seeing the connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing knowledge is not linear. So, why is it almost always a timeline? We let our tools dictate so much of what we do (&amp;lsquo;ahem, PowerPoint&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teachers have something to learn from students and students have something to learn from teachers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect that I found fascinating was this little equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflection + Action = Word = Praxis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved how Ghaith broke this down for us&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Action&lt;/strong&gt; ~ &amp;ldquo;Transform the world&amp;rdquo;
&lt;strong&gt;Word&lt;/strong&gt; ~ &amp;ldquo;Rights for everyone. With people not for people.&amp;rdquo;
&lt;strong&gt;Praxis&lt;/strong&gt; ~ Putting theory into practice or as per the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/praxis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cambridge English Dictionary definition&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;ldquo;the process of using a theory or something that you have learned in a practical way&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what about the relationship between the component parts of this equation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove &amp;lsquo;Action&amp;rsquo; and you are left with &amp;ldquo;Idle Chatter&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove &amp;lsquo;Reflection&amp;rsquo; and you are left with &amp;ldquo;Activism&amp;rdquo; for activism&amp;rsquo;s sake. Perhaps forgetting why you took action in the first place, is the action even still appropriate for meeting the desired end state?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equation above, together with the five pillars of dialogue (&amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;Love&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Humility&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Faith&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trust&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Hope&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;) are elements that I will consider including in my super group of thinking structures and frameworks. That is for a future blog post/s and was the topic of my own UX Camp presentation this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;reality as a process, as transformation, rather than as a static entity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;claire-bown&#34;&gt;Claire Bown&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I heard Claire speak at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://weareshesays.com/chapters/shesays-brighton/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SheSays Brighton&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.internationalwomensday.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;International Women&amp;rsquo;s Day&lt;/a&gt; event earlier this year and found her background in marketing and transition into AI consulting to be inspirational. As someone who spends a quite a bit of time researching and thinking about LLMs and machine learning, Claire&amp;rsquo;s talk covered some familiar ground. Regardless, I appreciated the visual way she presented both issues with gender equality in tech and the consequential issue of gender bias in the outputs form diffusion models. This will be further exacerbated by the prevalence of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychology#WEIRD_bias&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WEIRD biased data&lt;/a&gt; in the training models, so where women&amp;rsquo;s data is included, it will be predominantly Western and predominantly White. This is something that Michael Kibedi has discussed and explored on his &lt;a href=&#34;https://uxmichaelco.substack.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;First &amp;amp; Fifteenth Substack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claire asked &lt;a href=&#34;https://openai.com/index/hello-gpt-4o/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ChatGPT&amp;rsquo;s GPT-4o&lt;/a&gt; image generation to create an image for each professional role typically found on a product team. Interestingly all the images sort of look liked versions of the same caucasian man, with varying levels of facial hair. The exception was the UX designer who was both a woman and of mixed race. Without understanding more about the training data, it is hard to know why this role was different. If we assume majority US data, then the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uxpa.org/salary-surveys/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UXPA Salary Survey&lt;/a&gt; has pointed towards there being more women than men in UX roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.careerexplorer.com/careers/ux-designer/demographics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Career Explorer by Sokanu&lt;/a&gt; suggests that 53% of UX Designers are women in the US as compared to 47% men. This source also cites that many men more are interested in UX roles than are actually working in them, suggesting a bias towards women in the role. So, as compared to other roles, like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.careerexplorer.com/careers/app-developer/demographics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;App Developer&lt;/a&gt; (77% men | 23% women) this goes some way to explaining the generated image. The reason for the other characteristics remains unknown and I can only surmise that there might be something in the position of UX Designer as an advocate for all users that the model opted to be more representative of all users. A more linear explanation could be the language used to describe UX roles in job descriptions is typically femme-coded as &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@LadiesthatUX_Br/ltux-brighton-femme-coded-work-in-tech-4bc80b594cd7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LTUX Brighton, explored through a discussion panel last year.&lt;/a&gt; The panel included &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/intentionaut/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Saielle DaSilva&lt;/a&gt; who has spoken on this topic at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mindtheproduct.com/the-f-words-of-highly-successful-product-organisations-by-saielle-dasilva/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mind the Product&lt;/a&gt;. I need to do more research on this myself, anecdotally having looked at a lot of job descriptions recently I wonder if words like, empathy, collaboration, co-design, facilitation, listening, guiding, liaising, might lead an LLM towards this bias? (couching this thought&amp;hellip;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to the outputs above, I find this flagrant bias pretty disappointing. It concerns me that most things we build digitally seem to perpetuate the mistakes of the past rather than envisioning an entangled and messy, yet more humane future (á la &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ribaj.com/culture/profile-indy-johar-dark-matter-labs-boring-revolution&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Indy Johar&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;https://darkmatterlabs.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dark Matter Labs&lt;/a&gt;). I am not anti-AI by any means, I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://chat.greenpt.ai/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GreenPT&lt;/a&gt; and to supplement my own research for the paragraph above. I also use several other models in contextually sensitive and productivity focused ways. However, we really really need to try harder and not take what these companies, or their models, say at face value without scrutiny. Just as I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t believe a human, unless they provided evidence of what they were saying–even high trust humans&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; get things wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skepticism is probably one of the healthiest habits to cultivate. You can then feel happy on the occasions when you are proven wrong. It is the best route to critically responsible optimism!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my main take away from Claire&amp;rsquo;s talk - what do these platforms want?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;They want to keep you using their platform, their model.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, change it up, don&amp;rsquo;t have single brand loyalty try the same prompt in a different model and see how it performs. However, before you do, ask yourself my &lt;em&gt;Create Another Way&lt;/em&gt; question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; of the &lt;strong&gt;output&lt;/strong&gt; proportionate to the &lt;strong&gt;effort&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;cost&lt;/strong&gt; of the &lt;strong&gt;input&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, this is an existential question. If this question causes you to stop, pause, and create a single more effective prompt, in place of three, then I have done my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next year (although I will definitely blog sooner!), I leave you with Rebecca Hugo&amp;rsquo;s amazing speed tapping skills, as applied to the 2025 UX Camp Brighton quiz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;images/SpeedTapping.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Rebecca&#39;s using two fingers on one hand on a smartphone to extremely rapidly press on a click counter app, then changes strategy and moves the phone to her lap and presses even faster&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34; /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not related to the &amp;ldquo;AI-First Controversy&amp;rdquo;, a multifaceted issue discussed eloquently by &lt;a href=&#34;https://knowyourmeme.com/editorials/guides/whats-the-duolingo-ai-first-controversy-the-ceos-pro-ai-message-and-the-online-backlash-explained&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Know Your Meme&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time of writing I am now reading Freire&amp;rsquo;s book. Due to the way the book and the arguments within are structured, the format Ghaith used now makes even more sense!&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you consider me a &amp;ldquo;high-trust human&amp;rdquo; then I&amp;rsquo;m telling you now that I get things wrong and that is part of how I continually learn. It is possible that this post will have &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; things in it when I look back in future. However, unlike an LLM when you chat with me I will include phrases like, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;you&amp;rsquo;ll want to double-check this&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;*I&amp;rsquo;ll answer with the caveat that&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;I will come back to you with a more complete answer&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Falling back in love with the humble RSS feed</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2023 11:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kudos&#34;&gt;Kudos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post is inspired by a tip from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.alpower.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Al Power&lt;/a&gt;, who suggested that I check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://netnewswire.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NetNewsWire app&lt;/a&gt; (Mac, iPhone, iPad). Read Al&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.alpower.com/blog/my-news-feed-reader-setup/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;post at his blog for more details&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-history-of-my-relationship-with-rss&#34;&gt;A history of my relationship with RSS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-first-blog&#34;&gt;My first blog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My relationship with blogging and frontend web development began in 2005 when I started my first blog, &lt;em&gt;The Anatomy of an Armpit&lt;/em&gt;. The blog, which was on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blogger_%28service%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google&amp;rsquo;s Blogger platform&lt;/a&gt;, recounted my trials and tribulations while stuck in an area of Scotland I wasn&amp;rsquo;t fond of - as I was a youth at the time you can probably imagine the content (&lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; ill-advised Tumblr-style rants). Regardless, I owe a lot to my first blog which got me interested in HTML, CSS, frontend web design, accessibility, and usability - interests that I have to this very day. It also helped me gain an understanding of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RSS or Really Simple Syndication&lt;/a&gt;, which at that time was the main way to stay up-to-date on your favourite bloggers&amp;rsquo; content. At first this was via humble browser tools and bookmarking, then via the long defunct, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Reader&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Reader&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-first-podcast&#34;&gt;My first podcast&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then in 2006 I got into podcasting, a technology reliant on RSS metadata and distribution. To say I was ahead of the curve on this would be an understatement. At that time hosting a podcast was a painfully slow process and I used one of the more user-friendly tools, &lt;a href=&#34;https://libsyn.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Libsyn&lt;/a&gt; or Liberated Syndication. It would take 2 to 4 hours to upload one episode to your site host only to find out that the audio artifacting was so bad, you&amp;rsquo;d have to start again. I had many an all-nighter for the love of my show, &lt;em&gt;Motif Radio&lt;/em&gt; (you can still see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20060909220813/http://motifradio.libsyn.com:80/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;snapshots on the Internet Archive WayBack Machine&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;em&gt;Motif Radio&lt;/em&gt; was inspired by London arts radio station, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.resonancefm.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ResonanceFM&lt;/a&gt; and was eclectic to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Motif Radio&lt;/em&gt; cooincided with one of the most creative and productive periods in my life. It was also a time of hardship and so much of that difficulty fed into my passion for creating the podcast. One of my favourite memories was a successful episode release, it finished uploading by 11.30 pm which was highly unusual. I was so elated that my partner and I went to the midnight showing of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0434409/?ref_=fn_al_tt_1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;V for Vendetta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; at the Mall of America to celebrate. Even though it isn&amp;rsquo;t the best film, it will always have a place in my heart for that reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;podcasts---a-longterm-obsession&#34;&gt;Podcasts - a longterm obsession!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My obsession with podcasts continues to this day and I&amp;rsquo;m an avid follower of about thirty of them, funding my favourite creators on Patreon. I have often thought about resurrecting &lt;em&gt;Motif Radio&lt;/em&gt;, which ended in 2007, especially as now, after many years, I have the audio kit to do so. Something to consider on as we go into 2024, although it would need to come back under a new name as there is now another &lt;a href=&#34;https://motif-radio.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Motif Radio&lt;/a&gt; which specialises in urban music. In the meantime I have enjoyed my guest hosting spots on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://podcasters.spotify.com/pod/show/ltux-in-english&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ladies that UX podcast in English&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;so-why-the-return-to-rss-after-all-this-time&#34;&gt;So why the return to RSS after all this time?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was working on some frontend web development at my job and I setup a new RSS feed as part of that. While configuring the feed I fell in love once again with the simplicity, the clarity of information, and the potential for curatorial serendipity. What do I mean by &amp;lsquo;curatorial serendipity&amp;rsquo;? Well in the era of &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; and its ilk, so much of what I consume is curated by algorithms on my behalf. On the one hand this is helpful, as content is rich and time is short, but what is being filtered out? Am I missing the other books on the shelf which might be more interesting than the book I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; I need? Or to continue this library-inspired analogy, those other books might be more interesting than the book the library catalogue &lt;em&gt;thinks&lt;/em&gt; I need. I was yearning for a bit more control to follow the feeds that I really care about - enter &lt;a href=&#34;https://netnewswire.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NetNewsWire&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Ranchero-Software&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Brent Simmons&lt;/a&gt; which is my new favourite. An RSS curation app which allows me to setup up my feeds, sync them to iCloud, and access them on all my devices. More on that below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like to subscribe to this blog using RSS, here is the URL you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34; data-lang=&#34;html&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- xml feed for this blog--&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;https://www.fionamacneill.co.uk/index.xml
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;To find out the RSS feed for just about any site, including your favourite content on Medium, check out this helpful &lt;a href=&#34;https://zapier.com/blog/how-to-find-rss-feed-url/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;post on Zapier blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an added tip for sites using static site generators like Hugo, a good rule to follow is to take the root of the site and add &amp;lsquo;index.xml&amp;rsquo;. So I&amp;rsquo;d start by looking at the site footer and then the page source to identify which generator is in use. Then try adding &amp;lsquo;/index.xml&amp;rsquo; at the end and see if you get a page that looks like a feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E.g.,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take the example of one of my favourite websites about retractions in research, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://forrt.org/reversals/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;FORRT - Framework for Open and Reproducible Research Training&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I take a look at the footer of the site&amp;hellip;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-ah-thats-helpful-they-tell-me-it-is-made-with-hugo-in-the-footer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Forrt example - the website footer is shown which helpfully tells the site is made with Hugo&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/00ForrtExample_hu4052572961905556236.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/00ForrtExample_hu12930152033908072768.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/00ForrtExample_hu4333904368738214092.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/00ForrtExample_hu4052572961905556236.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;160&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;em&gt;Ah that&amp;rsquo;s helpful they tell me it is made with Hugo in the footer.&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then try adding /index.xml to the root web address&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34; data-lang=&#34;html&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;!--The website https://forrt.org/reversals/ becomes...--&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;https://forrt.org/index.xml
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-i-know-a-feed-when-i-see-one&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Forrt example - the feed page which shows metadata in xml code format&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/01ForrtExample_hu1266796247584971859.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/01ForrtExample_hu2215385035868816078.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/01ForrtExample_hu2543788095747838520.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/01ForrtExample_hu1266796247584971859.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;390&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;em&gt;I know a feed when I see one!&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bingo! There is the feed that I want for NetNewsWire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;festive-giving-aside&#34;&gt;Festive giving aside&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As as aside, this post is clearly indepted to both &lt;a href=&#34;https://donate.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special:LandingPage&amp;amp;country=GB&amp;amp;uselang=en&amp;amp;utm_medium=donatewiki_page&amp;amp;utm_source=Ways_to_Give&amp;amp;utm_campaign=donate_now_btn&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/donate&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;. I note that they both organisations have active fund-drives for the end of year. I will be giving to both as these types of organisations are important for preserving knowledge and transient digital artefacts. In a web which is progressively less free, I give back where I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rss---my-new-old-love&#34;&gt;RSS - my &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; old love&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So having now moved my feeds from Feedly, which I had a) forgotten about, and b) got annoyed with its paywall limitations - I am now once again enjoying my old-school blog consumption. My only slight gripe is that some of my favourite sites (ahem, NNG) do not have RSS feeds for their articles. I might start asking nicely as I feel it is time for an RSS comeback!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bonus-tutorial---how-i-moved-from-feedly&#34;&gt;Bonus tutorial - how I moved from Feedly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started in NetNewsWire by setting up my feed account in my iCloud storage. As NetNewsWire accepts emoji&amp;rsquo;s I couldn&amp;rsquo;t resist including a wee satellite emoji in my account name. Then I completed the following steps to migrate my RSS feeds from Feedly in OPML format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to your profile options on the bottom-left of Feedly (your avatar or the default placeholder).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select &amp;lsquo;Organize Feeds&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-click-on-your-avatarplaceholder-to-get-to-the-options&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Feedly account options - Organize Feeds is selected&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/01_Feedly_OrgFeeds_hu14135275574887153487.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/01_Feedly_OrgFeeds_hu15885409520482720785.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/01_Feedly_OrgFeeds_hu9232497157064194759.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/01_Feedly_OrgFeeds_hu14135275574887153487.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;400&#34;
               height=&#34;478&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;em&gt;Click on your avatar/placeholder to get to the options&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on the arrow on the right-hand side (great signposting here, anyone would think they might not want you to export your feeds&amp;hellip;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-click-on-the-non-descript-arrow-on-the-right-to-get-to-the-export-options&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Feedly OPML export arrow is shown&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/02_FeedlyExportYourFeeds_hu3816599171249320179.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/02_FeedlyExportYourFeeds_hu9261640742618808962.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/02_FeedlyExportYourFeeds_hu11730319665310116983.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/02_FeedlyExportYourFeeds_hu3816599171249320179.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;202&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;em&gt;Click on the non-descript arrow on the right to get to the export options&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download your Feedly OPML file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-click-on-the-big-green-button-to-get-your-opml-file-with-all-your-feedy-goodness&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Feedly OPML export button to initiate download&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/03_FeedlyOPMLExport_hu5037047899383026241.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/03_FeedlyOPMLExport_hu12834360592337868117.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/03_FeedlyOPMLExport_hu364207621991485832.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/03_FeedlyOPMLExport_hu5037047899383026241.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;207&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;em&gt;Click on the big green button to get your OPML file with all your feedy-goodness&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then open NetNewsWire and go to File &amp;gt; Import Subscriptions in the top menu bar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-in-netnewswire-access-the-import-option-from-file-in-the-top-menu-bar&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;NetNewsWire top menu, file, then import subscriptions option&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/04_NetNewsWire_ImportSubscriptions_hu15933679496086481210.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/04_NetNewsWire_ImportSubscriptions_hu16309521309018850666.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/04_NetNewsWire_ImportSubscriptions_hu17007930714363257810.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/04_NetNewsWire_ImportSubscriptions_hu15933679496086481210.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;394&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;em&gt;In NetNewsWire, access the import option from File in the top menu bar&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select your feed account and then select &amp;lsquo;Import from OPML&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-select-the-account-you-want-to-use-in-netnewswire&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;NetNewsWire - select the account that you want to import into&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/05_NetNewsWire_ImportfromOPML_hu13422806526339868307.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/05_NetNewsWire_ImportfromOPML_hu14681974085558782013.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/05_NetNewsWire_ImportfromOPML_hu6661528749697715151.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/05_NetNewsWire_ImportfromOPML_hu13422806526339868307.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;362&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;em&gt;Select the account you want to use in NetNewsWire&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the Feedly OPML from your computer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-select-the-account-you-want-to-use-in-netnewswire&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;NetNewsWire - select the OPML file which you downloaded to your computer&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/06_NetNewsWire_importfile_hu14595167636204587730.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/06_NetNewsWire_importfile_hu3310196773660815259.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/06_NetNewsWire_importfile_hu15269771724924565502.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/2023/12/humble-rss-feed/images/06_NetNewsWire_importfile_hu14595167636204587730.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;336&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;em&gt;Select the account you want to use in NetNewsWire&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then reorganise your feeds into an many folders as you like!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;housekeeping&#34;&gt;Housekeeping&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will be my last blog post for a little while as I will be updating this site. This will include an updated theme, some backend updates, and new case studies. I&amp;rsquo;ll also be finally moving some of my artefacts from the &lt;em&gt;temporary&lt;/em&gt; Notion page (temporary for two years&amp;hellip;) to this site.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
