<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Community | Fiona MacNeill | Macknowlogist</title>
    <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/tags/community/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://fionamacneill.co.uk/tags/community/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Community</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 09:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/media/icon_hu_57d0698421383678.png</url>
      <title>Community</title>
      <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/tags/community/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>LTUX Brighton presents, Talk UX: Redesigning Place</title>
      <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/events/talkux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/events/talkux/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2025, LTUX Brighton hosted the international conference for 
, 
. We hosted 32 speakers and panelists over two days and received amazing feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, Talk UX was one of the most challenging, yet fulfilling experiences of my life. It really warrants it&amp;rsquo;s own blog post, particularly because we tried to make the event as responsible and sustainable as we could. As organisers we considered this in terms of how we organised, resourcing (both in-person and digital), and environmental impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew both in so many ways as a person, as a designer, as a leader, and as a business leader through the experience. I will be forever thankful for the vision, belief, and trust or our organising group and everything we achieved together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This marked the end of my chapter leadership of LTUX Brighton. I&amp;rsquo;m staying on as treasurer as we move into next phase of our development as a group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;TalkUX-organisersonlyv2-170925.webp&#34; alt=&#34;the group of organiser for Talk UX at the front of the main room, in front of a projected image showing the Brighton beach front.&#34; /&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by Laura Rodriguez&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Left-to-right:&lt;/strong&gt; Inka Howorth, Fiona MacNeill, Heidi Swigon, Lou Carroll, Alex Woodward, Emily Clark, Deeksha Bhushan, Alice Umeji.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dialogue: community, volunteering, and setting up your own company at University of Brighton</title>
      <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/events/communityorganising/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/events/communityorganising/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
