<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Diagrams | Fiona MacNeill | Macknowlogist</title>
    <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/tags/diagrams/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://fionamacneill.co.uk/tags/diagrams/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Diagrams</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/media/icon_hu_57d0698421383678.png</url>
      <title>Diagrams</title>
      <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/tags/diagrams/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perplexed...or why we iterate</title>
      <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/blog/2015/11/perplexed-or-why-we-iterate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/blog/2015/11/perplexed-or-why-we-iterate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make, I am pretty perplexed by Unified Modeling Language (UML). If you were to look at this blog, based on the lack of posts, you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t think that I had made any progress over the past two weeks. We covered User Conceptual Modeling as a topic in class back on the 6th of November and in my last post on the 11th, I made the grand proclamation that I would complete my UML diagram by Friday (13th). Well I did create a UML diagram, and then I created another iteration and another; I became obsessed with understanding the syntax&amp;hellip;not a healthy obsession, but a frustrating one. During the past week I tried to read everything that I could in order to aid my understanding. Tonight I came to the realisation that Learning Objects are pretty hard to build in UML. I also made the decision to leave this part of the project for now and move on to writing some commentary on user requirements. I feel that by moving on, I may miss some error in the system design, but also if I continue to work on the diagram I am going to stall my progress further. This was paralleled early on in the other project that I am working on at the moment, where I attempted to create a diagram for a hypothetical wearable device as part of the Internet of Things. Four-plus iterations later I finally have something that resembles the operation of a real system. To summarise here is what I have learned from this road-block:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;step away from the diagram;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;perspective can only be capitalised upon by making some space between yourself and the problem and then walking back towards it;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make like Andy Warhol, and iterate;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow for frustration time - cook on a medium heat and allow to simmer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next time&amp;hellip; P.s. I am leaving this note here because these diagrams need a glossary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here is the first iteration of the model:&lt;/strong&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-full&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/UML%20diagram%20IDM21.webp&#34; alt=&#34;A very blocky UML model where almost all of the actions are crammed into one container - a rooky mistake&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And here is the most recent, albeit not entirely finished:&lt;/strong&gt;
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-full&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/V2%20UML%20diagram%20IDM21.webp&#34; alt=&#34;A far clearer visual taxonomy has emerged in this version with clearer relatioships and separation between the different functions, example functions include: status, topics, progress&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version completed on 05/12/15&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-full&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/V5%20UML%20diagram%20IDM21.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Version 5 of the model shows user states including returning and forgotten password/username this is a far more accomplished map of the inner workings of the application using the block based structure of UML&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;British Standard. (2005). &lt;em&gt;BS ISO/IEC 19501:2005 Information technology. Open distributed processing. Unified modeling language (UML). Version 1.4.2.&lt;/em&gt; Retrieved from 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brown, D. M. (2010). &lt;em&gt;Communicating design: Developing web site documentation for design and planning (2nd edition) (voices that matter)&lt;/em&gt; (2nd ed.). Berkeley, CA: New Riders Publishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Griffiths, R. (2012, April 2). User conceptual modeling [Blog post]. Retrieved from 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lynch, P. J., &amp;amp; Horton, S. &lt;em&gt;Web style guide, Third edition&lt;/em&gt;. Retrieved from 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Redmond-Pyle, D., &amp;amp; Moore, A. (1995). &lt;em&gt;Graphical user interface design and evaluation (GUIDE): A practical process&lt;/em&gt; (1st ed.). New York: Prentice Hall Professional Technical Reference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
