<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ladies That Ux | Fiona MacNeill Portfolio and Blog</title>
    <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/tags/ladies-that-ux/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://fionamacneill.co.uk/tags/ladies-that-ux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Ladies That Ux</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 16:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/media/icon_hu4186623227307172452.png</url>
      <title>Ladies That Ux</title>
      <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/tags/ladies-that-ux/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overdue reflections: playing games and taking walks </title>
      <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/11/overdue-reflections/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/11/overdue-reflections/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;previously-on-fionas-blog&#34;&gt;Previously on Fiona&amp;rsquo;s blog&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help-version-2.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;My last post&lt;/a&gt; was immediately before trying out a new version of the &amp;lsquo;These UXers Need Help&amp;rsquo; game. This post follows that and reflects on a recent Design Walk I devised and led.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;todays-method-via-aristotle&#34;&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s method via Aristotle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Who, When, Where, &lt;em&gt;Because&lt;/em&gt;, What, How&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most designers have probably heard of the &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;five W&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;. They may or may not know of its origins in Aristotle&amp;rsquo;s book 3 of &lt;em&gt;Nicomachean Ethics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; as a set of seven circumstances to understand a situation. Newer translations of the text bring added clarity to the original intention of the thinking method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Therefore it is not a pointless endeavor to divide these circumstances by kind and number: (1) the who, (2) the what, (3) around what place or (4) in which time something happens,and sometimes (5) with what, such as an instrument, (6) for the sake of what, such as saving a life, and (7) the how, such as gently or violently&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Aristotle, &lt;em&gt;Eth. Nic.&lt;/em&gt; 1111a3–8, as translated by Sloan, 2010, p.239).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the &amp;ldquo;for the sake of&amp;rdquo; bit that interests me. When did it become &amp;lsquo;why&amp;rsquo;? Recently, while reading Indi Young&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Time to Listen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I realised that &amp;lsquo;why&amp;rsquo; is not the most decisive question when working on listening sessions. &amp;lsquo;Why&amp;rsquo; is that? Young posits that asking why does not help guide people to their inner reasoning and &amp;ldquo;interior cognition&amp;rdquo; (Young, pp. 128-179). She also notes, and I agree, that &amp;lsquo;why&amp;rsquo; can be irritating when repeated more than once in an interview or listening session. From my practice, I also know that when you work with people working in highly codified environments, and you ask a &amp;lsquo;why&amp;rsquo; question you are more likely to receive the organisations&amp;rsquo; reasoning not their own. So, in this post, I am experimenting with Indi&amp;rsquo;s suggestion to use &amp;lsquo;because&amp;rsquo; as a substitute for &amp;lsquo;why&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;these-uxers-need-help---version-20&#34;&gt;These UXers Need Help - version 2.0&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompts for the questions below are based on Curedale (2013, p.255)&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who&#34;&gt;Who&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;is involved?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UXup invited me to be part of their evening meetup on the 20th July 2023. There were about 25 people. The folks in the room are involved in different UX-related fields with a range of experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;is affected?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People in the room may have personal experience with some of the issues raised by the cards. This makes it essential to establish the rules of the gameplay early. For instance, different cards can be requested to replace the randomly drawn cards. Also, where personal experiences are shared, those who do not have those experiences listen to those who do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;needs the problem solved?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one level, this session took some of the runtime of the event. On a meta-level, it is a game to encourage and build empathy. A core capability for all designers of solutions for humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;when&#34;&gt;When&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;did it happen?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happened towards the end of the event, and we ran out of time. This meant we had one practice round as an entire room, followed by one independent round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;is the solution, this game, needed?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few possibilities are listed below.
When a group or team are&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip;about to embark on a fresh research project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip;trying to calibrate and get to know each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip;thinking about ways to give back to the UX community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;where&#34;&gt;Where&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;is the situation?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pump House pub was a great venue for the game as there were spacious tables to work with the cards and game sheets. Currently, the game is designed to be played in person. It would be easy enough to play over a web call using photos of the drawn cards from the deck or a randomising spreadsheet (as a way to prototype it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;because&#34;&gt;Because&amp;hellip;?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The raison d&amp;rsquo;etre&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To build empathy in an applied and fun way. This game is about considering the life surrounding your practice as a designer and how that life can sometimes make it hard to be a designer. The goal is to help players to become more attuned to the way that situations, personal talents, attitudes, attributes, skills, and power and set someone up for success or place barriers in front of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;For the sake of&amp;hellip;because?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is rooted in my personal set of values. I have a passion to do something about making sure design is both inclusive, introspective, and reflective on a continual path of improvement. I want to share this passion with others. I want them to be infected by my enthusiasm. &amp;lsquo;Because&amp;rsquo; ultimately, none of us are here for long, and if you find ways to help improve other people&amp;rsquo;s circumstances, what better legacy is there? You can achieve this through &amp;lsquo;design&amp;rsquo; by thinking about the design of everything you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what&#34;&gt;What&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more on the &amp;lsquo;what&amp;rsquo; check out my earlier blog posts about the game:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/04/ux-camp-brighton-game-on/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UX Camp Brighton 2023 - Game on! (9th April, 2023)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help-version-2.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;These UXers Need Help - Version 2.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;are its weaknesses?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, because the cards are open to interpretation, they can lead to a surface-level conversation when more depth is the goal.  To solve this, testing and removing cards that have to be explained or could be performing better is essential. I did like the situation card ‘is transitioning from one state of being to another’ as it was interpreted as the move from graduate school to work, which is an entirely valid situation to discuss. One which can be fraught and particularly challenging in the current jobs market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another weakness is that the game really does need two independent rounds to work. Due to the luck of the draw, having two rounds gives the opportunity to have a round that has greater depth or ambiguity. Having only one independent round means it is essential for a warm-up only. I will do this differently next time and ensure a minimum of 30 minutes is allocated. That was beyond the scope of this event, where only 20 mins was given. It was still a valid opportunity to user-test the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how&#34;&gt;How&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the most significant area for improvement. The way I displayed the game using my phone and a display adapter for the screen in the room did not work well. In future, I will either use an external webcam with my laptop or take a photo with my phone and share it with my laptop screen. In both approaches, a laptop with a display adaptor would work more consistently with a display screen in the room. This would also allow me to move around more freely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;closing-thoughts&#34;&gt;Closing thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to have had a chance to use the game with a group again. I was asked if I might consider extending the game at some point. The main thing would be to capture some of the suggested solutions for the scenarios. These could be taken forward as ideas or commitments. Devising solutions also relies on a mixture of experience in the group so that knowledge of available solutions is forthcoming. A more accessible version of the game might need to offer solution cards. For instance, ‘find a mentor’, ‘join a meetup group’, ‘attend a conference’, ‘ask for help on Slack’, ‘check out the latest design articles’, ‘find a career coach’, ‘speak to HR about career options’, etc. There is also a risk that solution cards could restrict the creativity of the suggestions provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/ux-trait-card-July2023%20copy.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;UX Trait cards - cards: they manage projects with finesse; they help people feel comfortable and okay during sensitive research; they facilitate meetings with purpos; they share and explain their tools methods and resources&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ladies-that-ux-design-walk&#34;&gt;Ladies that UX Design Walk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-1&#34;&gt;Who&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;is involved?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who opted to attend the first Ladies that UX Brighton walk. Some of these folks come to LTUX events regulary. Many were attending their first event. There was a mixture of ages from under 10s to folks over 60. Having such a group of interested people to walk and converse with was a rare privilege!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;is affected?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The walk did touch on sensitive topics, so it was important to let people know that at the beginning and to provide options for them to opt out of elements or leave early. Strangely, it was also the hottest day of the year, so that impacted all of us and the design that had to be adapted ad hoc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;needs the problem solved?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem was grounded in the disconnection you can feel as a designer working in a digital and built environment. How can we find inspiration amidst distractions? How can we find quiet in the noise? The walk was about sharing creative methods for perceiving and imagining our city in new ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;helped me?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing an activity for people absolutely has to involve people. So, I asked several folks for feedback. Their thoughts and feedback helped me to refine and iterate the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ellen Mueller&lt;/strong&gt;: Ellen’s artistic practice includes organising walks, and has just written a book, &lt;a href=&#34;https://sunypress.edu/Books/W/Walking-as-Artistic-Practice&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Walking as Artistic Practice&amp;rsquo; (2023)&lt;/a&gt;. My chat with Ellen helped me think about ways to design the walk to care about the walkers and demonstrate that care. Ellen&amp;rsquo;s work and &lt;a href=&#34;https://teaching.ellenmueller.com/walking/resources/books-readings/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this reading list on her website&lt;/a&gt; were the primary sources of inspiration for the walk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://ladiesthatux.notion.site/e8ee4a8da6ab403096c15aa48e14e6c7?v=d4603d5164354e858aa3cf068ab5f514&amp;amp;pvs=4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the reading list for the walk here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kate Shields&lt;/strong&gt;: chats with Kate about all things art and walking definitely informed the design. Having attended virtual role-playing-game walks led by Kate on Twitch, rambling through the environments of Assasin&amp;rsquo;s Creed, Kate&amp;rsquo;s artistic practice is a great source of inspiration. For more &lt;a href=&#34;https://kateshields.substack.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;check out Kate&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heidi Swigon&lt;/strong&gt;: early chats with Heidi gave me the confidence to believe that folks would sign up to spend a Saturday afternoon walking with me! Heidi&amp;rsquo;s enthusiasm for some of the topics I was planning was like rocket fuel for my creative process. Heidi also helped put together the accompanying zine, contributing the front cover and other design flourishes. The zine was given to each walker on the day. Heidi also took photos and helped to re-find people during an activity during the walk. Big gratitude!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suse Bentley&lt;/strong&gt;: provided a vital listening ear more than once. The first time, we talked about the intentional act of walking as women in urban environments. The second time was when I needed to sense check an aspect of the walk to ensure I was handling it from a position of interest and understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am immensely grateful to everyone who helped me think through and produce the walk design. A special thank you to Viv Cohen, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, something that fed into the walk design was the gentrification of walkable urbanism, the walkable city as designed by architects and city/town planners. I was particularly interested in how this concept relates to the ongoing redevelopment of The Level down to the sea front&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Walkable urbanism is oft conceptualised through architectural mock-ups featuring stylised female characters &amp;lsquo;walking&amp;rsquo; through these imagined future spaces, providing their seal of approval (Bieri, 2015 &amp;amp; 2017)&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Through their presence, these characters give a sub-conscious message: yes, this space is trendy; yes, this space is safe; no, this space is not for everyone, for if it were, it would not be trendy or safe. I am personally a huge fan of walkable cities, yet it is important to consider that those who benefit the most from walkability are those who can afford inner-city housing price tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;when-1&#34;&gt;When&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;did it happen?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
Rescheduled to the 9th of September from July. As a note, unseasonably, this was the hottest day of the year. At 2pm in the afternoon, it was also at the peak of the heat, reaching 33.2 degrees Celsius (91.8 degrees Fahrenheit)&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;is the solution needed?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
The walk was structured as a story with a series of interventions along a planned journey, starting at The Level and ending at the Laines in Brighton. The story was mapped to the spine structure that Ellen de Vries provided at her session on facilitation at Ladies that UX Brighton in May 2023. As outlined below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guidance/Intervention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encounter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transition/adrenaline push&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resolution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside the points above, I considered how the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.designcouncil.org.uk/our-resources/framework-for-innovation/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;design council&amp;rsquo;s double diamond&lt;/a&gt; could feed into this - as a researcher, it seems important to start with discovery. Yet, I also felt that we might need to complete some extra work to enable ourselves to become more open to discovery, and this is where a meditation exercise came in as an early addition to the walk. A mental cleanse of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;where-1&#34;&gt;Where&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-my-imagined-map-given-to-walkers-more-representative-of-my-own-internal-mental-model-than-a-physical-map-would-be&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A hand drawn map showing various locations in Brighton along The Level and the sea front&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/11/overdue-reflections/images/mapimage09092023_hu17423346154976758025.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/11/overdue-reflections/images/mapimage09092023_hu9787682084289514564.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/11/overdue-reflections/images/mapimage09092023_hu9096938696180662751.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/11/overdue-reflections/images/mapimage09092023_hu17423346154976758025.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;570&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      My imagined map given to walkers, more representative of my own internal mental model than a physical map would be.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Locations planned:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Union Road, The Level next to the skate park.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;North of St. Peter&amp;rsquo;s Church, York Place, The Level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;South of St. Peter&amp;rsquo;s Church, York Place, The Level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mazda Fountain, Victoria Gardens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Memorial to nothing, Victoria Gardens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Old Steine Gardens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disco Balls - Seafront next to OHSO Social.**&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subway next to Shelter Hall.**&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Middle Street.**&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ship Street Gardens.**&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;St. Bartholomew&amp;rsquo;s Road.**&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poole Valley.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Starred locations were skipped for reasons I&amp;rsquo;ll explain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;is the situation?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
The heat and busyness of Brighton made it difficult to walk at speed, and being outside was unpredictable. For instance, at the &amp;lsquo;memorial to nothing&amp;rsquo; location, the remnants of a dead bird were scattered around it making it sad and unpleasant to stay there. We acknowledged the bird and the unpredictable nature of walking outdoors and moved on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;because-1&#34;&gt;Because&amp;hellip;?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The raison d&amp;rsquo;etre&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
To explore our city as designers together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;For the sake of&amp;hellip;because?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
I had a drive to share things I had discovered about our city by walking and running around it during the pandemic. Something that I have continued to do. This city has the capacity to provide neverending intrigue and wonder. It is constantly changing and evolving. For me, a big part of Brighton’s design is the people in it and their performative individuality; the unique clothing styles, mannerisms, and theatre of it all that I find endlessly intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-1&#34;&gt;What&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;are its weaknesses?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
I tried to pack too much into the walk, and this was exacerbated by the extreme heat which meant we had to find different places to stand together. Next time I would plan half the stops we had planned in the zine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What attendees said in the event feedback:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suggested an extended event starting in the morning, breaking for lunch, and continuing into the afternoon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A more focused narrative, such as focusing on specific design choices and changes over time, or accessibility and inclusivity (this is definitely a walk I&amp;rsquo;d like to do in the future!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checking for other events that are on at the same time. As we had to change the date, this was always going to be a risk and there is always a lot going on in Brighton. A funfair on The Level and a competition in the Skate Park proved challenging at the beginning of the event - it made it hard to find people and was loud.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They liked&amp;hellip;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The high level of preparation and organisation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rich discussions and variety of perspectives brought by fellow walkers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For a time, it changed their perception of their surroundings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The zine and accompanying reading list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The free gelato and art materials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;was unexpected?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
A group of young men decided to join our group near St. Peter&amp;rsquo;s church and listened to what I had to say. When I asked them if I could help, they asked if they could join our protest. It is interesting that a group of less than twelve, majority women, walking along a street was perceived as a protest. But then context is everything; The Level has a long history of public assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-1&#34;&gt;How&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did foresee that we might run out of time, so I built a real-world cheat code by planning a lane that allowed us to skip multiple stops and go to the end - Boho Gelato in the Poole Valley. This was an excellent plan, and I will continue to think about how role-playing games can provide inspiration across my creative practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;closing-thoughts-1&#34;&gt;Closing thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot by pushing myself out of my comfort zone for this walk, and I will definitely plan walks again. A realisation for me is how hard it is to plan an event in space, time, and motion. I am experienced in &amp;ldquo;space&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;time&amp;rdquo; due to my many years of teaching and running workshops, but traversing space over a set period of time definitely adds complication. Also, giving people time to explore an area independently and then regroup is nerve-wracking. I feared that we would not find each other again, and if it hadn&amp;rsquo;t been for Heidi&amp;rsquo;s help gathering people, we might not have. The bright pink bags with our art materials definitely helped - the whole tour guide thing of all having the same hat or backpack makes total sense!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big thank you to all those who attended the event and contributed feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-photo-by-deeksha-bhusan&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;An gelato in a tub with a spoon held up in front of the Boho Gelato shop front in the Poole Valley, Brighton&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/11/overdue-reflections/images/gelatoBrighton_hu3020362555727438274.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/11/overdue-reflections/images/gelatoBrighton_hu6418175485095250525.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/11/overdue-reflections/images/gelatoBrighton_hu8007787256140156424.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/11/overdue-reflections/images/gelatoBrighton_hu3020362555727438274.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;570&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Photo by Deeksha Bhusan.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sloan, M.C. (2010) &amp;lsquo;Aristotle’s Nicomachean Ethics as the Original Locus for the Septem Circumstantiae&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;Classical Philology&lt;/em&gt;, volume 105/3. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1086/656196&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1086/656196&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1086/656196&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF available at Academia.ed&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young, I. (2022) &lt;em&gt;Time to listen - How giving people space to speak drives invention and inclusion&lt;/em&gt;. USA: Indi Young Books.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curedale, R. (2013) &lt;em&gt;Service Design - 250 essential methods&lt;/em&gt;. CA: Design Community College Inc.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brighton-hove.gov.uk/news/2022/plans-final-phase-valley-gardens-press-forward&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Valley Gardens Redevelopment&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anja Hälg Bieri&amp;rsquo;s work was part of this amazing book I found in the research process, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.routledge.com/The-Routledge-International-Handbook-of-Walking/Hall-Ram-Shoval/p/book/9781032339542&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hall, C. M., Ram, Y., Shoval, N. (Eds.)&lt;em&gt;The Routledge International Handbook of Walking&lt;/em&gt; (2018)&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;British heatwave brings hottest day of 2023 so far&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;Reuters&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/world/uk/uk-records-hottest-day-year-so-far-met-office-2023-09-09/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Available at the Reuters website&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>These UXers Need Help - Version 2.0</title>
      <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 17:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;previously-on-fionas-blog&#34;&gt;Previously on Fiona&amp;rsquo;s blog&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created a game for UX Camp Brighton (9th April, 2023) designed to encourage reflection on power and social capital in UX. As I outlined in &lt;a href=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/04/ux-camp-brighton-game-on/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;my last blog post&lt;/a&gt;, some people enter UX with more power, some with less. My goal with the game was to encourage players to recognise opportunities and challenges, both overt and implicit and consider ways that we, as a community of designers, can help (if we can help!). The game was losely inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cardsagainsthumanity.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cards Against Humanity&lt;/a&gt; and has a four deck structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-did-it-go&#34;&gt;How did it go?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The playtest at UX Camp Brighton went well and the response to the game was far more positive than I anticipated. There was at least one person saying &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;these cards are like my life last year&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I liked about the experience was that in the span of 15 minutes we could break through the artifice of &lt;em&gt;&amp;rsquo;the designer&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;. Spending time reflecting on the fact that we are all real people with real problems and sometimes those things impact &lt;em&gt;&amp;rsquo;the designer&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, preventing us from doing our best work. In those times we may or may not need help, but experience is sometimes the thing we lack to access help or to help ourselves. That is where the experience &amp;lsquo;in the room&amp;rsquo; that the game unlocks can help us all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s also humour sprinkled through the game and I loved that the &amp;ldquo;has a landlord who is a 💩&amp;rdquo; card came up! This is definitely an identifiable experience for those in the rental market and added some levity to the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, folks liked the game enough for me to be invited to this month&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/uxup-summer-tickets-638632094787?aff=ebdsoporgprofile&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UXup on 20th July&lt;/a&gt; to play the game again. So, it&amp;rsquo;s time for Version 2.0 🎉, more on this in &lt;a href=&#34;#how-about-those-cards-then&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How about those cards then&amp;hellip;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-studio-action-shot---creating-new-situation-cards-for-version-20&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Desk with in-progress hand-drawn cards for &amp;lsquo;These UXers need help&amp;rsquo; on the surface&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/StudioWorkOnNewCards-July2023_hu15603715447926831359.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/StudioWorkOnNewCards-July2023_hu5452410757399018035.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/StudioWorkOnNewCards-July2023_hu9058367740732236880.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/StudioWorkOnNewCards-July2023_hu15603715447926831359.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Studio action shot - creating new situation cards for version 2.0
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-does-the-game-work&#34;&gt;How does the game work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;flex px-4 py-3 mb-6 rounded-md bg-primary-100 dark:bg-primary-900&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;pr-3 pt-1 text-primary-600 dark:text-primary-300&#34;&gt;
  &lt;svg height=&#34;24&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 24 24&#34;&gt;&lt;path fill=&#34;none&#34; stroke=&#34;currentColor&#34; stroke-linecap=&#34;round&#34; stroke-linejoin=&#34;round&#34; stroke-width=&#34;1.5&#34; d=&#34;m11.25 11.25l.041-.02a.75.75 0 0 1 1.063.852l-.708 2.836a.75.75 0 0 0 1.063.853l.041-.021M21 12a9 9 0 1 1-18 0a9 9 0 0 1 18 0m-9-3.75h.008v.008H12z&#34;/&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;dark:text-neutral-300&#34;&gt;This is the version 2.0 overview - I&amp;rsquo;ll undoubtedly refine it further.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four cards placed on the game sheet create two sentences which describe a fictional UXer. The friction created between the two sentences and the concepts within them are designed to stimulate conversation. The game probes the fascade of being a designer and is about helping us to empathise with factors that are internal and external to a person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deck 1: Situation&lt;/strong&gt; - this is how much power the fictional UXer brings to this situation. This could be a positive, neutral, or negative value. For example, positive could be &amp;ldquo;they know influential people&amp;rdquo;, negative would be that &amp;ldquo;they grew up in a poor family&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deck 2: Subject&lt;/strong&gt; - this is &amp;lsquo;subject&amp;rsquo; as in subjectivity of a UXer. Again this could be a positive, neutral or negative. So neutral could be &amp;ldquo;is a boxset binger&amp;rdquo; and negative could be, &amp;ldquo;is a solutioniser&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deck 3: UX Trait&lt;/strong&gt; - this is the thing that they do in UX. However, it is not all kittens and puppies, sometimes they aren&amp;rsquo;t happy in their field or are unsure of what to do next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deck 4: Barrier&lt;/strong&gt; - this is something that is preventing them from being the best they can be. For example, they &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t have a portfolio&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;have very little money&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-play&#34;&gt;How to play&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take one card from each deck: situation, subject, UX trait, and barrier. Place the cards face down on the game sheet in the spaces provided. Flip all four cards and then allow 5 minutes to discuss the person&amp;rsquo;s situation (in a group of 3-5), what type of help might be needed and who will provide it. You may draw a replacement card if needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rules-of-engagement&#34;&gt;Rules of Engagement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make your point concisely and then leave space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If someone in your group has lived experience, listen to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imagine how it would be to be this person who is a UXer (referring to our fictional UXer).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-about-those-cards-then&#34;&gt;How about those cards then&amp;hellip;?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cards-added-to-the-situation-deck&#34;&gt;Cards added to the &lt;strong&gt;Situation&lt;/strong&gt; deck&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following cards were inspired by discussions with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/verdenicci/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Serena Verdenicci&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/louvcarroll/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Lou Carroll&lt;/a&gt;. Serena is also giving a talk entitled, &lt;em&gt;Making your value visible&lt;/em&gt; at UXup on the 20th July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New cards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Grew up in a poor family&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Knows influential people&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Is managing a longterm illness&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Is using technology to aid their mobility&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; - this could be interpretted in many ways and is about emphasising capability rather than disability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Observes religious traditions&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We considered how the above factors might give people power or set them apart from others working in different design settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also added a card inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/uxmichaelco/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Michael Kibedi&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; phenomenal talk during UX Camp Brighton about problems with representation in datasets and the exploitation of labour in the global South supporting technologies such as AI and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mturk.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;mechanical turk&lt;/a&gt;. Specifically I was inspired by a map Michael showed where the language datasets for verbal interpretation used by voice assistants come from (e.g., Alexa, Siri). Based on this map, it was clear that these datasets were what might be termed &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apa.org/monitor/2010/05/weird&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WEIRD&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; – &lt;em&gt;Western, Educated, Industrialised, Rich, and Democratic&lt;/em&gt;. You can read more about Michael&amp;rsquo;s research on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uxmichael.co/project/voice-assistant-accent-bias&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;voice assistants and accent bias&amp;rdquo; at his website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New card&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Has a strong accent when speaking&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This spoken accent could be regional, international, or a unique hybrid as my accent was for many years. When I first moved back to the UK, people used to tell me my accent was distracting during workshops because they couldn&amp;rsquo;t place it (it had a North American twang). That made me pretty self-conscious and I resolved to sound more &amp;ldquo;Sussex&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I have had periodic issues with my voice for health reasons and this has made me appreciate all the more how important both having a voice and &lt;em&gt;having&lt;/em&gt; a voice are. Sometimes I don&amp;rsquo;t have much voice and as someone who likes to think a lot and then talk about my thoughts, it has been a source of frustration. To the extent that I once had an existential nightmare about being in someone else&amp;rsquo;s house with an Amazon Echo that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t speak to tell it to stop an alarm that was incessantly going off. It turned out that the sound in my dream was my actual voice assistant invading my REM sleep. Good fodder for an episode of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-66200334&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Charlie Brooker&amp;rsquo;s Black Mirror&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another source of inspiration for me was Trans Pride Brighton &amp;amp; Hove on Saturday, 16th July. When creating the cards I avoid using terminology and focus on what is going on for a person. The cards are also written to leave room for interpretation and that is both subjective and guided by the rest of the cards put down. So, I added the following cards and we&amp;rsquo;ll see how well they work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New cards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Is transitioning from one state of being to another&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Has a hidden identity&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add, Trans Pride Brighton &amp;amp; Hove are very much in need of support this year. So if you can help, &lt;a href=&#34;https://transpridebrighton.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;chip in to their fund at their site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, based on discussions I have had more broadly and UK news I added the following cards&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New cards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Has been made redundant&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; - inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;https://bootcamp.uxdesign.cc/whats-with-ux-research-layoffs-12c9d1fcf111&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this article on Medium by Jacqualyn Heth&lt;/a&gt; with regards to user research roles, but also a trend more broadly in tech.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Has exorbitant mortgage payments&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; - I realised I was only representing renters, and with the current interest rates, it is no walk in the park for homeowners either!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-new-situation-cards-that-will-be-tested-out-at-uxup-and-beyond&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;New Situation cards described in the text above&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/situation-cards-July2023_hu16439747338950367434.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/situation-cards-July2023_hu9003669930572965202.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/situation-cards-July2023_hu1183660955067304430.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/situation-cards-July2023_hu16439747338950367434.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      New situation cards that will be tested out at UXup and beyond
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;card-added-to-the-subject-deck&#34;&gt;Card added to the &lt;strong&gt;Subject&lt;/strong&gt; deck&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the &amp;ldquo;Accessible Forms&amp;rdquo; workshop that Ladies that UX Brighton had with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.effortmark.co.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Caroline Jarratt&lt;/a&gt; and Meghan Reed from &lt;a href=&#34;https://diversityandability.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Diversity and Ability&lt;/a&gt; in March, I rreflected on the impact that having a disability might have on doing UX work. There are so many experiences I could try to represent and such attempts could be viewed as reductive. I will take suggestions from people with lived experience, but I&amp;rsquo;m not going to try to speculate. In that vein, I have drawn on my own experience in that I can find it very hard to make eye contact with people whom I don&amp;rsquo;t know very well. This is something I have to actively think about when I meet someone new and consider &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;am I making enough or too much?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Do people think I&amp;rsquo;m too intense?&lt;/em&gt;. All these things run through my mind. It is all the more important when you are building trust during research. It isn&amp;rsquo;t easy and it has taken years of practice. Ultimately, I try to convey that I really care and I am genuinely interested through my eyes, because I truly am. I am also thankful for web calls where I don&amp;rsquo;t have this problem and can focus on the task of deep listening. This made me think that the following is a good card to add&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New card&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;can find it hard to make eye contact&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-new-subject-card-for-making-eye-contact&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;New Subject card described in the text above&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/subject-card-July2023_hu7470874530185881868.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/subject-card-July2023_hu7476996878649953868.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/subject-card-July2023_hu4683675281643390975.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/subject-card-July2023_hu7470874530185881868.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;450&#34;
               height=&#34;600&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      New subject card for making eye contact
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cards-in-the-ux-trait-deck&#34;&gt;Cards in the &lt;strong&gt;UX Trait&lt;/strong&gt; deck&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the playtest at UX Camp Brighton, I removed one card: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;They are an experience designer with emotional cloud&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. The card required a bit too much explanation and similar themes are covered by other cards in the deck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New cards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;They manage meetings with finesse&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; - I realised that I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a good project management card and it is such a core skill in design (and beyond).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;They facilitate meetings with purpose&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; - Inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.peterwinchester.co.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Peter Winchester&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Facilitation Fundamentals&lt;/em&gt; talk at UX Camp Brighton.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;They help people feel comfortable and okay during sensitive research&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; - inspired by Charlotte Parker&amp;rsquo;s talk &lt;em&gt;How to handle difficult situations in User Research&lt;/em&gt; and Lou Carroll&amp;rsquo;s talk on co-design, both at UX Camp Brighton.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;They share and explain their tools, methods, and resources&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; - inspired by Aaron Cameron&amp;rsquo;s talk &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Democratising Human-Centred Design&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; also at UX Camp Brighton.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-new-ux-trait-cards&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;New UX Trait cards described in the text above&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/ux-trait-card-July2023_hu3291046453624267637.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/ux-trait-card-July2023_hu7943134916643807312.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/ux-trait-card-July2023_hu579047236684706828.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/ux-trait-card-July2023_hu3291046453624267637.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      New UX Trait cards
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cards-added-to-the-barrier-deck&#34;&gt;Cards added to the &lt;strong&gt;Barrier&lt;/strong&gt; deck&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two new cards are inspired by AI. I am generally pro-AI but it is not without it&amp;rsquo;s foibles and I felt it was important to represent some of the understandable anxiety and also the downsides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New cards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;is worried about being replaced by AI&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;hellip;takes information at face value without checking it&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having had amazing discussions in preparation for a discussion panel for Ladies that UX Brighton later in the year on &amp;lsquo;fem-coded&amp;rsquo; work and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2022/may/09/they-feel-guilty-why-women-should-say-no-to-office-housework&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;non-promotable work&lt;/a&gt;. I added a couple of cards to help think about these types of tasks and how they might have an impact over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New cards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;always end up writing the meeting notes&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;they&amp;rsquo;ll only blame themselves&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;handles all the leaving cards and gifts&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-new-barrier-cards&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;New Barrier cards described in the text above&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/barrier-card-July2023_hu9151054866723809993.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/barrier-card-July2023_hu11397865665750429692.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/barrier-card-July2023_hu6556066273068473953.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/07/these-uxers-need-help---version-2.0/images/barrier-card-July2023_hu9151054866723809993.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      New Barrier cards
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is version 2.0 with a rationale for each addition. Let&amp;rsquo;s see how it plays out!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UX Camp Brighton 2023 - Game on!</title>
      <link>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/04/ux-camp-brighton-game-on/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 18:50:06 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/04/ux-camp-brighton-game-on/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;today-is-ux-camp-brighton&#34;&gt;Today is UX Camp Brighton!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is is 6.30am on the day of UX Camp Brighton 2023, one of my favourite days of the year! It is also the event&amp;rsquo;s 10th anniversary. I starting attending back in 2014; we go back a long way. Check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uxcampbrighton.org/history&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UX Camp Brighton&amp;rsquo;s history page&lt;/a&gt; for a flavour - I just noticed that I am on there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-ux-camp-brighton&#34;&gt;What is UX Camp Brighton?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BarCamp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BarCamp style&lt;/a&gt; event where anyone can present on a topic related to UX for 20 minutes. In the morning you are given an index card and you add your presentation title and description and put it up in a grid which indicates which room you will use. You then provide a verbal pitch to convince people to attend. I always try to generate some humour with my titles, last year&amp;rsquo;s title was: &lt;em&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s talk about LX maybe, lets talk about you and me&lt;/em&gt; (refer to Salt-N-Peppa&amp;rsquo;s seminal 1989 album &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blacks%27_Magic&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blacks&amp;rsquo; Magic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-do-i-love-ux-camp-brighton&#34;&gt;Why do I love UX Camp Brighton?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year I get to meet such amazing designers including people who are new to design and people who have years or experience. I also have design friends who I only see at this event and every year I catch-up with how they are doing and what they are working on. In short I learn a lot about what is going on in design in a short period of time and I have boatloads of fun doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-do-i-do-at-ux-camp-brighton&#34;&gt;What do I do at UX Camp Brighton?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year I attend I tend to host a session myself. Last year my friend Lou encouraged me to be brave and present in the biggest lexture hall type room. That was great and worked well as it was a slide-based presentation. However, although the session was good upon reflection afterwards I felt like I tried to pack too much in content and theory-wise (for more - check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2022/04/ux-camp-brighton-sticking-power/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;my post about last year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-am-i-doing-instead-this-year&#34;&gt;What am I doing instead this year?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of my presentations are strangely inspired by short conversations with one of the UX Camp Brighton organisers &lt;a href=&#34;https://uk.linkedin.com/in/hayluke&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Luke Hay&lt;/a&gt;, this year is no different. Luke said &amp;ldquo;why don&amp;rsquo;t you do something about &lt;a href=&#34;https://ladiesthatux.com/brighton/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ladies that UX Brighton?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;. I thought about this and also ruminated on what I had heard a couple of times when I first started to volunteer for Ladies that UX (LTUX). Some folks had queried, and to note there is never anything wrong with a bit of constructive enquiry, why groups like LTUX are still needed? This is a valid point given that LTUX was &lt;a href=&#34;https://ladiesthatux.com/about/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;founded in 2013 in Manchester&lt;/a&gt;, when speaking from experience as a woman or non-male person you&amp;rsquo;d find yourself looking around the room at tech conferences to find the two handfuls of people who were also not male. Representation for women in UX is far more healthy - a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zippia.com/user-experience-designer-jobs/demographics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;recent survey by Zippia&lt;/a&gt; estimating that in the United States 40.4% of UX designers are women and 59.6% are men. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://measuringu.com/salary-survey2022/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2022 UXPA survey as analysed by MeasuringU&lt;/a&gt; also points towards the fact that salary equality is on the rise in UX, with women earning slightly more than men in the 5 to 7 year experience bracket (data is United States-centric as only 9% of responses are from the UK).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-according-to-uxpa-in-2022-salaries-were-at-the-same-level-across-male-and-female-genders-in-2022&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Bar chart showing that salaries for men and women were equal in UX in 2022&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2023/04/ux-camp-brighton-game-on/images/MedianSalaryByGender_hu13721310628434127772.webp 400w,
               /post/2023/04/ux-camp-brighton-game-on/images/MedianSalaryByGender_hu6892823359747270884.webp 760w,
               /post/2023/04/ux-camp-brighton-game-on/images/MedianSalaryByGender_hu15631320791414348530.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2023/04/ux-camp-brighton-game-on/images/MedianSalaryByGender_hu13721310628434127772.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      According to UXPA in 2022, salaries were at the same level across male and female genders in 2022.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to be careful with this as history tells us that when work get associated with people who are not male, the pay goes down. To provide a quick example, take the pay differential between people working in customer service-related IT versus those in more technical roles (e.g., development, desktop systems). Even when men are in customer service roles this work is fem-coded and is usually paid less. I am just planting the seed of this idea in this post for now as I hope we can have a discussion panel on this in future at LTUX Brighton. In the meantime check out these fantastic resources which have been educating me on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work of &lt;a href=&#34;https://marhicks.com/writing.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mar Hicks&lt;/a&gt;, specifically her book &lt;a href=&#34;https://programmedinequality.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Programmed Inequality: How Britain Discarded Women Technologists and Lost Its Edge In Computing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daley Wilhelm&amp;rsquo;s recent article on Medium, &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/user-experience-design-1/why-are-women-encouraged-to-go-into-ux-d8765992509d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why are women encouraged to go into UX?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talks given by &lt;a href=&#34;https://hachyderm.io/@intentionaut&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Saielle DaSilva&lt;/a&gt;, as quoted by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fionamacneill.co.uk/post/2022/11/uxbrighton-0411/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Matt LeMay at UX Brighton&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;get-to-the-point-fiona&#34;&gt;Get to the point Fiona&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I have designed a game to playtest. The game encourages reflection on power and social capital in UX. Some people enter UX with more power automatically, some with less. How can we help within the community to not only level the playing field but start the race from the same starter mark on &amp;lsquo;said&amp;rsquo; field? The game is losely inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cardsagainsthumanity.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cards Against Humanity&lt;/a&gt;, but has a four deck structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cards create two sentences which describe a fictional UXer. The friction created between the two sentences and the concepts within them is designed to stimulate conversation. The game probes the facade of being a designer and is about helping us to empathise with struggles which are internal and external to a person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deck 1: Situation&lt;/strong&gt; - this is how much power you bring to this situation. This could be a positive, neutral or negative value. For example, positive could be you know influential people, negative would be that you grew up in a poor family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deck 2: Subject&lt;/strong&gt; - this is &amp;lsquo;subject&amp;rsquo; as in subjectivity of a UXer . Again this could be a positive, neutral or negative. So neutral could be &amp;ldquo;is a boxset binger&amp;rdquo; and negative could be, &amp;ldquo;is a solutioniser&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deck 3: UX Trait&lt;/strong&gt; - this is the thing that they do in UX, or want to do in UX. However, it is all not all kittens and puppies, sometimes they aren&amp;rsquo;t happy in their field or are unsure of what to do next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deck 4: Barrier&lt;/strong&gt; - this is something that is preventing them from being the best they can be. For example, they &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t have a portfolio&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;have very little money&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all for now, but I want to take a moment to cite my inspirations for the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more on power dynamics and UX check this month&amp;rsquo;s LTUX UX Book Club book, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.beyondstickynotes.com/what-is-codesign&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beyond Sticky Notes: Co-design for Real: Mindsets, methods and movements&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Kelly Ann McKercher (if you would like to come to book club on Weds 26th April, you can sign-up on Eventbrite).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Sauro, &lt;a href=&#34;https://measuringu.com/brand-affinity-sentiment/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How to Assess Brand Affinity &amp;amp; Sentiment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony Dunne and Fiona Raby&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speculative_design&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;speculative design practice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruben Pater, &lt;a href=&#34;http://thepoliticsofdesign.com/about-the-book&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Politics of Design&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.eu/d/fZvdYlz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The blank poker cards&lt;/a&gt; I bought and then hand drew to create this game!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
